<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <array name="it301">
        <item>SAD</item>
        <item>Reference Books: \n\n 1. Eric J. Braude , Software Design, John Wiley and Sons.\n
            2. Erich Gamma, Richard Helm, Ralph Johnson, and John Vlissides : Design Patterns:
            Elements of Reusable Object-Oriented Software, Addison – Wesley 1994\n
            3. James Rumbaugh, Object Oriented Modeling and Design, Prentice Hall India\n
            4. Len Bass, Paul Clements, Rick Kazman, Software Architecture in Practice (2nd Ed.),
            Pearson\n
            5. Mary Shaw and David Garlan, Software Architecture – Perspectives on an emerging
            discipline, Pearson, 1996\n
            6. Roger S.Pressman, Software Engineering – A Practitioner’s approach, 8th
            edition(2014), McGraw Hill Education
        </item>
        <item>3-1-0 - 4</item>
        <item>Nil</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>The Nature of Software – Defining software, Software Application domains. Software
            Engineering. The Software Process, Process Models: - Water fall model, Incremental
            model, Prototyping model, RAD, Spiral model and Agile Development. (Brief introduction
            of Agile Development). What is Software Architecture? Why is software architecture
            important? Role of software architect.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Software Design principles – Correctness and Robustness – Flexibility, Reusability and
            Efficiency – Tradeoffs among robustness, flexibility, reusability and efficiency
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to UML diagrams – Use case diagrams, Class diagrams, Sequence diagrams,
            Activity diagrams, State Transition diagram, Deployment diagram.
            Case study discussion on UML diagrams – Group presentation by students on different case
            studies
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Software architectural styles - pipes and filters, layered, eventbased, data-centered,
            interpreter, MVC, message dispatcher, multi-tier distributed
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>What is a design pattern? Creational patterns – Factory, Abstract Factory, Prototype
            and Singleton. Structural patterns – Composite, Decorator, Adapter, Façade and
            Flyweight. s
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Behavioral patterns- Chain of responsibility, Command, Interpreter, Mediator, State,
            Template and Observer. Evaluation of architectural design - ATAM
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it302">
        <item>IT</item>
        <item>TEXT BOOK \n\n1. Paul J. Deitel, Harvey M. Deitel, Abbey Deitel, “Internet and World
            Wide Web How To Program”, 5/E, Pearson Education, 2012.

            \n\nREFERENCES \n\n1. Robert W. Sebesta, “Programming the World Wide Web”, 8/E, Pearson
            Education, 2012.
            \n2. Chris Bates, “Web Programming – Building Intranet applications”, Wiley
            Publications, 3rd Edition, 2009.
            \n3. Jonathan Chaffer, Karl Swedberg, “Learning jQuery: Better interaction Design and
            Web Development with Simple JavaScript Techniques”, PACKT publishing, 2007
            \n4. www.w3schools.com
        </item>
        <item>4-0-0-4</item>
        <item>Nil</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>mIntroduction to Computers and the Internet- Web Basics, Introduction to HTML5 - W3C
            HTML5 Validation Service, Headings, Linking, Images, Special Characters and Horizontal
            Rules, Lists, Tables, Forms, Internal Linking, meta elements, New HTML5 Form input
            Types, input and data list elements and autocomplete Attribute, Page-Structure Elements.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Cascading Style Sheets -Inline Styles, Embedded Style Sheets,
            Conflicting Styles, Linking External Style Sheets, Positioning Elements - Absolute
            Positioning, zindex, Relative Positioning, span, Backgrounds, Element Dimensions, Box
            Model and Text Flow, Media Types, DropDown Menus
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>JavaScript: Introduction to Scripting - Control Statements - if Selection Statement,
            if…else Selection Statement, while Repetition Statement, for Repetition Statement,
            switch Multiple-Selection Statement, do…while Repetition Statement, break and continue
            Statements, JavaScript: Functions- Function Definitions, Random Number Generation,
            JavaScript Global Functions, JavaScript: Arrays - Declaring, Allocating and Using
            Arrays, Passing Arrays to Functions, Sorting Arrays with sort, Searching Arrays with
            index Of, JavaScript: Objects: Math, String, Date, Boolean and Number, document Object.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Document Object Model (DOM): Modeling a Document: DOM Nodes and Trees, Traversing and
            Modifying a DOM Tree, DOM Collections, Dynamic Styles, Using a Timer and Dynamic Styles
            to Create Animated Effects, JavaScript Event Handling: load Event, Event mouse move and
            the event Object, Form Processing with focus and blur, submit and reset, Event Bubbling
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>XML: Introduction, XML Basics, Structuring Data, XML Namespaces, Document Type
            Definitions (DTDs), W3C XML Schema Documents, XML Vocabularies: MathML, Extensible Style
            sheet Language and XSL Transformations, Document Object Model (DOM). Ajax-Enabled Rich
            Internet Applications with XML and JSON: Introduction, Rich Internet Applications (RIAs)
            with Ajax, Using XML and the DOM , Creating a FullScale Ajax-Enabled Applicatio
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Web Servers: Introduction, HTTP Transactions, Multitier Application Architecture,
            Client-Side Scripting versus ServerSide Scripting, Accessing Web Servers.
            Server Side Programming with PHP - Introduction, converting Between Data Types,
            Arithmetic Operators, Initializing and Manipulating Arrays, String Comparisons, String
            Processing with Regular Expressions, Form Processing and Business Logic, Using PHP to
            Process HTML5 Forms, Accessing MySQL Database with PHP, Using Cookies, Dynamic Content
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it303">
        <item>TOC</item>
        <item>Text Book: \n\n1. Hopcroft J. E., J. D. Ullman and R. Motwani, Introduction to
            Automata Theory, Languages and Computation, Pearson Education, 2008
            \n2. Misra and Chandrasekharan, Theory of Computation, Prentice Hall
            \n\nReferences: \n\n1. John Martin, Introduction to Language and Theory of Computation,
            TMH
            \n2. K.V.N. Sunitha and N Kalyani, Formal languages and Automata Theory Tata McGraw
            Hill, NewDelhi
            \n3. Michael Sipser, Introduction to the Theory of Computation, Thomson Learning
            \n4. Moret B. M., The Theory of Computation, Pearson Education
            \n5. Peter Linz, An Introduction to Formal Languages and Automata Narosa Publucation
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>Nil</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction: Formal representation of languages – Chomsky Classification,
            Introduction to Automata theory, Alphabets and Languages, language operations:
            Concatenation, sub string Kleene closure, Reversal, Finite state systems, Transition
            diagram and table
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Finite automata, Finite state automata – description of finite automata, language
            acceptability, designing finite automata, NFA, . Difference between NFAandDFA finite
            automata with epsilon moves, equivalence of NFA and DFA –Conversion of NFA to DFA -
            Minimisation of DFA-, Applications of finite automata, , Finite Automata with output.
            Moore and Meelay Machines.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Regular Expressions – Properties of Regular sets , Ardens theoremDFA to Regular
            Expressions conversion,DFA construction for given regular expression ,Pumping Lemma ,
            closure properties.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Context Free Grammar – Derivation trees, ambiguity, simplification of CFLs, normal
            forms of CFGs: Chomsky and Greibach NFs. PDA – formal definition, examples of PDA, ,
            language acceptability ,Deterministic PDA. Pumping lemma for CFGs. Applications of PDA
            and CFLs
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Turing machines - Chomsky classification of languages, formal definition of Turing
            Machine, language acceptability by TM, examples of TM. Variants of TMs – multitape TM,
            multiple tracks ,checking off symbols , Subroutines, Non-deterministic TM, offline TMs,
            Universal Turing Machine, equivalence of single tape and multitape TMs.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Linear bounded automata, Recursive and recursively enumerable languages – properties
            recursive and r.e. languages. Decidability - decidable and undecidable problems,
            tractable and intractable problems, halting problem, reducibility. Church Thesis
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it304">
        <item>DWM</item>
        <item>Text Book: \n\n1. Jaiwei Han, Micheline Kamber, “Data Mining Concepts and Techniques”,
            Elsevier, 2006.
            \n2. M. Sudeep Elayidom, “Data Mining and Warehousing”, 1st Edition, 2015 Cengage
            Learning India Pvt. Ltd.
            \n\nReferences: \n\n1. Pang-Ning Tan, Michael Steinbach, “Introduction to Data Mining”,
            Addison Wesley, 2006.
            \n2. Dunham M H, “Data Mining: Introductory and Advanced Topics”, Pearson Education, New
            Delhi, 2003.
            \n3. Mehmed Kantardzic, “Data Mining Concepts, Methods and Algorithms”, John Wiley and
            Sons, USA, 2003.
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>CS208 Principles of data base design</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Data Mining: Concepts: Concepts, Data Mining Applications, Data Mining Stages, Data
            Mining Models, Data Warehousing and OLAP, Need for Data Warehousing, Challenges,
            Application of Data Mining Principles, Machine Learning and Statistics, Ethics of Data
            Mining, Popular Tools. OLTP Vs DWH, Applications of DWH
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Data Preprocessing: Data Preprocessing Concepts, Data Cleaning, Handling Missing Data,
            Data Transformation and Discretization, Data Visualization. UCI Data Sets and Their
            Significance
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Classification Models: Introduction to Classification Models, Decision Tree, Neural
            Networks
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Naive Bayes Classifier, Support Vector Machines. Prediction Models, Issues regarding
            classification and prediction.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Association Rules Mining: Concepts, Apriori Algorithm. Cluster Analysis: Introduction,
            Concepts, K-Means Clustering, DensityBased Clustering, Weighted Graph Partitioning,
            Hypergraph Partitioning,
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Practical Data Mining Tools: Weka, R Package for Data Mining. Advanced Data Mining
            Techniques: Introduction, Web Mining- Web Content Mining, Web Structure Mining, Web
            Usage Mining. Text Mining, CRM Applications and Data Mining, CRM Data Mining Models.
            Data Warehousing with Oracle BI
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it305">
        <item>OS</item>
        <item>Text Books: \n\n1. Andrew S. Tanenbaum, “Modern Operating Systems”, Prentice Hall
            \n2. J. L. Peterson and A. Silberschatz , Operating System Concepts, Addison Wesley.
            \n\nReferences: \n\n1. D M Dhamdhere, “Operating Systems A Concept-based Approach”, Tata
            McGraw Hill, New Delhi, 2nd Edition, 2010.
            \n2. William Stallings, Operating Systems,6th Edition,Pearson,2009,ISBN
            978-81-317-2528-3
            \n3. Garry Nutt, “Operating Systems – A Modern perspective ”, Third Edition, Pearson
            Education
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0:3</item>
        <item>C202 Computer Organization and Architecture</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction: Operating Systems – Batch, Multi programmed, Time-sharing and Real time
            systems –System calls – System Programs –– Simple structure, Layered approach – Kernel,
            Shell.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Processes-. Process Scheduling - Round Robin Scheduling – Priority scheduling
            -multiple queues - Shortest Job First - Guaranteed scheduling - Two- level scheduling.
            Preemptive scheduling, Dispatcher –Multiple-processor scheduling.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Inter process Communication -Race Conditions - Critical Sections – Mutual Exclusion -
            Busy Waiting - Sleep And Wakeup - Semaphores - Event Counters - Monitors - Message
            Passing
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Memory management : Basics - swapping - fixed partitions - variable partitions -
            overlay - paging - segmentation - segmented paging - virtual memory concepts - demand
            paging - page replacement - space allocation policies - dynamic linking ,Thrashing
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Device management : Physical characteristics – disk scheduling algorithms - sector
            queuing -device drivers. Dead locks : Deadlock characteristics -conditions for deadlock-
            prevention - avoidance - detection – recovery from dead lock bankers algorithm.-
            resource trajectories - starvation.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>File System: File concept – Access methods – Directory structure – Directory
            implementation – Linear list, Hash table – Case study: Linux system.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it306">
        <item>DS</item>
        <item>Text Books:
            \n\n1. George Coulouris, Jean Dollimore, Tim Kindberg, “Distributed Systems: Concepts
            and Design”, Pearson 2009, 4th Edition.
            \n\nReferences:
            \n\n1. Andrew S Tanenbaum and Marteen Van Steen, “Distributed Systems Principles and
            Paradigms”, Pearson Education / Prentice Hall of India , New Delhi, 2002.
            \n2. Pradeep K Sinha, “Distributed Operating Systems: Concepts and Design”, Prentice
            Hall of India, New Delhi, 2004.
            \n3. Mukesh Singhal, Niranjan G Shivarathri, “Advanced Concepts in Operating systems”,
            Tata Mc Graw Hill Ltd.
            \n4. Tanenbaum A S, “ Modern Operating System”, 3/e, PHI
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>IT305 Operating Systems</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Characterization of Distributed Systems-Introduction-ExamplesResource Sharing and the
            Web-Challenges. System ModelsArchitectural-Fundamental. Inter process
            CommunicationIntroduction-API for Internet protocols-External data representation and
            marshalling--Client-server communication-Group communication- Case study: Inter process
            Communication in UNIX.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Distributed Objects and Remote Invocation-IntroductionCommunication between
            distributed objects-Remote procedure callsEvents and notifications-Case study: Java RMI.
            Operating System Support-Introduction-OS layer-Protection-Processes and threads-
            Communication and invocation OS architecture
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Distributed File Systems-Introduction-File service architecture-Case Study: Sun
            Network File System-Enhancements and further developments. Name
            Services-Introduction-Name Services and the Domain Name System-Directory Services-Case
            Study: Global Name Service
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Time and Global States-Introduction-Clocks, events and process states-Synchronizing
            physical clocks-Logical time and logical clocksGlobal states-Distributed debugging
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Coordination and Agreement-Introduction-Distributed mutual exclusion – Elections ¬
            Multicast communication-Consensus and related problems.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Distributed Shared Memory-Introduction-Design and implementation issues-Sequential
            consistency and Ivy case study Release consistency and Munin case study-Other
            consistency models. CORBA Case Study- Introduction-CORBA RMI-CORBA services.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it307">
        <item>CN</item>
        <item>Text Book: \n\n1. Andrew S. Tanenbaum, “Computer Networks”, Prentice Hall, 4th
            Edition, 2003 (Module 1 to 5)
            \n2. James F Kurose, Keith W Ross, Computer Networking: A top Down Approach featuring
            the Internet, Pearson Education, 3rd Edition. (Module 6)
            \n\nReferences: \n\n1. Behrouz A. Forouzan, TCP/IP Protocol Suite, Fourth Edition, Mc
            Graw Hill
            \n2. Behrouz A. Forouzan, Data Communication and Networking, Fourth Edition, Mc Graw
            Hill
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>Nil</item>
        <item>INTRODUCTION AND PHYSICAL LAYER</item>
        <item>Introduction: - Types of Computer Networks, Network Software - Protocol Hierarchies,
            Connection oriented and Connection less hierarchies, Reference Models - ISO-OSI
            Reference Model, TCP/IP Reference Model – Comparison of OSI and TCP/IP reference models.
            Physical Layer: - Guided Transmission Media– Twisted Pair, Coaxial and Fiber Optics,
            Wireless Transmission- Radio and Microwave transmission, Communication Satellites – GEO,
            MEO, LEO. Comparison of Network hardware - Repeaters, Routers, Bridges, Gateways, Hub
            and Cable Modem
        </item>
        <item>DATA LINK LAYER</item>
        <item>Data Link Layer: - Data link Layer design issues-Error Detection and correction –
            Elementary Data link protocols- Sliding window protocols- Basic Concept, One Bit Sliding
            window protocol, Concept of Go Back n and Selective repeat.
        </item>
        <item>MEDIUM ACCESS CONTROL</item>
        <item>Medium Access Control:- Static and Dynamic channel allocation in LAN, Multiple access
            protocols – ALOHA – Pure ALOHA – Slotted ALOHA – Carrier Sense Multiple Access protocols
            – persistent and non-persistent CSMA – CSMA with collision detection – Ethernet-
            Ethernet Cabling, Encoding, Frame Format, Binary Exponential Back Off Algorithm,
            Comparison of Fast and Gigabit Ethernet.
        </item>
        <item>NETWORK LAYER</item>
        <item>Network layer: -Network Layer Design Issues, Routing Algorithm – Optimality principle
            - Flooding - Distance vector routing – Link state routing –Multicast Routing -
            Congestion Control Algorithms – General principles – Congestion prevention policies –
            Choke packets – Random Early Detection- Quality of Service requirements- Buffering,
            Traffic shaping – Leaky bucket algorithm.
        </item>
        <item>TRANSPORT LAYER</item>
        <item>Transport Layer: - Transport Service – The services provided to upper layers,
            Transport Service primitives, Berkley Sockets. Elements of transport protocols, UDP-
            Segment Structure, Remote Procedure Call. TCP – Service model, TCP Protocol, TCP Segment
            Header, Connection establishment and Release, Transmission Policy, Congestion Control
        </item>
        <item>APPLICATION LAYER</item>
        <item>Application Layer: - HTTP- Overview, Persistent and non persistent Connections,
            Message formats, Concept of Cookies and Web Cache -FTP - Electronic Mail – SMTP, Mail
            message formats, POP3, IMAP – DNS- Services provided by DNS, Overview of how DNS works,
            DNS Caching, Message format - P2P File sharing
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it361">
        <item>GT</item>
        <item>References: \n\n1. Bondy,J. A. and Murty,U.S.R., ‘Graph Theory with Applications’,
            Springer, 2008.
            \n2. Diestel, R. Graph Theory (Graduate Texts in Mathematics). New York, NY:
            Springer-Verlag, 1997. ISBN: 3540261834
            \n3. N. Alon and J. Spenser, "Probabilistic Methods", John Wiley and Sons, 2nd edition,
            2000.
            Bollobás, B. Modern Graph Theory (Graduate Texts in Mathematics). New York, NY:
            SpringerVerlag, 1998. ISBN: 0387984917.
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>Nil</item>
        <item>GRAPHS AND SUB GRAPHS. TREES</item>
        <item>GRAPHS AND SUBGRAPH - Graphs and Simple Graphs, Graph Isomorphism, The Incidence and
            Adjacency Matrices, Subgraphs, Vertex Degrees, Paths and Connection, Cycles,
            Applications – The Shortest Path Problem, Sperner &#39;s Lemma .
            TREES - Cut Edges and Bonds, Cut Vertices, Cayley &#39;s Formula, Applications - The
            Connector Problem
        </item>
        <item>CONNECTIVITY</item>
        <item>CONNECTIVITY - Blocks, Applications-Construction of Reliable Communication Networks
            Euler Tours, Hamilton Cycles, Applications-The Chinese Postman Problem, The Travelling
            Salesman Problem
        </item>
        <item>MATCHINGS AND INDEPENDENT SETS and CLIQUES</item>
        <item>MATCHINGS - Matchings and Coverings in Bipartite Graphs Perfect Matchings,
            Applications - The Personnel Assignment Problem, The Optimal Assignment Problem.
            INDEPENDENT SETS AND CLIQUES - Independent Sets, Ramsey &#39;s Theorem, TurAn &#39;s
            Theorem, Applications - Schur &#39;s Theorem, A Geometry Problem.
        </item>
        <item>VERTEX COLOURINGS</item>
        <item>VERTEX COLOURINGS - Chromatic Number, Brooks &#39; Theorem, Hajos &#39; Conjecture,
            Chromatic Polynomials, Girth and Chromatic Number, Applications - A Storage Problem
        </item>
        <item>Planar Graphs</item>
        <item>Planar Graphs - Plane and Planar Graphs, Dual Graphs, Euler &#39;s Formula, Bridges,
            Muratowski &#39;s Theorem, The Five-Colour Theorem and the Four-Colour Conjecture,
            Nonharniltonian Planar Graphs, Applications - A Planarity Algorithm
        </item>
        <item>DIRECTED GRAPHS AND NETWORKS</item>
        <item>DIRECTED GRAPHS - Directed Graphs, Directed Paths, Directed Cycles, Applications - A
            Job Sequencing Problem, Designing an Efficient Computer Drum, Making a Road System
            One-way, Ranking the Participants in a Tournament
            NETWORKS - Flows , Cuts, The Max-Flow Min-Cut Theorem, Applications - Menger &#39;s
            Theorems, Feasible Flows
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it362">
        <item>IR</item>
        <item>Text Books: \n\n1. C. Manning, P. Raghavan, and H. Schütze, “Introduction to
            Information Retrieval”, Cambridge University Press, 2008.
            \n2. C.J. Van Rijsbergen , Information Retrieval:,
            http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/Keith/Preface.html
            \n3. Ricardo Baexa-Yates and Berthier Ribeiro-Neto, “Modern Information Retrieval”,
            Addison Wesley Longman, 1999.
            \n\nReferences: \n\n1. Bruce Croft, Donald Metzler and Trevor Strohman, “Search Engines:
            Information Retrieval in Practice”, 1st Edition Addison Wesley, 2009.
            \n2. Manu Konchady, “Building Search Applications: Lucene, Ling Pipe”, First Edition,
            Gate Mustru Publishing, 2008.
            \n3. Mark Levene, “An Introduction to Search Engines and Web Navigation”, 2nd Edition
            Wiley, 2010.
            \n4. Ophir Frieder, “Information Retrieval: Algorithms and Heuristics: The Information
            Retrieval Series”, 2nd Edition, Springer, 2004.
            \n5. Stefan Buettcher, Charles L. A. Clarke, Gordon V. Cormack, “Information Retrieval:
            Implementing and Evaluating Search Engines”, The MIT Press, 2010.
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>CS205 Data structures</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction – Information versus Data Retrieval. Modeling of Information retrieval.
            Boolean Model, Vector Model, Probabilistic Model, Set Theoretical Models, Structured
            Text Retrieval Models.
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 2</item>
        <item>Classification, Measures of Association, Cluster Hypothesis, Single Link Clusters,
            File Structures, Inverted Files, Index Sequential Files, Ring Structures, Doubly Chained
            Trees, Hash Addressing
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 3</item>
        <item>Evaluation, Relevance, Precision and Recall, Interpolation, Averaging techniques, The
            Swets Model.
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 4</item>
        <item>Search Engines, Boolean Search, Matching Functions, Serial Search, Cluster
            Representatives, Cluster based retrieval.
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 5</item>
        <item>Web search basics – Web characteristics - crawling and indexes – Features of a crawler
            – Crawler architecture – DNS resolution – The URL frontier – Distributing indexes –
            Connectivity servers.
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 6</item>
        <item>Link Analysis – The Web as a graph – Anchor text and the web graph, PageRank – Markov
            chains, Page Rank computation, Topic-specific Page Rank, Hubs and authorities.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it363">
        <item>USP</item>
        <item>Text Book: \n\n1. Sumitabha Das , “Unix the ultimate guide”, TMH. 2nd Edition.
            \n2. Behrouz A. Forouzan, Richard F. Gilberg,” Unix and shell Programming.”, Cengage
            Learning
            \n\nReferences: \n\n1. Kernighan and Pike, “Unix programming environment”, PHI. /
            Pearson Education
            \n2. Graham Glass, King Ables,” Unix for programmers and users”, 3rd edition, Pearson
            Education
            \n3. Maurice J. Bach, “The Design of the Unix Operating System”, First Edition, Pearson
            Education, 1999
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>IT 201 Operating Systems</item>
        <item>MODULE 1</item>
        <item>Introduction to Unix:- Architecture of Unix, Features of Unix , Introduction to unix
            file system, Basic Unix Commands – General-purpose utilities, vi editor
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 2</item>
        <item>The Unix file system – Parent-Child relationship – File types - File operations - File
            Permissions – File Ownership –File modification and access times – Directories –
            Directory permissions – File System and Inodes – Links and symbolic links – locating
            Files.
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 3</item>
        <item>Introduction to Shells – Shell as command Processor – quotes, escape characters, wild
            cards – Redirection – pipes –tee command –variables –command substitution – filters
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 4</item>
        <item>Concepts of process in Unix – process creation – process status – Background and
            foreground Jobs – Job Execution with low priority – Signals – Termination of process –
            Job control
            TCP/IP Networking tools – talk, mesg, finger, telnet, rlogin, ftp, rcp, rsh – security
            for the Berkeley r-Utilities.
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 5</item>
        <item>Filters using regular expressions – grep –sed – programming with awk – preliminaries,
            formatted output, variables, number processing, comparison operators, BEGIN and END
            sections, arrays, control flows, looping and functions.
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 6</item>
        <item>Shell Programming – Shell variables – Shell scripts – positional parameters – Exit
            status of a command – logical operator – script termination – conditional branching –
            looping – sleep and wait - set and let commands – redirection – Exporting shell
            variables – Arrays – String handling – Conditional Parameter Substitution – Shell
            functions –eval and exec statements.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it364">
        <item>SPM</item>
        <item>References \n\n1. Roger S. Pressman, Software Engineering, 8/e, McGraw Hill, 2014.
            \n2. Ian Sommervile, Software Engineering, 7/e, University of Lancastor, Pearson
            Education, 2004.
            \n3. Bob Huges, Mike Cotterell, Rajib Mall, Software Project Management, 8/e, McGraw
            Hill, 2015.
            \n4. Walker Royce, Software Project Management : A Unified Frame Work, Pearson
            Education.
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>Nil</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to software engineering- scope of software engineering, historical
            aspects, economic aspects, maintenance aspects, specification and design aspects, team
            programming aspects. Layered technology, processes, methods and tools.
            Phases in Software development.
            Process models- prescriptive process models- waterfall model, incremental models,
            evolutionary models, and concurrent models. Specialised process models- component based
            development, formal methods model, aspect oriented software development. The unified
            process, personal and team process models.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Agile development- agility, agile process. Extreme programming- XP Values, The XP
            Process, Industrial XP, The XP Debate. Agile development models- Adaptive Software
            Development (ASD), Scrum, Dynamic Systems Development Method (DSDM), Crystal, Feature
            Driven Development (FDD), Lean Software Development (LSD), Agile Modeling (AM) , Agile
            Unified Process (AUP).
            Project management concepts- the management spectrum, people, product, process, and
            project.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Process and project metrics- software measurement- size oriented, function oriented,
            LOC and function point, metrics for software quality- measuring quality, defect removal
            efficiency, integrating metrics within the software process.
            Estimation for software projects- project planning, software scope, resources. Software
            project estimation, decomposition techniques- Software Sizing, Problem-Based Estimation,
            Process-Based Estimation.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Empirical estimation models- structure of estimation models, COCOMO II model.
            Estimation for agile development. Make/buy decision.
            Project scheduling - relationship between people and effort, effort distribution. Task
            set, defining a task network. Scheduling- timeline chart, tracking the schedule. Earned
            value analysis.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Risk management- risk strategies, software risks, risk identification, risk
            projection, risk refinement, Risk Mitigation, Monitoring, and Management. The RMMM Plan.
            Software Configuration Management - An SCM Scenario, Elements of a Configuration
            Management System, Baselines, Software Configuration Items. The SCM Repository - The
            Role of the repository, General Features and Content, SCM Features. The SCM Process-
            Identification of Objects in the Software Configuration, Version Control, Change
            Control, and
            Configuration Audit, Status Reporting.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Software quality assurance- Background Issues, Elements of Software Quality Assurance.
            SQA Tasks, Goals, and Metrics. Formal Approaches to SQA. Statistical Software Quality
            Assurance- A Generic Example, Six Sigma for Software Engineering. Software Reliability
            -Measures of Reliability and Availability, Software Safety. The ISO 9000 Quality
            Standards. The SQA Plan.
            Software process improvement- Approaches to SPI, Maturity Models. The SPI Process-
            Assessment and Gap Analysis, Education and Training, Selection and Justification,
            Installation/Migration, Evaluation, Risk Management for SPI, Critical Success Factors.
            The CMMI, The People CMM. Other SPI Frameworks. SPI Return on Investment. SPI trends.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it365">
        <item>CAPP</item>
        <item>Text Books \n\n1. D.E. Culler, J.P. Singh, and A. Gupta. Parallel Computer
            Architecture - A Hardware/Software Approach. Morgan Kaufmann Publishers, 2010.
            \n2. Hennessy J. L., D. Patterson, “Computer Architecture – A quantitative Approach”,
            5/e, Morgan Kauffman 2012.
            \n\nReferences \n\n1. Kai Hwang, “Advanced Computer Architecture Parallelism,
            Scalability, Programmability”, Tata McGraw-Hill, 2003.
            \n2. Research papers from top conferences such as ISCA, HPCA, MICRO, and ASPLOS.
            \n3. S.W. Keckler, K. Olukotun, and H.P. Hofstee. Multicore Processors and Systems.
            Springer, 2009.
            \n4. W.J. Dally and B. Towles. Principles and Practices of Interconnection Networks.
            Morgan Kaufmann Publishers, 2003.
            \n5. WWW Computer Architecture page. http://www.cs.wisc.edu/arch.
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>Nil</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Computer architecture - design issues-Memory wall, Power Wall , Frequency Wall Classes
            of parallelism and parallel architecture,
            \n Performance measurements, Pipelining- Scalar and super scalar processors- Instruction
            level parallelism -concepts and challenges, ILP Wall
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Data hazards, Structural Hazards, Branch Hazards, Branch Prediction schemes
            \n Basic compiler techniques for exposing instruction-level parallelism.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Dynamic Scheduling- Tomasulo &#39;s approach, Hardware based speculation.
            \n ILP using multiple issue and static scheduling, ILP using dynamic scheduling,
            multiple issue and speculation.
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 4</item>
        <item>Case study- Intel Core i7.
            \n Data level parallelism -Vector architecture-Vector instruction types, Vector-Access
            memory schemes , Graphic processing units.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Centralized shared memory architecture. Multiprocessor cache coherence Distributed
            shared memory and Directory based coherence.
            \n Interconnection Network Design -- Interconnection topologies, routing techniques,
            flow control mechanisms, router architecture, arbitration logic
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Designing Multicore Architectures -- Unique challenges in multicore architectures,
            \n Multicore memory hierarchy organization, dealing with performance volatility,
            multicore memory traffic reduction techniques.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="it366">
        <item>ADBMS</item>
        <item>Text Book: \n\n1. R. Elmasri, S.B. Navathe, “Fundamentals Of Database Systems”,
            Pearson Education, 2004
            \n\nReferences: \n\n1. Abdullah Uz Tansel Et Al, “Temporal Databases: Theory, Design and
            Principles”, Benjamin Cummings Publishers, 1993.
            \n2. C.S.R Prabhu, “Object-Oriented Database Systems”, Prentice Hall Of India, 1998.
            \n3. Carlo Zaniolo, Stefano Ceri, Christos Faloustsos, R.T.Snodgrass, V.S.Subrahmanian,
            “Advanced Database Systems”, Morgan Kaufman, 1997.
            \n4. Elisa Bertino, Barbara Catania, Gian Piero Zarri, “Intelligent Database Systems”,
            Addison-Wesley, 2001.
            \n5. Henry F Korth, Abraham Silberschatz, S. Sudharshan, “Database System Concepts”,
            Fourth Edition, McGraw Hill, 2002.
            \n6. N.Tamer Ozsu, Patrick Valduriez, “Principles Of Distributed Database Systems”,
            Prentice Hall International Inc., 1999.
            \n7. Raghu Ramakrishnan, Johannes Gehrke, “Database Management Systems”, McGraw Hill,
            Third Edition 2004
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>CS208 Principles of database design</item>
        <item>Distributed Databases</item>
        <item>Distributed Databases Vs Conventional Databases – Architecture – Fragmentation– Query
            Processing – Transaction Processing – Concurrency Control – Recovery.
        </item>
        <item>Object Oriented Databases</item>
        <item>Introduction to Object Oriented Data Bases - Approaches - Modelling and Design-
            Persistence – Query Languages - Transaction - Concurrency – Multi VersionLocks -
            Recovery.
        </item>
        <item>Emerging Systems</item>
        <item>Enhanced Data Models - Client/Server Model - Web Databases – Mobile Databases.</item>
        <item>Data mining and data ware housing</item>
        <item>Data mining introduction-concepts-association-classificationclustering-applications
            Datawarehousing-introduction-architecture-characteristicsmodeling and building data
            warehouse
        </item>
        <item>Database Design Issues</item>
        <item>ER Model - Normalization - Security - Integrity - Consistency - Database Tuning-
            Optimization and Research Issues – Design of Temporal Databases – Spatial Databases
        </item>
        <item>Current Issues</item>
        <item>Rules - Knowledge Bases - Active And Deductive Databases - Parallel Databases–
            Multimedia Databases – Image Databases – Text Database
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it367">
        <item>CGandM</item>
        <item>References \n\n1. Donald Hearn, Pauline Baker, “ Computer Graphics – C Version”,
            Pearson Education.
            \n2. Steinmetz R. and Nahrstedt K., “Multimedia: Computing, Communications and
            Applications”, Pearson Education.
            \n3. David F. Rogers, “Procedural Elements for Computer Graphics”, Tata McGraw-Hill
            \n4. Foley, van Dam, Feiner and Hughes, “Computer Graphics Principles and Practice”,
            Pearson Education.
            \n5. William M. Newman, Robert F. Sproull, “Principles of Interactive Computer Graphics”
            , Tata McGraw-Hill.
            \n6. David F. Rogers, J. Alan Adams, “Mathematical Elements for Computer Graphics”, Tata
            McGraw-Hill.
            \n7. Tay Vaughan, “Multimedia: Making it Work”, Tata McGraw-Hill.
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>Nil</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Graphics Systems – Raster Scan and Random Scan systems. Output Primitives – Line
            Drawing Algorithms (DDA, Bresenham), Circle generation algorithm. Filled Area
            \nPrimitives – Scan Fill, Flood Fill, Boundary Fill. Inside outside tests.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Multimedia: Data Compression- Source, Entropy and Hybrid Coding, Basic compression
            techniques, JPEG, H.261, MPEG, DVI.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Display Technologies: Working principle behind CRT, LCD, Plasma, LED, OLED, AMOLED,
            E-Paper displays.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>2-Dimensional Geometric Transformations ( Basic Transforamtions, Reflection and
            Shear), Homogenous Matrix representation of transformations. Composite Transformations.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>2-D Clipping- Point Clipping, Cohen-Sutherland Line Clipping Algorithm,
            Sutherland-Hodgeman Polygon Clipping Algorithm. 3-Dimensional Geometric Transformations
            -Basic Transforamtions, Composite 3 D transformations.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Visible Surface Detection Methods: Back Face Detection, Depth Buffer, A-Buffer, Scan
            line, Depth sorting methods. Digital Image Processing: Histogram, Equalisation, Image
            Segmentation, Region Labeling.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="it368">
        <item>ITC</item>
        <item>References: \n\n1. Ranjan Bose ,Information Theory, Coding and Cryptography 2nd
            Edition:, Tata McGrawHill, New Delhi, 2008
            \n2. Simon Haykin, Communication Systems: John Wiley and Sons. Pvt. Ltd.
            \n3. Taub and Schilling, Principles of Communication Systems: Tata McGraw-Hill
            \n4. Das, Mullick and Chatterjee, Principles of Digital Communication: Wiley Eastern
            Ltd.
            \n5. Shu Lin and Daniel J. Costello Jr, Error Control Coding Fundamentals and
            Applications: Prentice Hall Inc.
            \n6. Bernard Sklar, Digital Communications Fundamentals and Applications, Prentice Hall,
            2/e, 2001
        </item>
        <item>3-0-0-3</item>
        <item>NIL</item>
        <item>Information theory</item>
        <item>Concept of amount of information units, Entropy -marginal, conditional and joint
            entropies relation among entropies Mutual information, information rate, channel
            capacity, redundancy and efficiency of channels.
        </item>
        <item>Discrete channels</item>
        <item>Symmetric channels, Binary Symmetric Channel, Binary Erasure Channel, Cascaded
            channels, repetition of symbols, Binary unsymmetric channel, Shannon theorem.
        </item>
        <item>Continuous channels</item>
        <item>Capacity of band limited Gaussian channels, Shannon-Hartley theorem, Trade off between
            band width and signal to noise ratio, Capacity of a channel with infinite band width,
            Optimum modulation system.
        </item>
        <item>Source codingl</item>
        <item>Encoding techniques, Purpose of encoding, Instantaneous codes, Construction of
            instantaneous codes, Kraft &#39;s inequality, Coding efficiency and redundancy,
            Noiseless coding theorem. Construction of basic source codes: - Shannon-Fano algorithm,
            Huffman coding, Arithmetic coding, ZIP coding.
        </item>
        <item>Codes for error detection and correction</item>
        <item>Parity check coding, Linear block codes,Error detecting and correcting capabilities,
            Generator and Parity check matrices, Standard array and Syndrome decoding, Hamming
            codes, Encoding and decoding of systematic and unsystematic codes. Cyclic codes: -
            Generator polynomial, Generator and Parity check matrices, Encoding of cyclic codes,
            Syndrome computation and error detection, Decoding of cyclic codes, BCH codes, RS codes,
            Burst error correction.
        </item>
        <item>Convolutional codes and ARQ</item>
        <item>Encoding- State, Tree and Trellis diagrams, Maximum likelihood decoding of
            convolutional codes -Viterby algorithm, Sequential decoding Stackalgorithm.
            \nInterleaving techniques: - Block and convolutional interleaving, Coding
            andinterleaving applied to CD digital audio system -CIRC encoding and
            decoding,interpolation and muting. \nARQ: - Types of ARQ, Performance of ARQ,
            Probability of error and throughput.
        </item>
    </array>


</resources>