<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <array name="ce201">
        <item>MS</item>
        <item>Review of Statics</item>
        <item>Review of Statics Types of external loads - internal stresses - normal and shear
            stresses - strain - Hooke’s law - working stress - stress strain diagrams - Poisson’s
            ratio - relationship between elastic constants
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Elongation of bars of constant and varying sections – statically indeterminate
            problems in tension and compression –Temperature effects – strain energy and
            complementary energy-strain energy due to tension, compression and shear
        </item>
        <item>Bending Moment and Shear force</item>
        <item>Bending Moment and Shear force: Different types of beams- various types of loading
            –Relationship connecting intensity of loading , shearing force and bending moment- shear
            force and bending moment diagrams for cantilever beams and Simply supported beams for
            different types of loading.
        </item>
        <item>Stresses in beams of symmetrical cross sections</item>
        <item>Stresses in beams of symmetrical cross sections: Theory of simple bending –assumptions
            and limitations – Normal stresses in beams- Moment of resistance - beams of uniform
            strength - beams of two materials – strain energy due to bending - shearing stresses in
            beams.
        </item>
        <item>Analysis of stress and strain on oblique sections, Thin and Thick Cylinders, Torsion
        </item>
        <item>Analysis of stress and strain on oblique sections: Stress on inclined planes for axial
            and biaxial stress fields - principal stresses - Mohr’s circle of stress \nThin and
            Thick Cylinders: Stresses in thin cylinders – thick cylinders - Lame’s equation –
            stresses in thick cylinders due to internal and external pressures \nTorsion: Torsion of
            solid and hollow circular shafts.-Pure shear- strain energy in pure shear and
            torsion.\nSprings: Close coiled and open coiled helical springs
        </item>
        <item>Deflection of statically determinate beams, Theory of columns</item>
        <item>Deflection of statically determinate beams: Differential equation of the elastic curve
            - Method of successive integration, Macaulay’s method, Method of superposition, moment
            area method. \nTheory of columns: Direct and bending stresses in short columns- Kern of
            a section. Buckling and stability-Euler’s buckling/crippling load for columns with
            different end conditions- Rankine’s formula
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ce202">
        <item>SA1</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>TRUSS ANALYSIS: Analysis of determinate trussMethods of joints and sections
            Displacement response of statically determinate structural systems using energy methods:
            Elastic theorems and energy principles - strain energy due to axial load, bending
            moment, shear and torsion - strain energy method, Castigliano’s method for deflection
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Principle of virtual work – Unit load method-Betti‟s theorem - Maxwell‟s law of
            reciprocal deflections - principle of least work - application of unit load method and
            strain energy method for determination of deflection of statically determinate beams,
            frames - pin jointed trusses - temperature effects, lack of fit. Statically
            indeterminate structures: Degree of static and kinematic indeterminacies - force and
            displacement method
        </item>
        <item>Strain Energy methods and Method of Consistent deformations</item>
        <item>Strain Energy methods: Analysis of beams, frames and trusses with internal and
            external redundancy - effect of prestrain, lack of fit, temperature changes, support
            settlement. \nMethod of Consistent deformations: Analysis of beams frames and trusses
            with internal and external redundancy - effect of prestrain, lack of fit, temperature
            changes, support settlement.
        </item>
        <item>Moving loads and influence lines</item>
        <item>Moving loads and influence lines. Introduction to moving loads - concept of influence
            lines - influence lines for reaction, shear force and bending moment in simply supported
            beams and over hanging beams - influence lines for forces in beams and trusses analysis
            for and trusses analysis for different types of moving loads - single concentrated load
            - several concentrated loads uniformly distributed load shorter and longer than the
            span.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Statically determinate suspension bridges and arches Analysis of forces in cables -
            temperature effects - suspension bridges with three hinged stiffening girders
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Statically indeterminate suspension bridges and arches.- theory of arches – Eddy’s
            theorem - analysis of three hinged arches-suspension bridges with two hinged stiffening
            girders - analysis of two hinged arches - settlement and temperature effects.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ce203">
        <item>FM1</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Fluid properties - density – specific gravity - surface tension and capillarity -
            vapour pressure - viscosity and compressibility - Classification of Fluids (No questions
            to be asked) . Fluid statics: Fluid pressure, variation of pressure in a fluid,
            measurement of pressure using manometerssimple manometers, differential manometers,
            Pressure head. Forces on immersed plane and curved surfaces. Pressure distribution
            diagram for vertical surfaces, Practical application of total pressure (spillway gates).
            Buoyancy and Floatation: Buoyant force, stability of floating and submerged bodies,
            metacentre and metacentric height, Analytical and experimental determination of
            metacentric height.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Kinematics of fluid flow: Methods of describing fluid motion, Lagrangian and Eulerian
            methods, Types of fluid flow: steady and unsteady flow, uniform and non-uniform flow,
            one, two and three dimensional flow, laminar and turbulent flow, rotational and
            irrotational flow. Types of flow lines: stream line, path line, streak lines,
            conservation of mass, equation of continuity in one, two and three dimensions,
            (Derivation in Cartesian co-ordinate system only) Velocity and Acceleration of fluid
            particle, convective and local acceleration, Deformation of fluid elements: circulation
            and vorticity, velocity potential, stream function, equipotential lines, flow net, uses
            of flow net; Vortex motion, free and forced vortex (no problems).
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Dynamic of fluid flow: Euler’s equation of motion and integration of Euler’s equation
            of motion along a streamline. Bernoulli’s Equation, Energy correction factors,
            Applications of Bernoulli’s equation : Pitot tube, Venturimeter and orifice meter.
            Momentum Principle- Steady flow momentum equation- Momentum correction factor, Force
            computation on a pipe bend
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Flow through orifices: Different types of orifices, Flow over a sharp edged orifice,
            Hydraulic coefficients – Experimental determination of these coefficients, flow through
            large rectangular orifice, Flow through submerged orifices, flow under variable heads,
            time of emptying. Flow over weirs: flow over rectangular, triangular and trapezoidal
            sharp crested weir, Cipolletti weir, Broad crested weir, Submerged weirs, Proportional
            weir.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Flow through pipes: Viscous flow - Shear stress, pressure gradient relationship -
            laminar flow between parallel plates - Laminar flow through circular tubes (Hagen
            Poiseulle&apos;s Eqn) - Hydraulic and energy gradient - flow through pipes - Darcy
            -Weisbach&apos;s equation - pipe roughness -friction factor- Moody&apos;s diagram- Major
            and
            minor losses of flow in pipes - Pipes in series and in parallel.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Boundary layer theory-no slip condition, boundary layer thickness, boundary layer
            growth over long thin plate, laminar, turbulent boundary layer, laminar sub layer,
            Momentum integral equation of boundary layer (no derivation), Blasius boundary layer
            equations for laminar and turbulent boundary layer. Drag and lift on Immersed
            bodies-Pressure drag and friction drag, profile drag, Drag and lift co-efficient-
            computation of drag on a flat plate. Separation of boundary layer and control.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ce204">
        <item>CT</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Construction Materials – Building stones – Classification of rocks – Quarrying of
            stones. Dressing – Properties and uses of common stones – Tests conducted on stones.
            \nTimber – Classification – seasoning -defects in Timber –– decay– preservation –
            Manufacture, properties and uses of plywood, fibre board, particle board. \nMortar –
            Types – Sand – properties – uses. \nIron and Steel –Reinforcing steel – types –
            specifications. Structural steel – specifications \nMiscellaneous materials (only
            properties, classifications and their use in construction industry): Glass, Plastics,
            A.C. Sheets, Bitumen, Adhesives, Aluminium
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Concrete – Aggregates – Mechanical and Physical properties and tests – Grading
            requirements – Water quality for concrete – \nAdmixtures – types and uses – plasticizers
            – accelerators – retarders –water reducing agents \nMaking of concrete - batching –
            mixing – types of mixers – transportation – placing – compacting – curing \nProperties
            of concrete – fresh concrete – workability – segregation and bleeding - factors
            affecting workability and strength – tests on workability – tests for strength of
            concrete in compression, tension and flexure

            \nConcrete quality control – statistical analysis of results – standard deviation
            –acceptance criteria – mix proportioning (B.I.S method) – nominal mixes.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Building construction - Preliminary considerations –Foundations - shallow and deep
            foundations – description of spread, grillage, raft and pile foundation. \nMasonry –
            Types of stone masonry – Bonds in brickwork – advantages and limitations of masonry
            construction - corbels, cornice and copings composite walls - cavity walls and partition
            walls – construction details and features – scaffoldings
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Lintels and arches – types and construction details. \nFloors and flooring – different
            types of floors and floor coverings \nRoofs and roof coverings – different types of
            roofs – suitability – types and uses of roofing materials \nDoors, windows and
            ventilators – Types and construction details \nFinishing works – Plastering, pointing,
            white washing, colour washing, distempering, painting. Methods of providing DPC. Termite
            proofing
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Tall Buildings – Framed building – steel and concrete frame – structural systems
            –erection of steel work–concrete framed construction– formwork – construction and
            expansion. joints Introduction to prefabricated construction – slip form construction
            \nVertical transportation –Stairs – types - layout and planning.- \nElevators – types –
            terminology – passenger, service and goods elevators – handling capacity - arrangement
            and positioning of lifts – \nEscalators – features –use of ramps
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Cost-effective construction - principles of filler slab and rat-trap
            bond masonry \nBuilding failures – General reasons – classification – Causes of failures
            in RCC and Steel structures \nFoundation failure – failures by alteration, improper
            maintenance, overloading – Fire, Wind and Earthquake.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ce205">
        <item>Geology</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Relevance of geology in Civil Engineering. Subdivisions of Geology. Weathering, types
            and its engineering significance. Laboratory tests used in civil engineering for
            assessing intensity of weathering. Engineering classification of weathered rock masses.
            Soil profile. Geological classification of soils.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Hydrogeology-occurrence of groundwater, Types of aquifers, permeability / hydraulic
            conductivity. Engineering significance of subsurface water- problems created in
            construction, as an erosional agent. Methods to control of subsurface water- barriers
            and liners, drains and wells.(Resistivity survey of groundwater may be demonstrated)
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Minerals- Properties that affect the strength of minerals. Physical properties and
            chemical composition of following minerals -quartz, feldspars (orthoclase and
            plagioclase), micas (biotite and muscovite), amphibole (hornblende), pyroxene (augite
            and hypersthene), gypsum, calcite, clay minerals (kaolinite), their chemical formulae.
            Earth quakes- in relation to internal structure of earth and plate tectonics
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Rocks as aggregates of minerals. Basic concepts- igneous, sedimentary and metamorphic
            rocks, Brief account of following rocks- granite, basalt, sandstone, limestone, shale,
            marble and quartzite. Rock features that influence the strength of rocks as construction
            material-concepts of lineation and foliation-schistosity and gneissosity. Rock types of
            Kerala. Brief account of engineering properties of rocks used as construction material
            (building and foundation) and road aggregates. Assessment of these properties.(Students
            should be taught to identify common rock forming minerals and common rocks based on
            their physical properties).
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Attitude of geological structures- strike and dip. Brunton compass. Deformation
            structures and their engineering significance- folds, faults and joints. Geological
            factors considered in the construction of dams and reservoirs, tunnels. (Simple
            exercises based on geological/topographic maps for determination of dip, apparent dip
            and thickness of lithological beds and preparation of geological cross sections should
            be performed. The students should be instructed in handling clinometer/Brunton compass
            to determine strike and dip)
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to natural hazards-Mass movements (Landslides), floods, their common
            management strategies. Coastal Processes- waves, currents and landforms. Types of
            coastal protection strategies. Soil erosion- causes and types and soil conservation
            measures.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ce206">
        <item>FM2</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Hydraulic Machines - Impulse momentum principle, impact of jets, force of a jet on
            fixed and moving vanes. Turbines- classification and comparison of velocity triangles
            for Pelton wheel and reaction turbines (Francis and Kaplan), work done and efficiency,
            specific speed, draft tube- different types, penstock, surge tank - types, cavitation in
            turbines.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Pumps- classification of pumps - Centrifugal pumps- types, work done, efficiency,
            minimum speed, velocity triangle for pumps, specific speed, priming, limitation of
            suction lift, net positive suction head, cavitation in centrifugal pump.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction: Open channel flow and its relevance in Civil Engineering , Comparison of
            open channel flow and pipe flow . Flow in open channels-types of channels, types of
            flow, geometric elements of channel section, velocity distribution in open channels,
            uniform flow in channels, Chezy’s equation, Kutter’s and Bazin’s equations, Manning’s
            formula, Most economic section for rectangular, trapezoidal and triangular channels.
            Condition for maximum discharge and maximum velocity through circular channels,
            computations for uniform flow, normal depth, conveyance of a channel section, section
            factor for uniform flow.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Specific energy, critical depth, discharge diagram, Computation of critical flow,
            Section factor for critical flow. Specific force, conjugate or sequent depths, hydraulic
            jump, expression for sequent depths and energy loss for a hydraulic jump in horizontal
            rectangular channels, types of jump, length of jump, height of jump, uses of hydraulic
            jump.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Gradually varied flow - dynamic equation for gradually varied flow, different forms of
            dynamic equation, Approximation for a wide rectangular channel, classification of
            surface profiles, Backwater and drawdown curves, characteristics of surface profiles in
            prismatic channels. Computation of length of surface profiles, direct step method.
            Design of lined open channels : triangular and trapezoidal cross-sections only
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Dimensional analysis and model studies - dimensions, dimensional homogeneity, methods
            of dimensional analysis, Rayleigh method, Buckingham method, dimensionless numbers,
            Similitude - geometric, kinematic and dynamic similarities. Model laws - Reynold’s and
            Froude model laws, scale ratios, types of models, distorted and undistorted models,
            scale effect in models.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ce207">
        <item>Surveying</item>
        <item>Introduction to Surveying</item>
        <item>Introduction to Surveying- Principles, Linear, angular and graphical methods, Survey
            stations, Survey lines- ranging, Bearing of survey lines, Local attraction, Declination,
            Dip, Latitude and Departure, Methods of orientation, Principle of resection
        </item>
        <item>Levelling and Contouring</item>
        <item>Levelling: Principles of levelling- Dumpy level- booking and reducing levels, Methods-
            simple, differential, reciprocal leveling, profile levelling and cross sectioning.
            Digital and Auto Level, Errors in levelling \nContouring: Characteristics, methods,
            uses.
        </item>
        <item>Area and Volume, Theodolite survey and Mass diagram</item>
        <item>Area and Volume: Various methods of computation. \nTheodolite survey: Instruments,
            Measurement of horizontal and vertical angle. \nMass diagram: Construction,
            Characteristics and Uses.
        </item>
        <item>Triangulation</item>
        <item>Triangulation: Triangulation figures, Strength of figure, Triangulation stations,
            Inter visibility of stations, Towers and signals – Satellite Stations and reduction to
            centre.
        </item>
        <item>Theory of Errors</item>
        <item>Theory of Errors – Types, theory of least squares, Weighting of observations, Most
            probable value, Application of weighting, Computation of indirectly observed quantities
            - method of normal equations.
        </item>
        <item>Electromagnetic distance measurement (EDM) and Total Station</item>
        <item>Electromagnetic distance measurement (EDM) – Principle of EDM, Modulation, Types of
            EDM instruments, Distomat Total Station – Parts of a Total Station – Accessories –
            Advantages and Applications, Introduction to Astronomical terms, Field Procedure for
            total station survey, Errors in Total Station Survey.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ce208">
        <item>Geotechnical Eng. 1</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to soil mechanics -Major soil deposits of India

            \nBasic soil properties - Void ratio, porosity, degree of saturation, air content,
            percentage air voids, moisture content, specific gravity, unit weight - Relationship
            between basic soil properties – Sensitivity – Thixotropy - numerical problems
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Index properties - Sieve analysis – Well graded, poorly graded and gap graded soils -
            Stoke’s law - Hydrometer analysis(no derivation required for percentage finer and
            diameter) - numerical problems- – Relative density \nConsistency-Atterberg Limits -
            Practical Applications - numerical problems I.S. classification of soils.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Permeability of soils - Darcy’s law – Factors affecting permeability - Practical
            Applications - Constant head and falling head permeability tests - Average permeability
            of stratified deposits (no derivation required) - numerical problems. \nPrinciple of
            effective stress - Total , neutral and effective stress variation diagrams - Quick sand
            condition - Critical hydraulic gradient - - numerical problems– Definition of phreatic
            line and exit gradient.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Shear strength of soils- Practical Applications - Mohr-Coulomb failure criterion –
            Mohr circle method for determination of principal planes and stresses- numerical
            problems – relationship between shear parameters and principal stresses[no derivation
            required} \nBrief discussion of direct shear test, tri-axial compression test, vane
            shear test and unconfined compression test – Applicability - numerical problems -UU and
            CD tests [Brief discussion only] - Liquefaction
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Compressibility and Consolidation - Void ratio versus pressure relationship -
            Coefficient of compressibility and volume compressibility – Compression index Practical
            Applications -

            \nChange in void ratio method - Height of solids method -Normally consolidated, under
            consolidated and over consolidated states - Estimation of pre consolidation pressure -
            Practical Applications - Estimation of magnitude of settlement of normally consolidated
            clays - Numerical problems

            \nTerzaghi’s theory of one-dimensional consolidation(no derivation required) - average
            degree of consolidation – Time factor - Coefficient of consolidation - Practical
            Applications -Square root of time and logarithm of time fitting methods - Numerical
            problems
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Stability of finite slopes - Toe failure, base failure, slip failure - Swedish Circle
            Method- Friction circle method- Factor of safety with respect to cohesion and angle of
            internal friction - Stability number - Stability charts - Methods to improve slope
            stability. \nCompaction of soils - Standard Proctor, Modified Proctor, I.S. light and
            Heavy Compaction Tests – OMC - Zero Air voids line - Control of compaction - numerical
            problems
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ce301">
        <item>DOCS</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction- Plain and Reinforced concrete- Properties of concrete and reinforcing steel-Objectives of design-Different design philosophies- Working Stress and Limit State methods-Limit Statemethod of design-Introduction to BIS code- Types of limit states-characteristic and design values-partial safety factors-types of loads and their factors.
            Limit State of Collapse in Bending-assumptions-stress-strain relationship of steel and concrete- analysis of singly reinforced rectangular beams-balanced-under reinforced-over reinforced sections-moment of resistance codal provisions</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Limit state of collapse in shear and bond- shear stresses in beams-types of reinforcement-shear strength of RC beam-IS code recommendations for shear design-design of shear reinforcement-examples
            Bond and development length - anchorage for reinforcement bars - code recommendations regarding curtailment of reinforcement</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Design of Singly Reinforced Beams- basic rules for design- design example of simply supported beam- design of cantilever beam-detailing Analysis and design of doubly reinforced beams –detailing, T-beams- terminology- analysis of T beams- examples - Design for torsion-IS code approach- examples</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Design of slabs- introduction- one-way and two-way action of slabs - load distribution in a slab- IS recommendations for design of slabs- design of one-way slab- cantilever slab- numerical problems – concepts of detailing of continuous slab –code coefficients</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Two- way slabs- simply supported and restrained slabs – design using IS Code coefficients Reinforcement detailing
            Limit State of Serviceability- limit state of deflection- short term and long term deflection-IS code recommendations- limit state of cracking- estimation of crack width- simple numerical examples</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Stair cases- Types-proportioning-loads- distribution of loads – codal provisions - design and detailing of dog legged stair- Concepts of tread-riser type stairs (detailing only)
            Columns- introduction –classification- effective length- short column - long column - reinforcement-IS specifications regarding columns- limit state of collapse: compression -design of axially loaded short columns-design examples with rectangular ties and helical reinforcement</item>
    </array>



    <array name="ce303">
    <item>STRUCTURAL ANALYSIS 11</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Clapeyrons Theorem (Three Moment Equation) :Derivation of threemoment equation - application of three moment equation for analysis of continuous beams under the effect of applied loads and uneven support settlement</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Slope Deflection Method : Analysis of continuous beams- beams with overhang- analysis of rigid frames - frames without sway and with sway - different types of loads -settlement effects</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Moment Distribution Method: Moment Distribution method – analysis of beams and frames – non sway and sway analysis</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Kani’s Method: Kani’s Method of analysis applied to continuous beams and single bay single storey rigid frames rigid frames – frames without sway and with sway.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Beams curved in plan: Analysis of cantilever beam curved in plan, analysis of circular beams over simple supports</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Plastic Theory: Introduction – plastic hinge concepts – plastic modulus – shape factor – redistribution of moments – collapse mechanisms –
        Plastic analysis of beams and portal frames by equilibrium and mechanism methods.(Single Storey and Single bay Frames only)</item>
</array>



    <array name="ce305">
    <item>GEOTECHNICAL ENGINEERING</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Stresses in soil due to loaded areas - Boussinesq’s formula for point loads – assumptions [no derivation required] – Comments - numerical problems
        Vertical stress beneath loaded areas of strip, rectangular and circular shapes(no derivation required)- Newmark’s chart[construction procedure not required] - Isobars- Pressure bulbs- numerical problems
    </item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Lateral earth pressure – At-rest, active and passive earth pressures – Practical examples
        Rankine’s and Coulomb’ theories[no derivation required]-Influence of surcharge, inclined backfill and water table on earth pressure- numerical problems
        Earth pressure on retaining walls with layered backfill- numerical problems</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Bearing capacity of shallow foundations – Ultimate, safe and allowable bearing capacity. - Failure mechanism, assumptions and equation of Terzaghi’s bearing capacity theory for strip footing[no derivation required] – Terzaghi’s formulae for circular and square footings numerical problems
        Local and general shear failure - Factors affecting bearing capacity – Influence of water table - numerical problems
        Total and differential settlement- Causes - Methods of reducing differential settlement–Brief discussion on soil improvement through installation of drains and preloading</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Combined footings- Rectangular and Trapezoidal combined footings - numerical problems
        Raft foundations (Design Concepts only) - Allowable Bearing capacity of Rafts on sands and clays - Floating foundation.
        Deep foundations - Elements of a well foundation – Problems encountered in well sinking – Methods to rectify tilts and shifts</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Pile foundations - Point bearing and friction piles - Bearing capacity of single pile in clay and sand[I.S. Static formulae] - numerical problems
        Dynamic formulae(Modified Hiley formulae only) - I.S. Pile load test [conventional]- Negative skin friction - numerical problems
        Group action - Group efficiency - Capacity of Pile groups- numerical problems</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Pile foundations - Point bearing and friction piles - Bearing capacity of single pile in clay and sand[I.S. Static formulae] - numerical problems
        Dynamic formulae(Modified Hiley formulae only) - I.S. Pile load test [conventional]- Negative skin friction - numerical problems
        Group action - Group efficiency - Capacity of Pile groups- numerical problems</item>
</array>


    <array name="ce307">

        <item>GEOMATICS</item>


        <item>Traverse Surveying</item>
        <item>Methods of traversing, Checks in closed traverse,
            Traverse computations, Balancing the traverse- methods
        </item>

        <item>Curve Surveying</item>
        <item>Elements of simple and compound curves –
            Method of setting out– Elements of Reverse curve (Introduction
            only)– Transition curve – length of curve – Elements of transition
            curve - Vertical curve (introduction only)
        </item>

        <item>Global Navigation Satellite System and Global Positioning
            Systems
        </item>
        <item>Global Navigation Satellite System- Types, Global Positioning
            Systems-Components and Principles, Satellite ranging-calculating
            position, Satellite signal structure, code phase and carrier phase
            measurements, GPS errors and biases, Application of GPS
        </item>

        <item>GPS Surveying methods</item>
        <item>Static, Rapid static , Kinematic methods –
            DGPS, Phases of GPS Survey -Planning and preparation, Field
            operation-horizontal and vertical control, data sheet, visibility
            diagram, Processing and report preparation,
        </item>

        <item>Remote Sensing</item>
        <item>Definition- Electromagnetic spectrum-Energy
            interactions with atmosphere and earth surface features-spectral
            reflectance of vegetation, soil and water- Classification of sensors-
            Active and Passive, Resolution-spatial, spectral radiometric and
            Temporal resolution, Multi spectral scanning-Along track and across
            track scanning
        </item>

        <item>Geographical Information System</item>
        <item>Geographical Information System-components of GIS, GIS
            operations, Map projections- methods, Coordinate systems-
            Geographic and Projected coordinate systems, Data Types- Spatial
            and attribute data, Raster and vector data representation-Data Input
            methods-Geometric Transformation-RMS error, Vector data
            Analysis-buffering, overlay.
        </item>
    </array>





    <array name="ce309">
        <item>WRE</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Hydrologic cycle-precipitation-mechanism, types and forms. Measurement of rainfall using rain gauges-optimum number of rain gauges. Estimation of missing precipitation. Representation of rainfall data-mass curve and hyetograph. Computation of mean precipitation over a catchment. Design rainfall - probable maximum rainfall. Infiltration-measurement by double ring infiltrometer. Horton’s model. Evaporation-measurement by IMD land pan, control of evaporation</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Runoff-components of runoff-methods of estimation of runoff-infiltration indices, Hydrograph analysis-Hydrograph from isolated storm-Base flow separation. Unit hydrograph –uses. Assumptions and limitations of unit hydrograph theory. Computation of storm/flood hydrograph of different duration by method of superposition and by development of S– Hydrograph.</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Irrigation– Necessity, Benefits and ill effects. Types: flow and lift irrigation - perennial and inundation irrigation. Methods: flooding, furrow, sprinkler and drip irrigation (concepts only, no design aspects/problems), Soil water plant relationships, soil moisture constants, Computation of crop water requirement: depth and frequency of Irrigation, Duty and delta, relationship, variation of duty, factors. Computation of design discharge of conveyance channels, Irrigation efficiencies. Consumptive use of water: concept of Evapotranspiration. (No detailed discussion on estimation procedures)</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Stream flow measurement: methods, Estimation of stream flow by area velocity method only, Stage discharge curve. Meandering of rivers, River training – objectives and classification, description of river training works</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Surface Water system: diversion and storage systems, necessity. River flow: Flow duration Curve, Firm yield. Reservoirs-types of reservoirs, zones of storage reservoir, reservoir planning-storage capacity and yield of reservoirs-analytical method and mass curve method. Reservoir sedimentation: trap efficiency, methods for control. Computation of useful life of reservoir</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Ground water : vertical distribution of groundwater, classification of saturated formation, water table, Aquifer properties : Porosity, Specific yield, specific retention, Types of aquifers. Darcy’s law, co-efficient of permeability, Transmissibility. Wells- Steady radial flow into a fully penetrating well in Confined and Unconfined aquifers. Estimation of yield of an open well, pumping and recuperation tests. Tube wells – types</item>
    </array>


    <array name="ce363">
        <item>GI</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction and practical importance - Objectives of soil exploration – Planning of a sub-surface exploration programme –Collection of existing information, reconnaissance, preliminary and detailed investigation - I.S. and other guidelines for deciding the number, size, spacing and depth of boreholes
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Methods of exploration - Open pits – Auger boring- -Wash boring, percussion drilling, rotary drilling – Comparison of the methods of exploration- Stabilization of bore holes
            Plate load test – Procedure, uses and limitations – modulus of subgrade reaction- Solution of numerical problems using plate load test data</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Sounding methods Standard Penetration Test – Procedure – corrections to be applied to observed N values – Procedure for estimation of representative average N value – Numerical examples - Factors influencing the SPT results and precautions to obtain reliable results – Merits/drawbacks of the test – Correlations of N value with various engineering and index properties of soils
            Static Cone Penetration Test – Procedure – Merits/drawbacks – Correlation of static CPT results with soil properties -Dynamic Cone Penetration Test – Procedure – Merits/drawbacks –
            Critical comparison of SPT, static CPT and dynamic CPT</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Geophysical methods – Seismic refraction method – Procedure, uses, limitations – Solution of numerical problems to estimate the velocity of seismic waves and the thickness of upper layer of a two-layered soil system - Electrical resistivity method – Electrical profiling and electrical sounding – Procedure, uses, limitations
            Pressure meter test - Procedure –Uses - limitations</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Soil sampling – Undisturbed, disturbed, and representative samples – Chunk and tube samples – Factors affecting sample disturbance and methods to minimise them –Area ratio - Inside clearance - Outside clearance - Recovery ratio –Ball check valve – Handling and transportation of samples – Extrusion of samples
            Types of samplers – Thin walled sampler – Piston sampler – Split spoon sampler – Methods for collection of sand samples from beneath the water table - Core retainers</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Rock Quality Designation –Bore log – Soil profile – Sub-soil investigation report
            Static pile load test – procedure for estimation of safe load - Cyclic pile load test –Procedure for separation of end bearing and skin friction resistance- solution of numerical problems using static and cyclic pile load test data</item>
    </array>



    <array name="ce361">
        <item>ACT</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Aggregates: Review of types; sampling and testing; effects on properties of concrete, production of artificial aggregates.
        Cements: Review of types of cements, chemical composition; properties and tests, chemical and physical process of hydration,blended cements
    </item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Properties of fresh concrete - basics regarding fresh concrete – mixing, workability, placement, consolidation, and curing, segregation and bleeding
        Chemical Admixtures: types and classification; actions and interactions; usage; effects on properties of concrete.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Mineral Admixtures: Flyash, ground granulated blast furnace slag, metakaolin, rice-husk ash and
        silica fume; chemical composition; physical characteristics; effects on properties of concrete; advantages and disadvantages.
        Proportioning of concrete mixtures: Factors considered in the design of mix . BIS Method, ACI method</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Properties of hardened concrete: Strength- compressive tensile and flexure - Elastic properties - Modulus of elasticity - Creep- factors affecting creep, effect of creep - shrinkage- factors affecting shrinkage, plastic shrinkage, drying shrinkage, autogeneous shrinkage, carbonation shrinkage</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Durability of concrete: Durability concept; factors affecting, reinforcement corrosion; fire resistance; frost damage; sulfate attack; alkali silica reaction; concrete in sea water, statistical quality control, acceptance criteria as per BIS code.
        Non-destructive testing of concrete: Surface Hardness, Ultrasonic, Penetration resistance, Pull-out test, chemical testing for chloride and carbonation- core cutting - measuring reinforcement cover</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Special concretes - Lightweight concrete- description of various types -High strength concrete - Self compacting concrete -Roller compacted concrete – Ready mixed concrete – Fibre reinforced concrete - polymer concrete
        Special processes and technology for particular types of structure - Sprayed concrete; underwater concrete, mass concrete; slip form construction, Prefabrication technology</item>
</array>

    <array name="ce365">
        <item>FDB</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Acoustics, fundamentals: Physics of sound-Frequency, period amplitude. Intensity of sound- Watts/m2- Bel- Decibel scales- dBA- Phon. Addition of sound levels. Human Audibility range. Behavior of sound in free and reverberant fields. Noise- allowable limits-effect of noise on human-Air and structure born noises-equivalent noise levels-day and night equivalent.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Acoustics, applications: Measures of noise control- Source-path and receiving end. TL value and computation of TL value, Flanking paths. Sound absorption-materials and fixings. Reverberation-Sabines formula-Eyrings modification. Acoustical defects- acoustical design of auditoriums and small lecture halls. Acoustical considerations of offices, hospitals and Industrial buildings</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Lighting, Natural: Visual tasks – Natural lighting- illumination requirements for various buildings –principles of day lighting – day light factor and its compon</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Lighting, Artificial: Artificial lighting- illumination requirements- lux meter – lamps and luminaries – polar distribution curves– Colour temperature and colour rendering index- glare -Design of artificial lighting – lumen method – point by point method. Basic idea of street lighting and outside lighting</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Thermal comfort: Factors affecting thermal comfort
            Effective temperature –Thermal comfort indices-ET-CET Charts- Bioclimatic chart- Psychrometry and Psycrometric chart.
            Earth-Sun relationship: Sun’s apparent movement with respect to the earth. Solar angles-Computation of solar radiation on different surfaces-solar path diagram-shadow-throw concept and design of shading devices</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Heat flow through building envelope: Thermo physical properties of building materials: Thermal quantities – heat flow – thermal conductivity – resistance and transmittance and surface coefficient - Sol- air temperature concept- solar gain factor. Thermal transmittance of structural elements – thermal gradients – heat gain/loss calculation. Periodic heat flow – time lag and decrement factor.
            Design approaches: Climate conscious designs- Climatic zones in India- orientation and shape of buildings in different climatic zones-Passive solar-Active solar and Active approaches. Requirements of buildings in tropical areas-Thermal insulation-Introduction to the concept of green-building</item>
    </array>




    <array name="ce367">
    <item>WCS</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Open channel flow- Pressure distribution in curvilinear flows. Application of specific energy principle to channel transitions with hump or change in width. Uniform flow-composite sections, Equivalent roughness, Hydraulic exponents N and M
    </item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Design of channels for uniform flow-Non erodible channel-Minimum permissible velocity-channel slopes-best hydraulic section. Erodible channels which scour but do not silt-Methods of approach-Method of permissible velocity-Tractive force –Method of tractive force-stable hydraulic section.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Gradually Varied flow computations- Direct integration method, standard step method, Unsteady flow-Gradually varied unsteady flow, Rapidly varied unsteady flow channels- Positive surges, Negative surges.(No numerical problem from negative surges)</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Head loss due to friction in pipes-Nikuradse experiment with artificially roughened pipe, Moody diagram, Friction coefficient for laminar and turbulent flows, reduction of carrying capacity with age. Hazen William’s formula.
        Reservoirs-Impounding reservoir, Service and Balancing reservoir. Two reservoir system, Three Reservoir system. Pumps- system head discharge curve and pump head discharge curve. Special valves-Check valve, Pressure reducing valve-modes of operation(No numerical problem with pressure reducing valve</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Pipe Network types and parameter interrelationships. Rules for solvability of pipe networks.Formulation of equations-Basic unknown parameter, Pipe discharge equations, Nodal Head equations,</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Analysis of water distribution network- Single and multisource networks with known pipe resistances- Hardy cross method- Method of balancing head, Method of balancing flow.</item>
</array>



    <array name="ce369">
    <item>DM</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Fundamental concepts of hazards and disasters: Relationship between disasters and development, implications. Introduction to key concepts and terminology of hazard, vulnerability, exposure, risk, crisis, emergencies, Disasters, Resilience</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Types of Natural Disasters I- Earth quakes, Landslides. Classification and nature of impacts.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Types of Natural Disasters II- Floods, Coastal disasters- Cyclones, Tsunamis. Classification and nature of impacts.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Types of Anthropogenic Disasters I– soil and soil degradation, desertification.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Types of Anthropogenic Disasters II-Fundamental concepts of water and atmospheric pollution.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Hazard and disaster management plans for floods, cyclones, tidal waves</item>
</array>




    <array name="ce371">
        <item>EAP</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Environment-Introduction-Multidisciplinary Nature
            Components of Environment, Ecology, Ecosystem- Material Cycling- Carbon and Nitrogen cycles
            Introduction: Classification of Pollution and Pollutants of environment, Pollution related Diseases, Basic requirements for healthy environment
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Air Pollution: Primary and Secondary Pollutants, Industrial Pollution, Ambient Air Quality Standards, Types of air pollutants-sulfur dioxide, nitrogen dioxide, carbon monoxide, particulate matter.
            Effects of air pollutants on human, vegetation and environment.</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Water Pollution: Point and Non-point Source of Pollution, Major Pollutants of Water, Physical, chemical and biological characteristics of water , Water borne diseases, Water Quality standards</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Solid Waste: Classification of Solid Waste, Composition and Characteristics of Solid Waste, Plastic wastes; Segregation of Solid waste, recycling and reuse of solid wastes, E-waste: Sources of generation</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Land/Soil Pollution: Effects of urbanization on land degradation, Impact of Modern Agriculture on Soil, pesticide pollution, Effect on Environment and Life sustenance, Abatement measures</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Noise pollution: Sources of Noise, Effects of Noise, measurement of noise, Equivalent sound pressure level, Control measures</item>
    </array>



    <array name="ce373">
    <item>AMM</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Stress, Principal stresses, Strain energy: Stress at a point – stress on an arbitrarily oriented plane-stress transformations- strain theory-principal stresses &amp; strains (2d &amp; 3d)- Generalized Hooke’s law-Equations of thermo-elasticity for isotropic materials-strain energy density- stress concentration
    </item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Failure &amp; Failure criteria: Modes of failure –yield failure criteria-introduction to fracture mechanics-cracks &amp; brittle fracture-fatigue-elastic and inelastic buckling.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Elements of theory of elasticity :Transformation of stress and strains: Plane state of stress - equations of transformation - principal stresses. Plane state of strain – analogy between stress and strain transformation - Mohr’s circles of stress and strain – strain rosettes</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Displacements-strains and compatibility-equilibrium equations and boundary conditions- stress field solutions for plane stress problems-polynomial solutions in Cartesian coordinates-displacements calculated from stresses-plane stress problems in polar coordinates</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Beams on elastic foundation: General theory-infinite beam subjected to concentrated load- beams with uniformly distributed loads- short beams
        Curved Beams: Winkler Bach formula-Equivalent area method- Circumferential stresses in Curved beams with I and T sections- Closed ring with circumferential load and uniform loads -deflections of sharply curved beams.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Torsion :Torsion of a cylindrical bar of circular cross section- St. Venant’s semi inverse method-stress function approach-elliptical, equilateral triangle &amp; narrow rectangular cross sections - Prandtl’s membrane analogy-Hollow thin wall torsion members-multiply connected cross sections- thin wall torsion members with restrained ends</item>
</array>


</resources>