<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <array name="hs210">
        <item>Life Skills</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Need for Effective Communication, Levels of communication;
            Flow of communication; Use of language in communication;
            Communication networks; Significance of technical
            communication, Types of barriers; Miscommunication; Noise;
            Overcoming measures.\n
            Listening as an active skill; Types of Listeners; Listening for
            general content; Listening to fill up information; Intensive
            Listening; Listening for specific information; Developing
            effective listening skills; Barriers to effective listening skills.\n
            Technical Writing: Differences between technical and literary
            style, Elements of style; Common Errors, Letter Writing:
            Formal, informal and demi-official letters; business letters, Job
            Application: Cover letter, Differences between bio-data, CV
            and Resume, Report Writing: Basics of Report Writing;
            Structure of a report; Types of reports.\n
            Non-verbal Communication and Body Language: Forms
            of non-verbal communication; Interpreting body-language
            cues; Kinesics; Proxemics; Chronemics; Effective use of body
            language.\n
            Interview Skills: Types of Interviews; Ensuring success in job
            interviews; Appropriate use of non-verbal communication.\n
            Group Discussion: Differences between group discussion and
            debate; Ensuring success in group discussions.\n Presentation
            Skills: Oral presentation and public speaking skills; business
            presentations.\nTechnology-based Communication:
            Netiquettes: effective e-mail messages; power-point
            presentation; enhancing editing skills using computer
            software.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Need for Creativity in the 21st century, Imagination, Intuition, Experience, Sources
            of Creativity, Lateral Thinking, Myths of creativity.\n
            Critical thinking Vs Creative thinking, Functions of Left Brain and Right brain,
            Convergent and Divergent Thinking, Critical reading and Multiple Intelligence.\n
            Steps in problem solving, Problem Solving Techniques, Problem Solving through Six
            Thinking Hats, Mind Mapping,
            Forced Connections.\n
            Problem Solving strategies, Analytical Thinking and quantitative reasoning expressed in
            written form, Numeric, symbolic, and graphic reasoning, Solving application problems.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Groups and Teams, Team Composition, Managing Team Performance,
            Importance of Group, Stages of Group, Group Cycle, Group thinking, getting acquainted,
            Clarifying expectations.\nGroup Problem Solving, Achieving Group Consensus.\n
            Group Dynamics techniques, Group vs Team, Team Dynamics, Teams for enhancing
            productivity, Building and Managing Successful Virtual Teams. Managing Team Performance
            and Managing Conflict in Teams.\n
            Working Together in Teams, Team Decision-Making, Team Culture and Power, Team Leader
            Development.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Morals, Values and Ethics, Integrity, Work Ethic, Service Learning, Civic Virtue,
            Respect for Others, Living Peacefully.\n
            Caring, Sharing, Honesty, Courage, Valuing Time, Cooperation, Commitment, Empathy,
            Self-Confidence, Character.\n
            Spirituality, Senses of \'Engineering Ethics\', variety of moral issued, Types
            of
            inquiry, moral dilemmas, moral autonomy, Kohlberg\'s theory, Gilligan\'s theory,
            Consensus and controversy, Models of Professional Roles, Theories about right action,
            Self-interest, customs and religion, application of ethical theories.\n
            Engineering as experimentation, engineers as responsible experimenters, Codes of ethics,
            Balanced outlook on.\n
            The challenger case study, Multinational corporations, Environmental ethics, computer
            ethics,Weapons development, engineers as managers, consulting engineers, engineers as
            expert witnesses and advisors, moral leadership, sample code of Ethics like ASME, ASCE,
            IEEE, Institution of Engineers(India), Indian Institute of Materials Management,
            Institution of electronics and telecommunication engineers(IETE), India, etc.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction, a framework for considering leadership, entrepreneurial and moral
            leadership, vision, people selection and development, cultural dimensions of leadership,
            style, followers, crises.\n
            Growing as a leader, turnaround leadership, gaining control, trust, managing diverse
            stakeholders, crisis management.\n
            Implications of national culture and multicultural leadership.\n
            Types of Leadership, Leadership Traits.\n
            Leadership Styles, VUCA Leadership, DART Leadership, Transactional vs Transformational
            Leaders, Leadership Grid, Effective Leaders, making of a Leader, Formulate Leadership
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="hs200">
        <item>Economics</item>
        <item>Business Economics</item>
        <item>Business Economics and its role in managerial decision makingmeaning-
            scope-relevance-economic problems-scarcity Vs choice (2
            Hrs)-Basic concepts in economics-scarcity, choice, resource
            allocation- Trade-off-opportunity cost-marginal analysis- marginal
            utility theory, Law of diminishing marginal utility -production
            possibility curve (2 Hrs).
        </item>
        <item>Basics of Micro Economics I</item>
        <item>Demand and Supply analysisequillibrium-
            elasticity (demand and supply) (3 Hrs.) -Production
            concepts-average product-marginal product-law of variable
            proportions- Production function-Cobb Douglas function-problems
            (3 Hrs).
        </item>
        <item>Basics of Micro Economics II</item>
        <item>Concept of costs-marginal, average,
            fixed, variable costs-cost curves-shut down point-long run and short
            run (3 Hrs.)- Break Even Analysis-Problem-Markets-Perfect
            Competition, Monopoly and Monopolistic Competition, Oligopoly-
            Cartel and collusion (3 Hrs).
        </item>
        <item>Basics of Macro Economics</item>
        <item>Circular flow of income-two sector
            and multi-sector models- National Income Concepts-Measurement
            methods-problems-Inflation, deflation (4 Hrs.)-Trade cycles-Moneystock
            and flow concept-Quantity theory of money-Fischer’s Equation
            and Cambridge Equation -velocity of circulation of money-credit
            control methods-SLR, CRR, Open Market Operations-Repo and
            Reverse Repo rate-emerging concepts in money-bit coin (4 Hrs).
        </item>
        <item>Business Decisions I</item>
        <item>Investment analysis-Capital Budgeting-NPV, IRR, Profitability Index, ARR, Payback
            Period (5 Hrs.)- Business decisions under certainty-uncertainty-selection of
            alternatives-risk and sensitivity- cost benefit analysis-resource management (4 Hrs).
        </item>
        <item>Business Decisions II</item>
        <item>Balance sheet preparation-principles and interpretation-forecasting techniques (7
            Hrs.)-business financing-sources of capital- Capital and money markets-international
            financing-FDI, FPI, FII-Basic Principles of taxation-direct tax, indirect tax-GST (2
            hrs).
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="hs300">
        <item>PM</item>

        <item>Introduction to Management</item>
        <item>Definitions, managerial roles and
            functions; Science or Art perspectives- External environmentglobal,
            innovative and entrepreneurial perspectives of
            Management (3 Hrs.)– Managing people and organizations in
            the context of New Era- Managing for competitive advantage -
            the Challenges of Management (3 Hrs.)
        </item>
        <item>Early Contributions and Ethics in Management</item>
        <item>Scientific
            Management- contributions of Taylor, Gilbreths, Human
            Relations approach-contributions of Mayo, McGregor's
            Theory, Ouchi's Theory Z (3 Hrs.) Systems Approach, the
            Contingency Approach, the Mckinsey 7-S Framework
            Corporate Social responsibility- Managerial Ethics. (3 Hrs)
        </item>
        <item>Planning</item>
        <item>Nature and importance of planning, -types of plans
            (3 Hrs.)- Steps in planning, Levels of planning - The Planning
            Process. – MBO (3 Hrs.).
        </item>
        <item>Organizing for decision making</item>
        <item>: Nature of organizing,
            organization levels and span of control in management
            Organisational design and structure –departmentation, line and
            staff concepts (3 Hrs.) Limitations of decision makingEvaluation
            and selecting from alternatives- programmed and
            non programmed decisions - decision under certainty,
            uncertainty and risk-creative process and innovation (3 Hrs.)
        </item>
        <item>Staffing and related HRD Functions</item>
        <item>Definition,Empowerment, staff – delegation, decentralization and
            recentralisation of authority – Effective Organizing and
            culture-responsive organizations –Global and entrepreneurial
            organizing (3 Hrs.) Manager inventory chart-matching person
            with the job-system approach to selection (3 Hrs.) Job designskills
            and personal characteristics needed in managersselection
            process, techniques and instruments (3 Hrs.)
        </item>
        <item>Leading and Controlling</item>
        <item>Leading Vs Managing – Trait
            approach and Contingency approaches to leadership -
            Dimensions of Leadership (3 Hrs.) - Leadership Behavior and
            styles – Transactional and Transformational Leadership (3
            Hrs.) Basic control process- control as a feedback system –
            Feed Forward Control – Requirements for effective control –
            control techniques – Overall controls and preventive controls –
            Global controlling (3 Hrs.)
        </item>
    </array>

</resources>