<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <array name="ee201">
        <item>CN</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Network theorems – Superposition theorem – Thevenin’s theorem – Norton’s theorem –
            Reciprocity Theorem – Maximum power transfer theorem – dc and ac steady state analysis –
            dependent and independent sources
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Network topology – graph, tree, incidence matrix – properties of incidence matrix –
            fundamental cut sets – cut set matrix – tie sets – fundamental tie sets – tie set matrix
            – relationships among incidence matrix, cut set matrix and tie set matrix – Kirchoff’s
            laws in terms of network topological matrices – formulation and solution of network
            equations using topological methods
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Steady state and transient response – DC response and sinusoidal response of RL, RC
            and RLC series circuits
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Application of Laplace transform in transient analysis – RL, RC and RLC circuits
            (Series and Parallel circuits) – step and sinusoidal response

            Transformed circuits – coupled circuits - dot convention - transform
            impedance/admittance of RLC circuits with mutual coupling – mesh analysis and node
            analysis of transformed circuits – solution of transformed circuits including mutually
            coupled circuits in s-domain
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Two port networks – Z, Y , h, T parameters – relationship between parameter sets –
            condition for symmetry and reciprocity – interconnections of two port networks – driving
            point and transfer immittance – T-π transformation.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Network functions–Network synthesis-positive real functions and Hurwitz
            polynomial-synthesis of one port network with two kinds of elements-Foster form I and
            II-Cauer form I and II.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee202">
        <item>SIM</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Alternators - basic principle, constructional features of salient pole type and
            cylindrical type alternators, advantages of stationary armature, turbo-alternator.
            Armature winding – types of armature winding- single layer, double layer, full pitched
            and short pitched winding,slot angle, pitch factor and distribution factor – numerical
            problems. Effect of pitch factor on harmonics – advantages of short chorded winding, EMF
            Equation – numerical problems. Harmonics in generated EMF – suppression of harmonics.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Performance of an alternator – Causes for voltage drop in alternators – armature
            resistance, armature leakage reactance – armature reaction, synchronous reactance,
            synchronous impedance, experimental determination – phasor diagram of a loaded
            alternator. Voltage regulation – EMF, MMF, ZPF and ASA methods – numerical problems.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Theory of salient pole machine – Blondel’s two reaction theory – direct axis and
            quadrature axis synchronous reactances – phasor diagram and determination of Xd and Xq
            by slip test. Parallel operation of alternators – necessity of parallel operation of
            alternators, methods of synchronisation– dark lamp method and bright lamp method,
            synchroscope, Synchronising current, synchronising power, synchronising torque. Effects
            of changing excitation of alternators, load sharing of two alternators in parallel
            operation.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Synchronous motor – construction and principle of synchronous motor, methods of
            starting. Effects of excitation on armature current and power factor, v-curve and
            inverter v-curve, load angle, torque and power relationship, phasor diagram, losses and
            efficiency calculations. Three phase induction motor – constructional features, slip
            ring and cage types. Theory of induction motor with constant mutual flux, slip, phasor
            diagram, expression for mechanical power and torque, torque-slip characteristics,
            starting torque, full load and pull out torque, equivalent circuit.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Circle diagrams – tests on induction motors for determination of equivalent circuit
            and circle diagram. Cogging, crawling and noise production in cage motors – remedial
            measures. Double cage induction motor – principle, torque-slip curves. Starting of
            induction motors – types of starters – DOL starter, autotransformer starter, star-delta
            starter, rotor resistance starter – starting torque and starting currentnumerical
            problems. Braking of induction motors – plugging, dynamic braking and regenerative
            braking (no numerical problems). Speed control – stator voltage control, V/f control,
            rotor resistance control.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Induction generator – principle of operation, grid connected and self excited
            operation, comparison of induction generator with synchronous generators. Synchronous
            induction motor – principle of operation. Single-phase induction motor – double field
            revolving theory, equivalent circuit, torque slip curve. Types of single phase induction
            motor – split phase, capacitor start, capacitor start and run types. Principle of shaded
            pole motor – applications.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee203">
        <item>AEC</item>
        <item>Diode Circuits and Bipolar Junction Transistors</item>
        <item>Diode Circuits: Diode clipping circuits - Single level and two level clippers -
            Clamping circuits – Design of Zener Voltage Regulators.
            Bipolar Junction Transistors : Review of BJT characteristics- Operating point of a BJT –
            Factors affecting stability of Q point and DC Biasing – Biasing circuits: fixed bias,
            collector to base bias, voltage division bias and self bias. (Derivation of stability
            factors for Voltage Divider Biasing only) –Bias compensation using diode and thermistor.

            Low frequency equivalent circuit of BJT. Common Emitter amplifier - AC Equivalent
            Circuit – Role of coupling and emitter bypass capacitors – h parameter model of BJT
            -Amplifier gains and impedances calculations using h equivalent circuit.
        </item>
        <item>Field Effect Transistors and Frequency response of Amplifiers</item>
        <item>Field Effect Transistors : Review of JFET and MOSFET construction, working and
            characteristics- Biasing a JFET and MOSFET using voltage divider bias–- CS and CD
            amplifiers – small signal models-FET as switch and voltage controlled resistance.
            Frequency response of Amplifiers : Miller’s Theorem- BJT Internal Capacitances at high
            frequency operationsHigh frequency analysis of CE Amplifier using hybrid Pi Model -Low
            Frequency Response of Common Emitter amplifier -– CE High frequency response-Gain
            bandwidth product- –––Low and High Frequency response of FET amplifiers
        </item>
        <item>Multistage amplifiers,Power amplifiers using BJT and Feedback Amplifiers</item>
        <item>Multistage amplifiers : Direct, RC, transformer coupled amplifiers – Power amplifiers
            using BJT : Class A, Class B and Class AB and class C- Conversion efficiency and
            distortion in power amplifiers. Feedback Amplifiers- Effect of positive and negative
            feedbacks- Basic feedback topologies and their properties
        </item>
        <item>Oscillators and Operational Amplifiers</item>
        <item>Oscillators : Bark Hausen’s criterion – RC oscillators (RC Phase shift oscillator and
            Wein Bridge oscillator) –LC oscillators (Hartley and Colpitt’s)- Derivation of frequency
            of oscillation for the above mentioned oscillators- Crystal oscillator. Operational
            Amplifiers: Review of Operational Amplifier basics - Analysis of fundamental
            differential amplifier- Properties of ideal and practical Op-Amp - Gain, CMRR and Slew
            rate of IC 741 and LM 301– Drift and frequency compensation in OP Amps- Open loop and
            Closed loop Configurations-Concept of virtual short and its relation to negative
            feedback
        </item>
        <item>OP-AMP Circuits</item>
        <item>OP-AMP Circuits : Review of inverting and noninverting amplifier circuits- Summing and
            difference amplifiers, Differentiator and Integrator circuits- Logarithmic amplifier-
            Half Wave Precision rectifier - Instrumentation amplifier.

            Comparators: Zero crossing and voltage level detectors, Schmitt trigger.
        </item>
        <item>Wave form genereation using OP-Amps, Timer 555 IC and Oscillator Circuits using
            OP-amps
        </item>
        <item>Wave form generation using Op-Amps: Square, triangular and ramp generator circuits
            using Op-Amp - Effect of slew rate on waveform generation.
            Timer 555 IC : Internal diagram of 555 IC– Astable and Monostable multivibrators using
            555 IC.
            Oscillator circuits using Op-amps : RC Phase shift oscillator, Wein Bridge oscillator,
            LC Oscillators- (Derivation not required) - Crystal oscillator.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ee204">
        <item>DELD</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Number Systems and Codes : Binary, Octal and hexadecimal conversions- ASCII code,
            Excess -3 code, Gray code, Error detection and correction - Parity generators and
            checkers – Fixed point and floating point arithmetic. Binary addition and subtraction,
            unsigned and signed numbers, 1&amp;apos;s complement and 2’s complement arithmetic
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>TTL logic and CMOS logic - Logic gates, Universal gates - Boolean Laws and theorems,
            Sum of Products method, Product of Sum method – K map representation and
            simplification(upto four variables) - Pairs, Quads, Octets, Dont care conditions.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Combinational circuits: Adders _ Full adder and half adder – Subtractors,
            halfsubtractor and fullsubtractor – Carry Look ahead adders – ALU(block diagram only).
            Multiplexers, Demultiplexers, Encoders, BCD to decimel decoders.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Sequential circuits: Flip-Flops, SR, JK, D and T flip-flops, JK Master Slave
            Flip-flop, Conversion of flip-flops, Registers -SISO,SIPO, PISO, PIPO. Counters :
            Asynchronous Counters – Modulus of a counter – Mod N counters.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Synchronous counters: Preset and clear modes, Counter Synthesis: Ring counter, Johnson
            Counter, Mod N counter, Decade counter. State Machines: State transition diagram, Moore
            and Mealy Machines – Design equation and circuit diagram.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Digital to Analog conversion – R-2R ladder, weighted resistors. Analog to Digital
            Conversion - Flash ADC, Successive approximation, Integrating ADC. Memory Basics, Read
            and Write, Addressing, ROMs, PROMs and EPROMs, RAMs, Sequential Programmable Logic
            Devices - PAL, PLA, FPGA (Introduction and basic concepts only) Introduction to VHDL,
            Implementation of AND, OR, half adder and full adder.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee205">
    <item>DC MAT</item>
    <item>1. Bimbra P. S., Electrical Machinery, 7/e, Khanna Publishers, 2011.
        \n2. Nagrath J. and D. P. Kothari, Theory of AC Machines, Tata McGraw Hill, 2006</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>NONE</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Electromagnetic principles for Machines
        Electro dynamical equations and their solution – rotational
        motion system – mutually coupled coils – construction of DC
        machines – energy conversion in rotating electrical machines –
        eddy currents and eddy current losses – flux distribution curve
        in the airgap – armature windings – lap and wave windings –
        selection criteria – equalizer rings – dummy coils.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>DC generators – EMF equation – methods of excitation –
        separately and self excited – shunt, series, compound –
        armature reaction – effects of armature reaction –
        demagnetizing &amp; cross magnetizing ampere-turns –
        compensating windings – interpoles – commutation – methods
        to improve commutation – voltage build-up – no loadcharacteristics – load characteristics – losses and efficiency –
        power flow diagram – parallel operation – applications of dc
        generators</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>DC motor – principle of operation – back emf – classification
        – torque equation – losses and efficiency – power flow
        diagram – performance characteristics of shunt, series and
        compound motors – starting of dc motors – necessity and
        types of starters – speed control – methods of speed control –
        testing – Swinburne’s test – Hopkinson’s test – separation of
        losses – retardation test – applications of dc motors.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Transformer losses and efficiency – voltage regulation – OC &amp; SC test – Sumpner’s test
        – all day efficiency
        Autotransformer – saving of copper – current rating and kVA
        rating of autotransformers, parallel operation of single phase
        transformers, necessary and desirable conditions of parallel
        operation, on load and off load tap changers.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Transformer losses and efficiency – voltage regulation – OC &amp; SC test – Sumpner’s test
        – all day efficiency
        Autotransformer – saving of copper – current rating and kVA
        rating of autotransformers, parallel operation of single phase
        transformers, necessary and desirable conditions of parallel
        operation, on load and off load tap changers.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>3-phase transformer – 3-phase transformer connections – Δ-Δ,
        Y-Υ , Δ-Y , Y-Δ, V-V – vector groupings Yy0, Dd0, Yd1,
        Yd11, Dy1, Dy11 – Scott connection – three winding
        transformer – tertiary winding – percentage and per unit
        impedance – parallel operation of three phase transformers.</item>
</array>
    <array name="ee206">
        <item>Material Science</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Conducting Materials: Conductivity- dependence on temperature and composition –
            Materials for electrical applications such as resistance, machines, solders etc.
            Semiconductor Materials: Concept, materials and properties– Basic ideas of Compound
            semiconductors, amorphous and organic semiconductors- applications. Dielectrics:
            Introduction to Dielectric polarization and classification –Clausius Mosotti relation-
            Behavior of dielectric in static and alternating fields
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Insulating materials and classification- properties- Common insulating materials used
            in electrical apparatus-Inorganic, organic, liquid and gaseous insulators- capacitor
            materials- Electro-negative gases- properties and application of SF6 gas and its
            mixtures with nitrogen Ferro electricity.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Dielectric Breakdown: Mechanism of breakdown in gases, liquids and solids –basic
            theories including Townsend&amp;apos;s criterion, Streamer mechanism, suspended particle
            theory,
            intrinsic breakdown, electro-mechanical breakdown- Factors influencing Ageing of
            insulatorsApplication of vacuum insulation- Breakdown in high vacuum-Basics of treatment
            and testing of transformer oil
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Magnetic Materials: Origin of permanent magnetic dipoles- Classification of magnetic
            materials -Curie-Weiss law- Properties and application of iron, alloys of iron- Hard and
            soft magnetic materials– Ferrites- Magnetic materials used in electrical machines,
            instruments and relays-
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Superconductor Materials:-Basic Concept- typescharacteristics-applications Solar
            Energy Materials: Photo thermal conversion- Solar selective coatings for enhanced solar
            thermal energy collection –Photovoltaic conversion – Solar cells -Silicon, Cadmium
            sulphide and Gallium arsenic – Organic solar cells.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Modern Techniques for materials studies: Optical microscopy – Electron microscopy –
            Photo electron spectroscopy – Atomic absorption spectroscopy – Introduction to
            Biomaterials and Nanomaterials.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee207">
        <item>CP</item>
        <item>Intro to Programming and Basic Elements of C</item>
        <item>Introduction to Programming: Machine language, assembly language, and high level
            language. Compilers and assemblers. Flow chart and algorithm – Development of algorithms
            for simple problems. Basic elements of C: Structure of C program –Keywords, Identifiers,
            data types, Operators and expressions – Input and Output functions
        </item>
        <item>Control Statements</item>
        <item>if, if-else, while, do-while and for statements, switch, break, continue, go to, and
            labels. Programming examples.
        </item>
        <item>Arrays and Strings</item>
        <item>Declaration, initialisation, processing arrays and strings– two dimensional and
            multidimensional arrays –application of arrays. Example programs
        </item>
        <item>Functions and Storage Classes</item>
        <item>Functions : Functions – declaring, defining, and accessing functions –parameter
            passing methods – – passing arrays to functions , Recursion . Storage classes – extern,
            auto, register and static. Example programs.
        </item>
        <item>Structures and Pointers</item>
        <item>Structures – declaration, definition and initialization of structures, unions
            Pointers: Concepts, declaration, initialization of pointer variables, Accessing a
            Variable through its Pointer Chain of Pointers, Pointer Expressions, Pointer Increments
            and Scale Factor, Pointers and Arrays, examples
        </item>
        <item>File management and Intro to Python</item>
        <item>File Management – File operations, Input/Output Operations on Files, Random Access to
            Files ,File pointer. Introduction to Python :Basic Syntax, Operators, control
            statements, functions-examples.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee208">
        <item>MI</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>General principles of measurements – measurement system- measurement standards –
            characteristics - errors in measurement- calibration of meters- significance of IS
            standards of Instruments. Classification of meters - operating forces - essentials of
            indicating instruments - deflecting, damping, controlling torques. Ammeters and
            voltmeters - moving coil, moving iron, constructional details and operating, principles
            shunts and multipliers – extension of range.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Measurement of resistance: measurement of insulation resistance - loss of charge
            method, measurement of earth resistance. Measurement of power and energy: Dynamometer
            type wattmeter – 1-phase and 3-phase power measurement – 1-phase and 3-phase energy
            meters (induction type) – electronic energy meter, TOD meter.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to high voltage and high current measurements: Measurement of high DC
            voltages - measurement of high AC voltages - electrostatic voltmeters – sphere gaps - DC
            Hall effect sensors - high current measurements. Study of Phasor Measurement Units
            (PMU). Current transformers and potential transformers – principle working, ratio and
            phase angle errors – numerical problems, Clamp on meters.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Magnetic Measurements: Measurement of flux and permeability - flux meter - hall effect
            Gaussmeter - BH curve and permeability measurement - hysteresis measurement- ballistic
            galvanometer – principle- determination of BH curve - hysteresis loop. Lloyd Fisher
            square — measurement of iron losses Measurement of rotational speed using proximity
            sensors and optical sensors.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>DC and AC potentiometers - General Principle - calibration of ammeter, voltmeter and
            wattmeter using potentiometer. AC Bridges: Maxwell’s bridge- Schering bridge and Wien’s
            bridge Oscilloscopes – Basic principle of signal display - Block diagram and principle
            of operation of general purpose CRO - vertical deflecting system - horizontal deflection
            system - basic sweep generator - XY mode and Lissajous patterns - applications of CRO -
            dual trace oscilloscope. digital storage oscilloscope
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Transducers - Definition and classification - common transducers for measurement of
            displacement, velocity, flow, liquid level, force, pressure, strain and temperature -
            basic principles and working of LVDT, electromagnetic and ultrasonic flow meters,
            piezoelectricforce transducer, load cell, strain gauge- bridge configuration for four
            strain gauges, RTD, Thermistors, thermocouple, Need for instrumentation system, data
            acquisition system.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee216">
        <item>EE</item>
        <item>Transformers</item>
        <item>Transformers- Principle of operation - emf equation - Phasor diagram - Equivalent
            circuit - OC and SC tests – Basic principles of auto transformer and three phase
            transformer
        </item>
        <item>DC Generator</item>
        <item>DC Generator – E.M.F equation- Armature reaction – Commutation - interlopes – power
            flow diagram – losses and efficiency – voltage regulation – parallel operation – load
            sharing
        </item>
        <item>DC Motor</item>
        <item>DC Motor- back E.M.F. – speed equation – torques – performance characteristics – power
            flow diagram losses and efficiency – starter- two point and three point – swinburns test
            – thyristor control of series and shunt motor.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Alternator- Rotating field - Frequency effect of distribution of winding - emf
            equation – Basic principles of synchronous motor – Losses and Efficiency - Torque
            equation - Starting methods - induction motor - Constructional features - Principle of
            operation of 3 phase induction motor – Vector diagram and equivalent circuits - Starting
            and speed control of squirrel cage and wound rotor induction motor
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Three phase Induction motor- types – torque equations- torque slip and torque speed
            characteristics- power flow diagram – efficiency – equivalent circuit- induction
            generator Special machines – single phase FHP motor starting methods- double field
            revolving theory-types and applications – stepper motor –classifications and
            applications – servomotors – classifications and applications –shaded pole motors
            –applications
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Principle of Indicating instruments- moving coil, moving iron and dynamometer type
            instruments- Extension of range of voltmeter and ammeter - Measurement of 3 phase power
            by two wattmeter method – Principle and working of Induction type energy meter- DC slide
            wire, potentiometer
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee311">
        <item>EDCA</item>
        <item>
            1. Kothari D. P. and I. J. Nagrath, Electrical Machines, Tata McGraw Hill, 2004.\n
            2. Nagrath .I.J. &amp; Kothari .D.P, Electrical Machines, Tata McGraw-Hill, 1998\n
            3. Richard Crowder, Electrical Drives and Electromechanical systems, Elsevier, 2013\n
            4. Mehta V. K. and R. Mehta, Principles of Electrical and Electronics, S. Chand &amp;
            Company
            Ltd., 1996.\n
            5. Theraja B. L. and A. K. Theraja, A Text Book of Electrical Technology, S. Chand &amp;
            Company Ltd., 2008.\n
            6. Vedam Subrahmaniam, Electric Drives (concepts and applications), Tata McGraw- Hill,
            2001\n
        </item>
        <item>3</item>
        <item>NIL</item>
        <item>DC Machines</item>
        <item>Principle of operation-emf equation-types of excitations. Separately excited, shunt
            and series excited DC generators, compound generators. General idea of armature
            reaction, OCC and load characteristics - simple numerical problems.
        </item>
        <item>Principles of DC motors</item>
        <item>Torque and speed equations-torque speed characteristics- variations of speed, torque
            and power with motor current. Applications of dc shunt series and compound motors.
            Principles of starting, losses and efficiency – load test- simple numerical problems
        </item>
        <item>Transformers</item>
        <item>Principles of operations – emf equation- vector diagrams- losses and efficiency – OC
            and SC tests. Equivalent circuits-efficiency calculations- maximum efficiency – all day
            efficiency –simple numerical problems. Auto transformers constant voltage transformer-
            instrument transformers
        </item>
        <item>Three phase induction motors</item>
        <item>Slip ring and squirrel cage types-principles of operation – rotating magnetic field-
            torque slip
            characteristics- no load and blocked rotor tests. Circle diagrams- methods of starting –
            direct online – auto transformer starting
        </item>
        <item>Single phase motors</item>
        <item>Principle of operation of single phase induction motor – split phase motor – capacitor
            start motor- stepper motor-universal motor Synchronous machines types – emf equation of
            alternator – regulation of alternator by emf method. Principles of operation of
            synchronous motors- methods of starting- V curves-synchronous condenser
        </item>
        <item>Stepper motors</item>
        <item>Principle of operation, multistack variable reluctance motors, single-stack variable
            reluctance motors, Hybrid stepper motors,Linear stepper motor, comparison, Torque-speed
            characteristics,control of stepper motors
            Controllers for automation, servo control, Digital controllers, Advanced control
            systems, Digital signal processors, motor controllers,Axis controllers, Machine tool
            controllers, Programmable Logic Controllers
        </item>
    </array>


</resources>