<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>


    <array name="ph100">
        <item>Physics</item>
        <item>REFERENCE TEXTS\n\n1. Aruldhas, G., Engineering Physics. Pill Ltd. \n2. Beiser. A..
            Concepts of Modern Physics. McGraw Hill India Ltd. \n3. Bhattacharya and Tandon,
            Engineering Physics , Oxford India \n4. Brijlal and Subramanyam. A Text Book of Optics.
            S. Chand and Co. \n5. Dominic and Nahari, A Text Book of Engineering Physics, Owl Books
            Publishers \n6. Hecht, E., Optics, Pearson Education \n7. Mchta, N.. Applied Physics for
            Engineers, Pill Ltd \n8. Patois, J. C., Fiber Optic Communications, Pearson Education
            \n9. Pandey. B. K. and Chathurvedi. S.. Engineering Physics. Cengage Learning \n10.
            Philip, J., A Text Book of Engineering Physics, Educational Publishers \n11. Premlet.
            B.. Engineering Physics, Mc GrawUill India Ltd \n12. Sarin, A. and Rewal, A.,
            Engineering Physics, Wiley India Pvt Ltd \n13. Sears and Zemansky, University Physics ,
            Pearson \n14. Vasudeva, A. S., A Text Book of Engineering Physics, S. Chand and Co
        </item>
        <item>Four</item>
        <item>NONE</item>
        <item>Harmonic Oscillations and Waves</item>
        <item>Harmonic Oscillations: Differential equation of damped harmonic oscillation, forced
            harmonic oscillation and their solutions- Resonance, Q factor, Sharpness of resonance-
            LCR circuit as an electrical analogue of Mechanical Oscillator (Qualitative) Waves: One
            dimensional wave - differential equation and solution. Three dimensional waves -
            Differential equation and its solution. (No derivation) Transverse vibrations of a
            stretched string.
        </item>
        <item>Interference and Diffraction</item>
        <item>Interference: Coherence. Interference in thin films and wedge shaped films (Reflected
            system) Newton\'s rings-measurement of wavelength and refractive index of liquid
            Interference filters. Anlireflection coaling. Diffraction lresnel and Fraunhofer
            diffraction. Fraunhofer diffraction at a single slit. Plane transmission grating.
            Grating equation - measurment of wavelength. Rayleigh\'s criterion for resolution of
            grating- Resolving power and dispersive power of grating.
        </item>
        <item>Polarization and Superconductors</item>
        <item>Polarization of Light: Types of polarized light. Double refraction. Nicol Prism.
            Quarter wave plate and half wave plate. Production and detection of circularly and
            elliptically polarized light. Induced birefringence- Kerr Cell - Polaroid and
            applications. Superconductivity: Superconducting phenomena. Meissner effect. Type-I and
            Type-II superconductors. BCS theory (qualitative). High temperature superconductors -
            Applications of superconductors.
        </item>
        <item>Quantum Mechanics and Statistical Mechanics</item>
        <item>Quantum Mechanics: Uncertainty principle and its applications-formulation of time
            dependent and Time independent SchrOdinger equations- physical meaning of wave function-
            Energy and momentum Operators-Eigen values and functions- One dimensional infinite
            square well potential .Quantum mechanical \'Funnelling (Qualitative) Statistical
            Mechanics: Macrostates and Microstates. Phase space. Basic postulates of Maxwell-
            Boltzmann, Bose-Einstein and Fermi Dirac statistics. Distribution equations in the three
            cases (no derivation). Fermi Level and its significance.
        </item>
        <item>Acoustics and Ultrasonics</item>
        <item>Acoustics: Intensity of sound- Loudness-Absorption coefficient -Reverberation and
            reverberation time- Significance of reverberation time-Sabine\'s formula (No derivation)
            -Factors affecting acoustics of a building.
            Ultrasonics: Production of ultrasonic waves - Magnetostriction effect and Piezoelectric
            effect - Magnetostriction oscillator and Piezoelectric oscillator - Detection of
            ultrasonics -thermal and piezoelectric methods-Applications of ultrasonics - NDT and
            medical.
        </item>
        <item>Laser and Photonics</item>
        <item>Laser: Properties of Lasers, absorption, spontaneous and stimulated emissions,
            Population inversion, Einstein\'s coefficients, Working principle of laser,Optical
            resonant cavity. Ruby Laser, Helium-Neon Laser, Semiconductor Laser (qualitative).
            Applications of laser, holography (Recording and reconstruction)
            Photonics: Basics of solid state lighting - LED — Photodetectors - photo voltaic cell,
            junction and avalanche photo diodes, photo transistors, thermal detectors, Solar cells-
            I-V characteristics - Optic fibre-Principle of propagation-numerical aperture-optic
            communication system (block diagram) - Industrial, medical and technological
            applications of optical fibre. Fibre optic sensors - Basics of Intensity modulated and
            phase modulated sensors.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="be100">
        <item>EM</item>
        <item>MAIN TEXTS\n\n(1) Shames. I. H., Engineering Mechanics - Statics and Dynamics, Pearson
            Prentice \n(2) Timoshenko, S. and Young D. H., Engineering Mechanics, McGraw Hill
            \n\nREFERENCE BOOKS: \n\n1. Babu. J.. Engineering Mechanics, Pearson Prentice Hall \n2.
            Beer and Johnson, Vector Mechanics for Engineers - Statics and Dynamics, Tata McGraw
            Hill Publishing Company Limited \n3. Benjamin J.. Engineering Mechanics. Pentex Book
            Publishers and Distributors \n4. Bhavikkatti, S. S.. Engineering Mechanics, New Age
            International Publishers \n5. Hibbeler, R. C., Engineering Mechanics: Statics and
            Dynamics. Pearson Prentice Hall \n6. Kumar. K. L.. Engineering Mechanics. Tata McGraw
            Hill Publishing Company Limited \n7. Merriam J. L. and Kraige L. G.. Engineering
            Mechanics — Vol. 1 and 2 John Wiley \n8. Rajasekaran S. and Sankarasubramanian, G.,
            Engineering Mechanics, Vikas Publishing House Private Limited \n9. Tayal, A. K.,
            Engineering Mechanics- Statics and Dynamics, Umesh Publications
        </item>
        <item>Four</item>
        <item>NONE</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Statics: Fundamental concepts and laws of mechanics — Rigid body —Principle of
            transmissibility of forces Coplanar force systems - Moment of a force — Principle of
            moments Resultant of force and couple system Equilibrium of rigid body — Free body
            diagram — Conditions of equilibrium in two dimensions — Two force and three force
            members.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Types of supports — Problems involving point loads and uniformly distributed loads
            only. Force systems in space — Degrees of freedom — Free body diagram —Equations of
            equilibrium — Simple resultant and Equilibrium problems.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Properties of planar surfaces — Centroid and second moment of area (Derivations not
            required) - Parallel and perpendicular axis theorem — Centroid and Moment of Inertia of
            composite area. Polar Moment of Inertia — Radius of gyration — Mass moment of inertia of
            cylinder and thin disc (No derivations required). Product of inertia — Principal Moment
            of Inertia (conceptual level). Theorems of Pappus and Guldinus.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Friction — Characteristics of dry friction — Problems involving friction of ladder,
            wedges and connected bodies. Definition of work and virtual work — Principle of virtual
            work for a system of connection bodies — Problems on determinate beams only.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Dynamics: Rectangular and Cylindrical co-ordinate system Combined motion of rotation
            and translation — Concept of instantaneous centre — Motion of connecting rod of piston
            and crank of a reciprocating pump. Rectilinear translation — Newton\'s second law —
            D\'Alembert\'s Principle — Application to connected bodies (Problems on motion of lin
            only).
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Mechanical vibrations — Free and forced vibration - Degree of freedom. Simple harmonic
            motion — Spring-mass model — Period — Stiffness —Frequency — Simple numerical problems
            of single degree of freedom.
        </item>
    </array>


</resources>