<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <array name="me201">
        <item>MS</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to analysis of deformable bodies – internal forces – method of sections –
            assumptions and limitations. Stress – stresses due to normal, shear and bearing loads –
            strength design of simple members. Definition of linear and shear strains. Material
            behavior – uniaxial tension test – stress-strain diagrams concepts of orthotropy,
            anisotropy and inelastic behavior – Hooke’s law for linearly elastic isotropic material
            under axial and shear deformation Deformation in axially loaded bars – thermal effects –
            statically indeterminate problems – principle of superposition - elastic strain energy
            for uniaxial stress.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Definition of stress and strain at a point (introduction to stress and strain tensors
            and its components only) – Poisson’s ratio – biaxial and triaxial deformations – Bulk
            modulus - Relations between elastic. Torsion: Shafts - torsion theory of elastic
            circular bars – assumptions and limitations – polar modulus - torsional rigidity –
            economic cross-sections – statically indeterminate problems – shaft design for torsional
            load.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Beams- classification - diagrammatic conventions for supports and loading - axial
            force, shear force and bending moment in a beam. Shear force and bending moment diagrams
            by direct approach. Differential equations between load, shear force and bending moment.
            Shear force and bending moment diagrams by summation approach – elastic curve – point of
            inflection.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Stresses in beams: Pure bending – flexure formula for beams assumptions and
            limitations – section modulus - flexural rigidity economic sections – beam of uniform
            strength. Shearing stress formula for beams – assumptions and limitations – design for
            flexure and shear.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Deflection of beams: Moment-curvature relation – assumptions and limitations - double
            integration method – Macaulay’s method superposition techniques – moment area method and
            conjugate beam ideas for simple cases. Transformation of stress and strains: Plane state
            of stress - equations of transformation - principal planes and stresses.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Mohr’s circles of stress – plane state of strain – analogy between stress and strain
            transformation – strain rosettes. Compound stresses: Combined axial, flexural and shear
            loads – eccentric loading under tension/compression - combined bending and twisting
            loads.Theory of columns: Buckling theory –Euler’s formula for long columns – assumptions
            and limitations – effect of end conditions - slenderness ratio – Rankin’s formula for
            intermediate columns.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me202">
        <item>AMS</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to stress analysis in elastic solids - stress at a point – stress tensor
            – stress components in rectangular and polar coordinate systems - Cauchy’s equations –
            stress transformation – principal stresses and planes - hydrostatic and deviatoric
            stress components, octahedral shear stress - equations of equilibrium.\nDisplacement
            field – engineering strain - strain tensor (basics only) – analogy between stress and
            strain tensors - strain-displacement relations (small-strain only) – compatibility
            conditions .
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Constitutive equations – generalized Hooke’s law – equations for linear elastic
            isotropic solids - relation among elastic constants – Boundary conditions – St. Venant’s
            principle for end effects – uniqueness theorem.\n2 -D problems in elasticity - Plane
            stress and plane strain problems – stress compatibility equation - Airy’s stress
            function and equation – polynomial method of solution – solution for bending of a
            cantilever with an end load
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Equations in polar coordinates (2D) – equilibrium equation, straindisplacement
            relations, conversion of Airy\'s equation and definition of stress function and stress
            components.\nApplication of stress function to Lame’s problem - stress concentration
            problem of a small hole in a large plate.\nAxisymmetric problems – governing equations –
            application to thick cylinders, interference fit and rotating discs.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Unsymmetrical bending of straight beams – curved beams (rectangular c/s) - shear
            center – shear stresses in thin walled open sections\nStrain energy of deformation –
            special cases of a body subjected to concentrated loads, moment or torque - reciprocal
            relation – strain energy of a bar subjected to axial force, shear force, bending moment
            and torque.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Maxwell reciprocal theorem – Castigliano’s first and second theorems – virtual work
            principle – minimum potential energy theorem - complementary energy theorem.\nTorsion of
            non-circular bars: Saint Venant’s theory - solutions for circular and elliptical
            cross-sections.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Prandtl’s method - solutions for circular and elliptical cross-sections - membrane
            analogy - approximate solution methods for non-circular shafts.\nTorsion of thin walled
            tubes, thin rectangular sections, rolled sections and multiply connected sections.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="me203">
        <item>MF</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction: Fluids and continuum, Physical properties of fluids, density, specific
            weight, vapour pressure, Newton’s law of viscosity. Ideal and real fluids, Newtonian and
            non-Newtonian fluids. Fluid Statics- Pressure-density-height relationship, manometers,
            pressure on plane and curved surfaces, center of pressure, buoyancy, stability of
            immersed and floating bodies, fluid masses subjected to uniform accelerations,
            measurement of pressure.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Kinematics of fluid flow: Eulerian and Lagrangian approaches, classification of fluid
            flow, 1-D, 2-D and 3-D flow, steady, unsteady, uniform, non-uniform, laminar, turbulent,
            rotational, irrotational flows, stream lines, path lines, streak lines, stream tubes,
            velocity and acceleration in fluid, circulation and vorticity, stream function and
            potential function, Laplace equation, equipotential lines flow nets, uses and
            limitations.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Dynamics of Fluid flow: Fluid Dynamics: Energies in flowing fluid, head, pressure,
            dynamic, static and total head, Control volume analysis of mass, momentum and energy,
            Equations of fluid dynamics: Differential equations of mass, energy and momentum
            (Euler’s equation), Navier-Stokes equations (without proof) in rectangular and
            cylindrical co-ordinates, Bernoulli’s equation and its applications: Venturi and Orifice
            meters, Notches and Weirs (description only for notches and weirs). Hydraulic
            coefficients, Velocity measurements: Pitot tube and Pitot-static tube.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Pipe Flow: Viscous flow: Reynolds experiment to classify laminar and turbulent flows,
            significance of Reynolds number, critical Reynolds number, shear stress and velocity
            distribution in a pipe, law of fluid friction, head loss due to friction, Hagen
            Poiseuille equation. Turbulent flow: Darcy- Weisbach equation, Chezy’s equation Moody’s
            chart, Major and minor energy losses, hydraulic gradient and total energy line, flow
            through long pipes, pipes in series, pipes in parallel, equivalent pipe, siphon,
            transmission of power through pipes, efficiency of transmission, Water hammer,
            Cavitation.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Concept of Boundary Layer : Growth of boundary layer over a flat plate and definition
            of boundary layer thickness, displacement thickness, momentum thickness and energy
            thickness, laminar and turbulent boundary layers, laminar sub layer, velocity profile,
            Von- Karman momentum integral equations for the boundary layers, calculation of drag,
            separation of boundary and methods of control.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Dimensional Analysis and Hydraulic similitude: Dimensional analysis, Buckingham’s
            theorem, important dimensional numbers and their significance, geometric, Kinematic and
            dynamic similarity, model studies. Froude, Reynold, Weber, Cauchy and Mach laws-
            Applications and limitations of model testing, simple problems only.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me204">
        <item>Thermal Engineering</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Steam engineering- T- S diagram, Mollier chart, Steam cycles- Rankine cycle, Modified
            Rankine cycle, Relative efficiency, Improvement in steam cycles-Reheat, Regenerative and
            Binary vapor cycle Steam Boilers: Types of boilers –Cochran boiler, Babcock and Wilcox
            boiler, Benson boiler, La Mont boiler, Loeffler boiler, Velox boiler, Boiler Mountings
            and Accessories Steam nozzles:-Types of nozzle- Velocity of steam, mass flow rate,
            critical pressure ratio and its significance, effect of friction, super saturated flow
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Steam turbines: classification, compounding of turbines-pressure velocity variation,
            velocity diagrams, work done, efficiency, condition for maximum efficiency, multistage
            turbines-condition line, stage efficiency. Steam turbine performance-reheat factor,
            degree of reaction, cycles with reheating and regenerative heating, governing of
            turbines
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Internal combustion engines: classification of I.C. Engines- four stroke and two
            stroke I.C. Engines, Comparison of four stroke and two stroke Engine. Wankel Engine, Air
            standard cycle-Carnot cycle, Otto cycle; Diesel cycle, dual combustion cycle, comparison
            of Otto, diesel and dual combustion cycles. Stirling and Ericsson cycles, air standard
            efficiency, specific work output, work ratio, Actual cycle analysis, deviation of actual
            engine cycle from ideal cycle. Rotary engines, Stratified charge engine , super charging
            of SI and CI Engines – turbo charging. Variable specific heats.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Performance Testing of I C Engines: Indicator diagram, mean effective pressure.
            Torque, Engine power- BHP, IHP. Engine efficiencymechanical efficiency, volumetric
            efficiency, thermal efficiency and relative efficiency, Specific fuel consumption.
            Testing of I C enginesMorse test, Heat balance test and Retardation test Fuels and fuel
            combustion: flash point and fire point, calorific value, Fuels for SI and CI engine,
            Important qualities of SI and CI engine fuels, Rating of SI engine and CI engine fuels,
            Dopes, Additives, Gaseous fuels, LPG, CNG, Biogas, Producer gas. Analysis of fuel
            combustion-A/F ratio, equivalence ratio, minimum quantity of air, flue gas analysis,
            excess air.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Air pollution from I.C. Engine and its remedies: Pollutants from S.I. and C.I.
            Engines, Methods of emission control, alternative fuels for I.C. Engines; the blending
            of fuels, Bio fuels. Combustion in I.C. Engines: Combustion phenomena in S.I. engines;
            Ignition limits, stages of combustion in S.I. Engines, Ignition lag, velocity of flame
            propagation, auto ignition, detonation; effects of engine variables on detonation;
            theories of detonation, octane rating of fuels; pre-ignition; S.I. engine combustion
            chambers. Stages of combustion in C.I. Engines; delay period; variables affecting delay
            period; knock in C.I. engines, Cetane rating; C.I. engine combustion chambers.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Gas turbines: classification, Thermodynamic analysis of gas turbine cycles-open ,
            closed and semi closed cycle; ideal working cycle- Brayton cycle-P-v and T-s diagram,
            thermal efficiency. Effect of compressor and turbine efficiencies. Optimum pressure
            ratio for maximum specific work output with and without considering machine
            efficiencies. Comparison of gas turbine and IC engines, Analysis of open cycle gas
            turbine, Improvements of the basic gas turbine cycles-regeneration, intercooling and
            reheating-cycle efficiency and work output-Condition for minimum compressor work and
            maximum turbine work. Combustion chambers for gas turbines. pressure loss in combustion
            process and stability loop.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me205">
        <item>Thermodynamics</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Role of Thermodynamics in Engineering and Science -- Applications of Thermodynamics
            Basic Concepts - Macroscopic and Microscopic viewpoints, Concept of Continuum,
            Thermodynamic System and Control Volume, Surrounding, Boundaries, Types of Systems,
            Universe, Thermodynamic properties, Process, Cycle, Thermodynamic Equilibrium, Quasi –
            static Process, State, Point and Path function. (Review only- self study) Zeroth Law of
            Thermodynamics, Measurement of TemperatureThermometry, reference Points, Temperature
            Scales, Ideal gas temperature scale, Comparison of thermometers-Gas Thermometers,
            Thermocouple, Resistance thermometer Energy - Work - Pdv work and other types of work
            transfer, free expansion work, heat and heat capacity.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Joule’s Experiment- First law of Thermodynamics - First law applied to Non flow
            Process- Enthalpy- specific heats- PMM1, First law applied to Flow Process, Mass and
            Energy balance in simple steady flow process. Applications of SFEE, Transient flow
            –Filling and Emptying Process. (Problems), Limitations of the First Law.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Second Law of Thermodynamics, Thermal Reservoir, Heat Engine, Heat pump - Performance
            factors, Kelvin-Planck and Clausius Statements, Equivalence of two statements,
            Reversibility, Irreversible Process, Causes of Irreversibility, Corollaries of second
            law, PMM2, Carnot’s theorem and its corollaries, Absolute Thermodynamic Temperature
            scale. Clausius Inequality, Entropy- Causes of Entropy Change, Entropy changes in
            various thermodynamic processes, principle of increase of entropy and its applications,
            Entropy generation in open and closed system, Entropy and Disorder, Reversible adiabatic
            process- isentropic process
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Available Energy, Availability and Irreversibility- Useful work, Dead state,
            Availability function, Availability and irreversibility in open and closed systems -
            Gouy-Stodola theorem , Third law of thermodynamics. Pure Substances, Phase
            Transformations, Triple point, properties during change of phase, T-v, p-v and p-T
            diagram of pure substance, p-v-T surface, Saturation pressure and Temperature, T-h and
            T-s diagrams, h-s diagrams or Mollier Charts, Dryness Fraction, steam tables. Property
            calculations using steam tables.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>The ideal Gas Equation, Characteristic and Universal Gas constants, Deviations from
            ideal Gas Model: Equation of state of real substancesVander Waals Equation of State,
            Berthelot, Dieterici, and Redlich-Kwong equations of state , Virial Expansion,
            Compressibility factor, Law of corresponding state, Compressibility charts Mixtures of
            ideal Gases – Mole Fraction, Mass fraction, Gravimetric and volumetric Analysis,
            Dalton’s Law of partial pressure, Amagat’s Laws of additive volumes, Gibbs-Dalton’s law
            -Equivalent Gas constant and Molecular Weight, Properties of gas mixtures: Internal
            Energy, Enthalpy, specific heats and Entropy, Introduction to real gas mixtures- Kay’s
            rule. *Introduction to ideal binary solutions, Definition of solution, ideal binary
            solutions and their characteristics, Deviation from ideality, Raoult’s Law, Phase
            diagram, Lever rule(*in this section numerical problems not )
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>General Thermodynamic Relations – Combined First and Second law equations – Helmholtz
            and Gibb’s functions - Maxwell’s Relations, Tds Equations. The Clapeyron Equation,
            equations for internal energy, enthalpy and entropy, specific heats, Throttling process,
            Joule Thomson Coefficient, inversion curve. #Introduction to thermodynamics of
            chemically reacting systems, Combustion, Thermochemistry – Theoretical and Actual
            combustion processes- Definition and significance of equivalence ratio, enthalpy of
            formation , enthalpy of combustion and heating value (in this section numerical problems
            not included)
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me206">
        <item>Fluid Machinery</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Impact of jets: Introduction to hydrodynamic thrust of jet on a fixed and moving
            surface (flat and curve),– Series of vanes - work done and efficiency Hydraulic Turbines
            : Impulse and Reaction Turbines – Degree of reaction – Pelton Wheel – Constructional
            features - Velocity triangles – Euler’s equation – Speed ratio, jet ratio and work done
            , losses and efficiencies, design of Pelton wheel – Inward and outward flow reaction
            turbines- Francis Turbine – Constructional features – Velocity triangles, work done and
            efficiencies.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Axial flow turbine (Kaplan) Constructional features – Velocity triangles- work done
            and efficiencies – Characteristic curves of turbines – theory of draft tubes – surge
            tanks – Cavitation in turbines – Governing of turbines – Specific speed of turbine ,
            Type Number– Characteristic curves, scale Laws – Unit speed – Unit discharge and unit
            power.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Rotary motion of liquids – free, forced and spiral vortex flows Rotodynamic pumps-
            centrifugal pump impeller types,-velocity triangles-manometric head- work, efficiency
            and losses, H-Q characteristic, typical flow system characteristics, operating point of
            a pump. Cavitation in centrifugal pumps- NPSH required and availableType number-Pumps in
            series and parallel operations. Performance characteristics- Specific speed-Shape
            numbers – Impeller shapes based on shape numbers.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Positive displacement pumps- reciprocating pump – Single acting and double acting-
            slip, negative slip and work required and efficiencyindicator diagram- acceleration head
            - effect of acceleration and friction on indicator diagram – speed calculation- Air
            vessels and their purposes, saving in work done to air vessels multi cylinder pumps.
            Multistage pumps-selection of pumps-pumping devices-hydraulic ram, Accumulator,
            Intensifier, Jet pumps, gear pumps, vane pump and lobe pump.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Compressors: classification of compressors, reciprocating compressor-single stage
            compressor, equation for work with and without clearance volume, efficiencies,
            multistage compressor, intercooler, free air delivered (FAD)
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Centrifugal compressor-working, velocity diagram, work done, power required, width of
            blades of impeller and diffuser, isentropic efficiency, slip factor and pressure
            coefficient, surging and chocking. Axial flow compressors:- working, velocity diagram,
            degree of reaction, performance. Roots blower, vane compressor, screw compressor.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me210">
        <item>MME</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Earlier and present development of atomic structure; attributes of ionization energy
            and conductivity, electronegativity and alloying; correlation of atomic radius to
            strength; electron configurations; electronic repulsion Primary bonds: - characteristics
            of covalent, ionic and metallic bond: attributes of bond energy, cohesive force,
            density, directional and non-directional and ductility. properties based on atomic
            bonding:- attributes of deeper energy well and shallow energy well to melting
            temperature, coefficient of thermal expansion - attributes of modulus of elasticity in
            metal cutting process -Secondary bonds:- classification- hydrogen bond and anomalous
            behavior of ice float on water, application- atomic mass unit and specific heat,
            application. (brief review only, no University questions and internal assessment from
            these portions). \nCrystallography:- Crystal, space lattice, unit cell- BCC, FCC, HCP
            structures - short and long range order - effects of crystalline and amorphous structure
            on mechanical properties. \nCoordination number and radius ratio; theoretical density;
            simple problems - Polymorphism and allotropy. \nMiller Indices: - crystal plane and
            direction (brief review) - Attributes of miller indices for slip system, brittleness of
            BCC, HCP and ductility of FCC - Modes of plastic deformation: - Slip and twinning.
            \nSchmid\'s law, equation, critical resolved shear stress, correlation of slip system
            with plastic deformation in metals and applications.\n
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Mechanism of crystallization: Homogeneous and heterogeneous nuclei formation, under
            cooling, dendritic growth, grain boundary irregularity. \n Effects of grain size, grain
            size distribution, grain shape, grain orientation on dislocation/strength and creep
            resistance - Hall - Petch theory, simple problems \nClassification of crystal
            imperfections: - types of dislocation – effect of point defects on mechanical properties
            - forest of dislocation, role of surface defects on crack initiation.\nBurgers vector
            –dislocation source, significance of Frank Read source in metals deformation -
            Correlation of dislocation density with strength and nano concept, applications.
            \nSignificance high and low angle grain boundaries on dislocation – driving force for
            grain growth and applications during heat treatment. \nPolishing and etching to
            determine the microstructure and grain size. \nFundamentals and crystal structure
            determination by X – ray diffraction, simple problems –SEM and TEM. \nDiffusion in
            solids, Fick’s laws, mechanisms, applications of diffusion in mechanical engineering,
            simple problems.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Phase diagrams: - Limitations of pure metals and need of alloying - classification of
            alloys, solid solutions, Hume Rothery`s rule - equilibrium diagram of common types of
            binary systems: five types.\nCoring - lever rule and Gibb`s phase rule - Reactions: -
            monotectic, eutectic, eutectoid, peritectic, peritectoid. \n Detailed discussion on
            Iron-Carbon equilibrium diagram with microstructure and properties changes in austenite,
            ledeburite, ferrite, cementite, special features of martensite transformation, bainite,
            spheroidite etc. \nHeat treatment: - Definition and necessity – TTT for a eutectoid
            iron–carbon alloy, CCT diagram, applications - annealing, normalizing, hardening,
            spheroidizing.\nTempering:- austermpering, martempering and ausforming - Comparative
            study on ductility and strength with structure of pearlite, bainite, spherodite,
            martensite, tempered martensite and ausforming. \nHardenability, Jominy end quench test,
            applications- Surface hardening methods:- no change in surface composition methods :-
            Flame, induction, laser and electron beam hardening processes- change in surface
            composition methods :carburizing and Nitriding; applications.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Types of Strengthening mechanisms: - work hardening, equation - precipitation
            strengthening and over ageing- dispersion hardening.\nCold working: Detailed discussion
            on strain hardening; recovery; re-rystallization, effect of stored energy; re-
            crystallization temperature - hot working Bauschinger effect and attributes in metal
            forming.Alloy steels:- Effects of alloying elements on steel: dislocation movement,
            polymorphic transformation temperature, alpha and beta stabilizers, formation and
            stability of carbides, grain growth, displacement of the eutectoid point, retardation of
            the transformation rates, improvement in corrosion resistance, mechanical properties .
            \nNickel steels, Chromium steels etc. - Enhancement of steel properties by adding
            alloying elements: - Molybdenum, Nickel, Chromium, Vanadium, Tungsten, Cobalt, Silicon,
            Copper and Lead. \nHigh speed steels:- Mo and W types, effect of different alloying
            elements in HSS \nCast irons: Classifications; grey, white, malleable and spheroidal
            graphite cast iron etc, composition, microstructure, properties and applications. \n
            Principal Non ferrous Alloys: - Aluminum, Copper, Magnesium, Nickel, study of
            composition, properties, applications, reference shall be made to the phase diagrams
            whenever necessary.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Fatigue: - Stress cycles – Primary and secondary stress raisers - Characteristics of
            fatigue failure, fatigue tests, S-N curve.\nFactors affecting fatigue strength: stress
            concentration, size effect, surface roughness, change in surface properties, surface
            residual stress. \nWays to improve fatigue life – effect of temperature on fatigue,
            thermal fatigue and its applications in metal cutting.\nFracture: – Brittle and ductile
            fracture – Griffith theory of brittle fracture – Stress concentration, stress raiser –
            Effect of plastic deformation on crack propagation. \ntransgranular, intergranular
            fracture - Effect of impact loading on ductile material and its application in forging,
            applications - Mechanism of fatigue failure. \nStructural features of fatigue: - crack
            initiation, growth, propagation - Fracture toughness (definition only) - Ductile to
            brittle transition temperature (DBTT) in steels and structural changes during DBTT,
            applications.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Creep: - Creep curves – creep tests - Structural change:- deformation by slip,
            sub-grain formation, grain boundary sliding.\nMechanism of creep deformation - threshold
            for creep, prevention against creep - Super plasticity: need and
            applications.\nComposites:- Need of development of composites - geometrical and spatial
            Characteristics of particles – classification - fiber phase: - characteristics,
            classifications - matrix phase:- functions – only need and characteristics of PMC, MMC,
            and CMC – applications of composites: aircraft applications, aerospace equipment and
            instrument structure, industrial applications of composites, marine applications,
            composites in the sporting goods industry, composite biomaterials.\nModern engineering
            materials: - only fundamentals, need, properties and applications of, intermetallics,
            maraging steel, super alloys, Titanium – introduction to nuclear materials, smart
            materials and bio materials.\nCeramics:-coordination number and radius ratios- AX, AmXp,
            AmBmXp type structures – applications.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me220">
        <item>Manufacturing Technology</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Sand Casting – Sand Molds-Types of Molding Sands and Testing . Type of patterns -
            Pattern Materials. Cores –Types and applications –Sand Molding Machines. Gating System –
            Risering. Shell Mold Casting – Ceramic Mold Casting. Investment Casting – Vacuum Casting
            – Slush Casting. Pressure Casting – Die Casting – Centrifugal Casting. Design
            Considerations based on Various Shapes - Defects in Castings – simple problems in
            casting.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Principles of Rolling –Types of rolling mills, Mechanics of Flat Rolling. Roll Force
            and Power Requirement - Neutral Point. Hot and Cold Rolling.Defects in Rolled Plates -
            Rolling Mills.Ring Rolling – Thread Rolling. Applications- Rolling of tubes, wheels,
            axles and I-beams
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Classification of forging – Forging methods – Forging under sticking condition.
            Precision Forging – Coining – Heading – Piercing. Die Design:- Preshaping, Design
            Features, Draft Angles – Die Materials and Lubrication. Forging Machines – Forging
            Defects and tests. Extrusion Process - Hot Extrusion – Cold Extrusion. Impact Extrusion
            – Extrusion Defects – Drawing Process, wire drawing process.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Principles Location - Degrees of Freedom, 3-2-1 principle of locating. Locating from
            Planes - Locating from Circular Surfaces. Concentric Locating - Principles of Clamping.
            Types of Clamps - Strap Clamps Slide Clamps - Swing Clamps - Hinge Clamps. Vacuum
            Clamping - Magnetic Clamping
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Sheet metal characteristics – Typical shearing.Bending Sheet and Plate – Spingback -
            Bending Force. Press Brake Forming - Tube Bending. Stretch Forming - Deep Drawing.
            Rubber forming - Spinning Shear Spinning - Tube Spinning. Definition of Welding -
            Weldability – Solidification of the Weld Metal. Heat Affected Zone – correlation of
            strength of welded joint with structure - Welding Defects
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Gas Welding: – Flame Characteristics. Equipment, fluxes and filler rods. Arc Welding –
            Applications and Equipment. Electrodes. Shielded Metal Arc Welding- Submerged Arc
            Welding. GTAW – Plasma Arc Welding. Ultrasonic Welding – Friction Welding. Resistance
            Spot Welding. Resistance Seam Welding – Stud Welding – Percussion Welding - simple
            problems in welding. Brazing:- Filler Metals, Methods - Soldering:- Techniques, Types of
            Solders and Fluxes
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="me301">
        <item>MM</item>

        <item>Introduction to kinematics and mechanisms</item>
        <item> Various mechanisms, kinematic diagrams, degree of freedom- Grashof’scriterion,
            inversions, coupler curves straight line mechanisms exact, approximate – Ackerman
            Steering Mechanism - Hooke’s joint - Geneva mechanism -mechanical advantage,
            transmission angle
        </item>
        <item>Displacement, velocity and acceleration analysis</item>
        <item> Relative motion - relative velocity - instant centre -Kennedy’s theorem Relative
            acceleration - Coriolis acceleration - graphical and analytical methods – complex number
            methods – computer oriented methods. Cams - classification of cam and followers –
            displacement diagrams, velocity and acceleration analysis of SHM, uniform velocity,
            uniform acceleration, cycloidal motion
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Graphical cam profile synthesis, pressure angle Analysis of tangent cam with roller
            follower and circular cam with flat follower Introduction to polynomial cams.
        </item>
        <item>Gears</item>
        <item>Gears – terminology of spur gears – law of Gearing - involute
            spur gears involutometry - contact ratio - interference - backlash -
            gear standardization – interchangability
            Non-standard gears, centre distance modification, long and short
            addendum system. - internal gears - theory and details of bevel,
            helical and worm gearing

        </item>
        <item>Gear trains</item>
        <item>Simple and compound gear trains - planetary gear trains – differential -solution of
            planetary gear train problems –applications Kinematic synthesis ( planar mechanisms) -
            tasks of kinematic synthesis – type, number and dimensional synthesis – precision
            points. Graphical synthesis for motion - path and prescribed timing -function generator
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>2 position and 3 position synthesis – overlay Method Analytical synthesis techniques,
            Freudenstein&apos;s equation –complex number methods - one case study in synthesis of
            mechanism.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me303">
        <item>MTDM</item>

        <item>Introduction to metal cutting</item>
        <item>Tool nomenclature – Attributes of each tool nomenclature – Attributes of feed and tool
            nomenclature on surface roughness obtainable Orthogonal and oblique cutting - Mechanism
            of metal removal –Primary and secondary deformation shear zones Mechanism of chip
            formation – Types of chips, need and types of chip breakers – Merchant’s theory.
            Analysis of cutting forces in orthogonal cutting– Work done, power required (simple
            problems) Friction forces in metal cutting – development of cutting tool materials.
            Thermal aspects of machining -Tool wear and wear mechanisms. Factors affecting tool
            life– Economics of machining (simple problems) Cutting fluids
        </item>
        <item>General purpose machine tools </item>
        <item>Principle and operation of lathe –Types of lathes and size specification. Work holding
            parts of lathes and their functions – Main operations.
            Taper turning and thread cutting attachments Feeding mechanisms, Apron mechanisms
            Drilling Machines – Types – Work holding devices Tool holding devices – Drill machine
            operations Drilling machine tools – Twist drill nomenclature- cutting forces in
            drilling.
        </item>
        <item>Reciprocating machines</item>
        <item>Shaping machines – Types – Size –Principal parts – Mechanism Work holding devices –
            operations performed – Tools
            Cutting speed, feed and depth of cut – Machining time. Slotting machines – Types – Size
            – principal parts – Mechanism –Work holding devices
            Operations performed – Tools – Cutting speed, feed and depth of cut
            Planing machines – Types – Size – Principal parts – Mechanism –
            Work holding devices
            Operations performed – Tools – Cutting speed, feed and depth of cut – Machining time-
            Surface roughness obtainable.

        </item>
        <item>Milling machines</item>
        <item>Types – Principal parts – Milling mechanism Work holding devices – Milling machine
            attachments Types of milling cutters – Elements of plain milling cutters
            Nomenclature - Cutting forces in milling – Milling cutter materials Up milling, down
            milling and face milling operations Calculation of machining time Indexing – Simple
            indexing – Differential indexing
        </item>
        <item>Grinding machines</item>
        <item>Classification – Operations – Surface,cylindrical and centreless grinding
            Grinding mechanisms – Grinding wheels: Specification – types of abrasives, grain size
            Types of bond, grade, structure – Marking system of grinding wheels – Selection of
            grinding wheels
            Glazing and loading of wheels – Dressing and Truing of grinding wheels, surface
            roughness obtainable
            Superfinishing operations: Lapping operation– Types of hand lapping – Lapping machines –
            Types of honing –Methods of honing Types of honing stones – Honing conditions – Cutting
            fluids –Types of broaches – Force required for broaching – Surface roughness obtainable
            in lapping, honing and broaching operations. Semi-automatic machine tools – Turret and
            capstan lathes. Automatic machine tools – Single and multi-spindle machines
        </item>
        <item>Introduction to Digital Manufacturing</item>
        <item>Concepts and research and development status of digital manufacturing
            Definition of digital manufacturing – Features and development of digital manufacturing.
            Theory system of digital manufacturing science: Operation Mode and Architecture of
            Digital Manufacturing System
            Operation reference mode of digital manufacturing system –Architecture of digital
            manufacturing system Modeling theory and method of digital manufacturing science
            Critical modeling theories and technologies of digital manufacturing science
            Theory system of digital manufacturing science – Basic architecture model of digital
            manufacturing system.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me305">
        <item>CP</item>

        <item>Introduction to Computer programming concept</item>
        <item>Internal representation of data - Algorithm and flow chart, Basics of procedure
            oriented and object oriented programming. Introduction to C++: Structure of C++ program;
            Keywords; Identifiers; Data types – integer, real, character, string, boolean,
            enumeration, Constant and Variables; Operators – assignment, arithmetic, relational,
            logical, increment, decrement and conditional operators;Statements – simple &amp;
            compound, declaration statements. Input and output streams.
        </item>
        <item>Control statements</item>
        <item>if, if-else, switch, for, while, do-while, break and continue statements, Arrays – one
            dimensional &amp; two dimensional; Functions: inline functions, function over loading,
            Functions
            with default arguments, recursion
        </item>
        <item>Basics of Pointers.</item>
        <item>Function call by value, call by reference. Preparation of programs for evaluation of
            Factorial of a number, infinite series, Sorting, Searching and Matrix multiplication
        </item>
        <item>Introduction to Class and Object</item>
        <item>Definition, data members, member function. private &amp; public member functions,
            member access, friend declaration, class objects, predefined classes, initialization.
            Inheritance- base class and derived class. Simple programs using the above features. (No
            programming questions for University examination and internals)
        </item>
        <item>Errors and approximations</item>
        <item>Sources of errors. Solution of linear system of equations: Gauss elimination,
            Gauss-Jordan and Gauss–Seidel methods. Interpolation: Lagrange and Aitken techniques.
        </item>
        <item>Curve fitting</item>
        <item>Method of least squares, non-linear relationships, Linear correlation, measures of
            correlation. Solution of Partial differential equations: classification, Laplace
            equation, Finite difference method. Numerical problems and preparation of computer
            programs for the above methods
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me361">
        <item>AFM</item>
        <item>Basic Concepts and Fundamentals</item>
        <item>Fluid statics, Cartesian Tensors, Fluid Kinematics, and Description of fluid motion
            –Types of motion of fluid elements, Vorticity and circulation– Concept of rotational and
            irrotational flows. Equation of motion of forced and free vortex flow.
            Stream function and Potential function. Stream function and its relation with velocity
            field. Relation between stream function and stream lines - Relation between stream
            function
            and velocity potential for a 2-D irrotational and incompressible flow.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Relation between stream lines and lines of constant potential. Sketching of stream
            lines. Lagrangian and Eulerian approaches, acceleration, temporal acceleration,
            convective acceleration. Reynolds transport theorem, derivation of continuity and
            momentum equations using Reynolds transport theorem. Problems on the application of
            momentum equation
        </item>
        <item>Potential flow</item>
        <item>Uniform flow, source flow, sink flow, free vortex flow and super imposed flow-source
            and sink pair,doublet, plane source in a uniform flow(flow past a half body), source and
            sink pair in a uniform flow(flow past a Rankine oval body), doublet in a uniform
            flow(flow past a circular cylinder). Pressure distribution on the surface of the
            cylinder. Flow past a cylinder with Circulation, Kutta-Juokowsky’s law. Complex flow
            potential, complex flow potentials for source, sink, vortex and doublet. Potential flow
            between two parallel plates, potential flow in a sector. Introduction to conformal
            transformation, conformal mapping.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Incompressible viscous flow. Concepts of laminar and turbulent flows . Stokes
            viscosity law. Navier Stoke’s equation and significance (Derivation not
            necessary).Simplification of Havier stock equation for steady incompressible flows with
            negligible body forces. Parallel flow through straight channel and couette flow. Hagen -
            Poiseuille flow. Derivation of Hagen Poissuille equations for velocity and discharge
            through a pipe, derivation of friction factor for laminar flow, Couette flow for
            negative, zero and positive pressure gradients, flow in a rotating annulus, Viscometer
            based on rotating annulus
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Boundary layer theory, Boundary layer thickness, Displacement thickness, momentum
            thickness, Energy thickness and their calculation. Laminar Boundary Layers,Boundary
            layer equations; Boundary layer on a flat plate, Prandtl boundary layer equations,
            Blasius solution for flow over a flat plate, Von- Karman momentum integral equations,
            Pohlhausen approximation solution of boundary layer for non-zero pressure gradient flow,
            favorable and adverse pressure gradients, Entry flow into a duct, flow separation and
            vortex shedding.

        </item>
        <item>Turbulent Flow</item>
        <item>Introduction to turbulent flow, Governing equations of turbulent flow, Turbulent
            boundary layer equation, Flat plate turbulent boundary layer, Fully developed Turbulent
            pipe flow for moderate Reynold’s number, Prandtl mixing hypothesis, Turbulence modeling.
            Boundary layer control.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me363">


        <item>CMM</item>

        <item>Composite</item>

        <item>Introduction, definition, characteristics, functions classification of composites
            based on structure and matrix smart composites, advantages and limitations history,
            industrial scene and applications Interfaces: wettability and bonding interface in
            composites
            types of bonding at interface.
        </item>

        <item>Fibers</item>

        <item>Introduction, types of fibers, natural fibers glass fiber fabrication, structure,
            properties and applications boron fiber fabrication, structure, properties and
            applications carbon fiber, Ex-Pan carbon fiber Ex cellulose carbon fiber, Ex-Pitch
            carbon carbon fiber structure, properties and applications aramid fiber fabrication,
            structure, properties and applications whiskers: characteristics, properties and
            applications
        </item>

        <item>Polymer matrix composites </item>

        <item>Thermoset, thermoplastic and elastomeric polymers properties, characteristics and
            applications as matrix materials processing of polymer matrix composites: hand methods,
            Lay up method, spray up method moulding methods, pressure bagging and bag moulding
            methods, pultrusion and filament winding process.
        </item>

        <item>Metal matrix composites (MMC)</item>

        <item>Classification of metals, intermetallics, alloys and their potential role as matrices
            in composites properties, characteristics and applications of metals as matrix materials
            production techniques: powder metallurgy, diffusion bonding, melt stirring squeeze
            casting, liquid infiltration under pressure, spray code position, insitu process.
        </item>

        <item>Ceramic matrix composites (CMC)</item>

        <item>Classification of ceramics and their potential role as matrices,properties,
            characteristics and applications of ceramics as matrix materials conventional techniques
            : cold pressing and sintering, hot pressing,reaction bonding,hot pressing and reaction
            bonding new techniques : liquid infiltration, pultrusion, lanxide process, insitu
            chemical technique, sol-gel technique
        </item>

        <item>Post processing operations</item>

        <item>Machining, cutting, polishing, welding, rivetting and painting Advanced post
            processing methods : ultrasonic welding, plasma coating, Water jet cutting and laser
            machining Micromechanics of composites: maximum stress and strain
            criterion(derivations)Tsai-Hill and Tsai-Wu failure criterion (derivations)mechanics of
            load transfer from matrix to fiber (description)
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="me365">


        <item>AMC</item>


        <item>Design of molds</item>

        <item>Functional requirements of molding materials, type of sands Properties of molding
            sand, sand testing techniques Effect of molding on sand properties, Bonding material
            Mould surface coating Sand design and control Thermal aspect of molding sand, mould wall
            movement

        </item>

        <item>Pouring and feeding Gating
        </item>

        <item>Type of gating- gating design Factor involved in gating design-illustrative problems
            in determination of filling time and discharge rate Aspiration effect- effects of
            friction and velocity distribution
            Risers – primary function of a riser Theoretical consideration Riser design and
            placement Determination of dimensions of rise- blind risers Internal risers-use of
            chills Use of insulators and exothermic compound

        </item>

        <item>Solidification</item>

        <item>Freezing of pure metal Skin effects- nucleation and growth Shrinkage- freezing of
            alloys Effect of mould materials and alloy composition on casting Fluidity- factor
            affecting fluidity- fluidity measurement and application of fluidity Gases in metals-
            degassing Grain refinement Illustrative problems related to determination of
            solidification time
        </item>

        <item>Heat transfer during solidification</item>

        <item>Methods of manipulating heat transfer Experimental methods for the study of heat
            transfer during solidification Crystal growth methods Heat flow in solidification Heat
            transfer with in the solid/liquid metal system Heat transfer at the metal-mould
            interface Heat flow in one dimensional solidification geometries Freezing at mould wall
            Rapid freezing in contact with a cold substrate with initial melt super cooling
        </item>

        <item>Ferrous and non ferrous castings Steel Casting
        </item>

        <item>The family of cast iron Melting of steels and cast irons–Grey iron Foundry practice –
            ductile iron – Malleable Iron casting design
            Aluminum and its alloys: Different Aluminum alloy systems
            Advantage and limitation of Aluminum alloy castings Molding for aluminum castings -
            melting of Aluminum- degassing- grain refinement Modification- effect of various melt
            treatment on the
            mechanical properties of Aluminum castings.
            Magnesium and its alloys: different alloy systems- advantage and limitation of Magnesium
            alloy castings Molding for magnesium casting- melting of Magnesium-
            flux and flux less melting Type and functions of fluxes used- degassing and grain
            refinement- pouring technique.
            Copper alloys: advantage of Copper alloys- melting- drossing-oxygen and hydrogen in
            Copper melting- control of gases- de oxidation

        </item>

        <item>Casting defects and testing</item>

        <item>Functional design- metallurgical design simplification of foundry practice- economic
            considerations design of junction- specification of castings inspection of castings-
            analysis of casting defects nondestructive testing of casting- dye penetrant testing
            magnetic flaw detection, radiography, ultrasonic testing,etc.quality control and quality
            assurance
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="me367">


        <item>NDT</item>

        <item>Introduction to NDT</item>

        <item>Comparison between destructive and NDT,Importance of NDT, Scope of NDT, difficulties
            of NDT, future progress in NDT, economics aspects of NDT.
            Visual Inspection - tools, applications and limitations -Fundamentals of visual testing:
            vision, lighting, material attributes,environmental factors.visual perception, direct
            and indirect methods mirrors, magnifiers,boroscopes, fibroscopes, closed circuit
            television, light sources special lighting, a systems, computer enhanced system
        </item>

        <item>Liquid Penetrant Inspection</item>

        <item> Principles, properties required for a good penetrants and developers - Types of
            penetrants and developers and advantages and limitations of various methods of LPI – LPI
            technique/ test procedure interpretation and evaluation of penetrant test indications,
            false indication and safety precaution required in LPI, applications, advantages and
            limitations

        </item>

        <item>Magnetic Particle Inspection (MPI)</item>

        <item>Principles of MPI, basic physics of magnetism, permeability, flux density, cohesive
            force, magnetizing force, rentivity, residual magnetism Methods of magnetization,
            magnetization techniques such as headshot technique, cold shot technique, central
            conductor testing,magnetization using products using yokes direct and indirect method of
            magnetization, continuous testing of MPI, residual technique of MPI, system sensitivity,
            checking devices in MPI Interpretation of MPI, indications, advantage and limitation of
            MPI.
        </item>

        <item>Ultrasonic Testing</item>

        <item>Principle, types of waves, frequency,velocity, wavelength, reflection, divergence,
            attenuation, mode conversion in ultrasonic UT testing methods contact testing and
            immersion testing, normal beam and straight beam testing, angle beam testing, dual
            crystal probe, ultrasonic testing techniques resonance testing, through transmission
            technique, pulse echotesting technique, instruments used UT, accessories such as
            transducers, types, frequencies, and sizes commonly used. Reference blocks with
            artificially created defects, calibration of equipment, Applications, advantages,
            limitations, A, B and C scan- Time of Flight Diffraction (TOFD).
        </item>

        <item>Radiography Testing</item>

        <item>Principle, electromagnetic radiation sources: X-ray source, production of X-rays, high
            energy X-ray source, gamma ray source - Properties of X-rays and gamma rays Inspection
            techniques like SWSI, DWSI, DWDI, panoramic exposure, real time radiography, films used
            in industrial radiography, types of film, speed of films, qualities of film screens used
            in radiography, quality of a good radiograph, film processing, interpretation,
            evaluation of test results, safety aspects required in radiography applications,
            advantages and limitations of RT
        </item>

        <item>Eddy Current Testing (ECT)</item>

        <item>Principle, physics aspects of ECT like conductivity, permeability, resistivity,
            inductance, inductive reactance, impedance Field factor and lift of effect, edge effect,
            end effect, impedance plane diagram in brief, depth of penetration of ECT, relation
            between frequency and depth of penetration in ECT equipments and accessories, various
            application of ECT such as conductivity measurement, hardness measurement, defect
            detection coating thickness measurement, advantages and limitations of eddy current
            testing
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="me369">
        <item>Tribology</item>


        <item></item>

        <item>Introduction to Tribology- Tribology in Design, Tribology in Industry, Economic
            Aspects of Tribology Tribological Parameters Like Friction, Wear and Lubrication The
            Topography of Engineering Surface, Contact Between Surfaces.Types of Bearings,
            Comparison of Sliding and Rolling Contact Bearings.
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Introduction, Empirical Laws of Friction, Kinds of Friction Causes of Friction,
            Theories of Friction Measurement of Friction Friction of Metals, Ceramic Materials,
            Polymers.Rolling Friction- Laws of Rolling Friction, Relation Between Temperature and
            Friction Stick-Slip, Prevention of Stick-Slip, Consequences of Friction
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Types of Wear, Various Factors Affecting Wear Theories of Wear, Wear Mechanisms
            Measurement of Wear.Wear Regime Maps, Alternative Form of Wear Equations Lubricated and
            Unlubricated Wear of Metals, Materials Used in Different Wear Situations.
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Fundamentals of Viscosity And Viscous Flow Principle and Application of;
            Hydrodynamic Lubrication, Elastrodynamic Lubrication, Boundary and Solid
            Lubrication.Types of Lubricants, Properties of Lubricants Effect of Speed and Load on
            Lubrication, Frictional Polymers.Lubrication in Metal Working: Rolling, Forging, Drawing
            and Extrusion.
        </item>

        <item>Adhesion</item>

        <item>Introduction, Adhesion Effect by Surface Tension, Purely Normal Contact and
            Compression Plus Shear Adhesion in Magnetic Recording Systems Dependence of Adhesion on
            Material and Geometric Properties.
            Bearing Materials: Introduction, Rolling Bearing, Fluid Film Lubricated Bearing, Dry
            Bearing, Bearing Constructions.

        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Introduction To Surface Engineering, Concept and Scope of Surface Engineering.Surface
            Modification – Transformation Hardening, Surface Melting, Thermo chemical Processes
            Surface Coating – Plating and Anoding Processes, Fusion Processes, Vapor Phase
            Processes.Selection of Coating For Wear And Corrosion Resistance,Potential Properties
            and Parameters of Coating
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="me371">


        <item>NE</item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Review of Elementary nuclear physics: Atomic structure – nuclear energy and nuclear
            forces – Nuclear fission. Nuclear reactions and radiations – Principles of radioactive
            decay interactions of an ray with matter – Neutron cross sections and reactions –The
            fission process – Chain reactions
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Basic principles of controlled fusion .Nuclear reactor principles –Reactor
            classification – Critical size. Basic diffusion theory -Slowing down of neutrons –
            Neutrons – Neutron flux and power –Four factor formula – Criticality condition – Basic
            features of reactor control 
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Boiling water reactor . Description of reactor system – Main components –Control and
            safety features .Materials of reactor construction – Fuel , moderator , coolant
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Structural materials – Cladding –Radiation damage,Nuclear fuels : Metallurgy of
            Uranium – General principles of solvent extraction – Reprocessing of irradiated fuel –
            eparation process fuel enrichment .
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Reactor heat removal / equations of heat transfer as applied to reactor cooling–
            Reactor heat transfer systems – Heat removed in fast reactors. Radiation safety :
            Reactor shielding – Radiation dozes – Standards of radiation protection
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Safety and disposal: Nuclear plant safety-safety systems-changes and consequences of
            accident-criteria for safety-nuclear waste- types of waste and its disposal-radiation
            hazards and their prevention-weapons proliferation
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="me373">


        <item>HRM</item>
        <item>Human Behaviour</item>

        <item>Biological characteristics, age, gender, tenure.Ability, intellectual and physical
            abilities. Learning, theories of learning.Values, importance of values, types.
            Attitudes, types, attitudes and
            consistency, workforce diversity. Personality and emotions, personality determinants and
            traits, emotion dimensions. Perception, factors influencing perception, making judgement
            about others, link betweenperception and individual decision making
        </item>

        <item>Human Behaviour and Relations in Groups</item>

        <item>Defining and classifying different groups. Stages of group development, Five stage
            model. Group structure, roles, norms, status and size. Group decision making, group
            versus the individual. Types of teams, self-managed work teams, problem solving teams.
            Creating effective teams, composition, work design, process and team players.
        </item>

        <item>Management of Human Relations in Organisations</item>

        <item>Ethics and fair treatment at work, ethics and the law, ethics fair treatment and
            justice. Ethical behaviour at work, individual factors, organizational factors, the
            boss’s influence, ethics policies and codes, the organization’s culture, role of HR in
            fostering ethics and fair treatment. Disciplining an employee, formal disciplinary
            appeals process, discipline without punishment, employee privacy.
        </item>

        <item>Management of Human Laws and Collective Bargaining</item>

        <item>Employment law, gross misconduct, personal supervisory liability, layoffs and the
            plant closing law. Collective bargaining, good faith, negotiating team, bargaining
            items, bargaining stages, bargaining hints, impasses, mediation, and strikes, the
            contract agreement. Grievances, sources of grievances, the grievance procedure,
            guidelines for handling grievances.
        </item>

        <item>Management of Training and Employer-Employee Relations</item>

        <item>Training and development, objectives, strategies, methods and techniques. Design and
            organisation of training and evaluation of training. Employee relations,
            management-employee relations, managing discipline, grievance and stress, counselling,
            are handling problem employees. Industrial relations implications of personnel policies,
            nature of employment relationship
        </item>

        <item>Management of Human Conflicts, Customer Relations, Unions and Global Relations
        </item>

        <item>Industrial and organisational conflict, managing for good industrial relations and
            managing the moment of conflict. Customer relationship management, what if customer is
            the problem. Place of unions in organizations. The future scenario, the changing
            personnel management scenario. Managing global human relations. HRD the development role
            of personnel to the force. Employee safety and health
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="me302">

        <item>HMT</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Modes of Heat Transfer: Conduction: Fourier law of heat conduction-Thermal
            conductivity of solids, liquids and gases-Factors affecting thermal conductivity- Most
            general heat conduction equation in Cartesian, cylindrical and spherical coordinates One
            dimensional steady state conduction with and without heat generation conduction through
            plane walls, cylinders and spheres-variable thermal conductivity conduction shape
            factor- heat transfer through corners and edges. Critical radius of insulation.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Elementary ideas of hydrodynamics and thermal boundary layers-Thickness of Boundary
            layer-Displacement, Momentum and Energy thickness (description only).\n
            Convection heat transfer: Newton’s law of cooling- Laminar and Turbulent flow, Reynolds
            Number, Critical Reynolds Number, Prandtl Number, Nusselt Number, Grashoff Number and
            Rayleigh’s Number.\n Dimensional analysis Buckingham’s Pi theorem- Application of
            dimensional analysis to free and forced convection- empirical relations- problems using
            empirical relations
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Transient heat conduction-lumped heat capacity method. Fins: Types of fins - Heat
            transfer from fins of uniform cross sectional area- Fin efficiency and effectiveness.
            Boiling and condensation heat transfer(elementary ideas only),Introduction to heat pipe.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Combined conduction and convection heat transfer-Overall heat transfer coefficient -
            Heat exchangers: Types of heat exchangers, AMTD, Fouling factor, Analysis of Heat
            exchangers- LMTD method, Correction factor, Effectiveness- NTU method, Special type of
            heat exchangers (condenser and evaporator, simple problems only)
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Radiation- Nature of thermal radiation-definitions and concepts- monochromatic and
            total emissive power-Intensity of radiation- solid angle- absorptivity, reflectivity and
            transmissivity-Concept of black body- Planck’ law- Kirchoff’s law- Wein’s displacement
            law-Stefan Boltzmann’s law- black, gray and real surfaces-Configuration factor
            (derivation for simple geometries only)- Electrical analogy- Heat exchange between
            black/gray surfaces- infinite parallel plates, equal and parallel opposite
            plates-perpendicular rectangles having common edge- parallel discs (simple problems
            using charts and tables). Radiation shields(no derivation).
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Mass Transfer :Mass transfer by molecular diffusion- Fick’s law of diffusion-
            diffusion coefficient Steady state diffusion of gases and liquids through solid-
            equimolar diffusion, Isothermal evaporation of water through air- simple problems.
            Convective mass transfer- Evaluation of mass transfer coefficient- empirical relations-
            simple problems- analogy between heat and mass transfer.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me304">

        <item>DOM</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to force analysis in mechanisms - static force analysis
            (four bar linkages only) - graphical methods\n\nMatrix methods - method of virtual work
            - analysis with sliding and
            pin friction
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Dynamic force analysis: Inertia force and inertia torque. D’Alemberts
            principle, analysis of mechanisms (four bar linkages only),
            equivalent dynamical systems\n\nForce Analysis of spur- helical - bevel and worm gearing
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Flywheel analysis - balancing - static and dynamic balancing -
            balancing of masses rotating in several planes\n\nBalancing of reciprocating masses -
            balancing of multi-cylinder in
            line engines - V engines - balancing of machines
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Gyroscope – gyroscopic couples\n\nGyroscopic action on vehicles-two wheelers, four
            wheelers, air planes
            and ships. Stability of an automobile – stability of a two wheel vehicle
            –Stabilization of sh
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to vibrations – free vibrations of single degree freedom
            systems – energy Method\n\nUndamped and damped free vibrations – viscous damping –
            critical
            damping - logarithmic decrement - Coulomb damping – harmonically
            excited vibrations\n\nResponse of an undamped and damped system – beat phenomenon -
            transmissibility
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Whirling of shafts – critical speed - free torsional vibrations – self
            excitation and stability analysis - vibration control - vibration isolation
            – vibration absorbers\n\nIntroduction to multi-degree freedom systems - vibration
            measurement - accelerometer – seismometer – vibration exciters
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me306">

        <item>AMT</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction: Need and comparison between traditional, nontraditional
            and micro &amp; nano machining process.\nPowder Metallurgy: Need of P/M - Powder
            Production methods:-
            Atomization, electrolysıs, Reduction of oxides, Carbonyls
            (Process parameters, characteristics of powder produced in each
            method).\nPowder characteristics: properties of fine powder, size, size
            distribution, shape, compressibility, purity etc.\n\nMixing – Compaction:- techniques,
            pressure distribution, HIP &amp; CIP.\n\nMechanism of sintering, driving force for pore
            shirking, solid and
            liquid phase sintering - Impregnation and Infiltration Advantages,
            disadvantages and specific applications of P/M.\n\nProgrammable Logic Controllers (PLC):
            need – relays - logic
            ladder program –timers, simple problems only.\n\nPoint to point, straight cut and
            contouring positioning -
            incremental and absolute systems – open loop and closed loop
            systems - control loops in contouring systems: principle of
            operation.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>DDA integrator:-Principle of operation, exponential deceleration
            –liner, circular and complete interpolator.\nNC part programming: part programming
            fundamentals - manual
            programming – NC coordinate systems and axes –– sequence number, preparatory
            functions, dimension words, speed word, feed world, tool world,
            miscellaneous functions – Computer aided part programming:– CNC languages – APT
            language structure: geometry commands, motion
        </item>
        commands, postprocessor commands, compilation control
        commands \n\nProgramming exercises: simple problems on turning and drilling
        etc - machining centers- 5 axis machining (At least one
        programming exercise must be included in the end semester
        University examination).
        <item></item>
        <item>Electric Discharge Machining (EDM):- Mechanism of metal removal, dielectric fluid,
            spark generation, recast layer and attributes of process characteristics on MRR,
            accuracy, HAZ etc, Wire EDM, applications and accessories. \n\nUltrasonic Machining
            (USM):-mechanics of cutting, effects of parameters on amplitude, frequency of vibration,
            grain diameter, slurry, tool material attributes and hardness of work material,
            applications. \n\nElectro chemical machining (ECM):- Mechanism of metal removal
            attributes of process characteristics on MRR, accuracy, surface roughness etc,
            application and limitations.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Laser Beam Machining (LBM), Electron Beam Machining (EBM), Plasma arc Machining (PAM),
            Ion beam Machining(IBM) - Mechanism of metal removal, attributes of process
            characteristics on MRR, accuracy etc and structure of HAZ compared with conventional
            process; application, comparative study of advantages and limitations of each process.
            \n\nAbrasive Jet Machining (AJM), Abrasive Water Jet Machining (AWJM) - Working
            principle, Mechanism of metal removal, Influence of process parameters, Applications,
            Advantages &amp; disadvantages.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>High velocity forming of metals:-effects of high speeds on the stress strain
            relationship steel, aluminum, Copper – comparison of conventional and high velocity
            forming methods- deformation velocity, material behavior, stain distribution.\n\nStress
            waves and deformation in solids – types of elastic body waves- relation at free
            boundaries- relative particle velocity.\n\nSheet metal forming: - explosive
            forming:-process variable, properties of explosively formed parts, etc.\n\nElectro
            hydraulic forming: - theory, process variables, etc, comparison with explosive forming.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Micromachining: Diamond turn mechanism, material removal mechanism,
            applications.\n\nAdvanced finishing processes: - Abrasive Flow Machining, Magnetic
            Abrasive Finishing.\n\nagnetorheological Abrasive Flow Finishing, Magnetic Float
            Polishing, Elastic Emission Machining.\n\nMaterial addition process:-
            stereo-lithography, selective laser sintering, 3D Printing, fused deposition modeling,
            laminated object manufacturing, , laser engineered net-shaping, laser welding, LIGA
            process.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me308">

        <item>CAD and Analysis</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to CAD , Historical developments, Industrial look at CAD,
            Comparison of CAD with traditional designing, Application of
            computers in Design Basics of geometric and solid modeling, Packages for
            CAD/CAM/CAE/CAPP
            Hardware in CAD components, user interaction devices, design
            database, graphic Standards, data Exchange Formats, virtual Reality.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Transformation of points and line, 2-D rotation, reflection, scaling and
            combined transformation, homogeneous coordinates, 3-D scaling.\n\n
            Shearing,rotation, reflection and translation, combined transformations,
            orthographic and perspective projections, reconstruction of 3-D objects.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Algebraic and geometric forms, tangents and normal, blending functions,
            reparametrization, straight lines, conics, cubic splines, Bezier curves and
            B-spline curves.\n\n
            Plane surface, ruled surface, surface of revolution, tabulated cylinder, bicubic
            surface, bezier surface, B-spline surfaces and their modeling
            techniques.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Solid models and representation scheme, boundary representation,
            constructive solid geometry.\n\nSweep representation, cell decomposition, spatial
            occupancy
            enumeration, coordinate systems for solid modeling
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to finite element analysis - steps involved in FEMPreprocessing
            phase – discretisation - types of elements
            Formulation of stiffness matrix (direct method, 1-D element) -
            formulation of load vector - assembly of global equations -
            implementation of boundary conditions - solution procedure - post
            processing phase\n\n
            Simple problems with axial bar element (structural problems only)
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Interpolation – selection of interpolation functions - CST element -
            isoparametric formulation (using minimum PE theorem) – Gaussquadrature
            Solution of 2D plane stress solid mechanics problems (linear static analysis)
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me312">

        <item>MI</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Concept of measurement:-Introduction to Metrology; Need for high precision
            measurements; Terminologies in Measurement- Precision, accuracy, sensitivity,
            calibration. Errors in Measurement, types of errors, Abbe’s Principle.Basic standards of
            length- Line standard, End standards, Wavelength standard; Various Shop floor standards.
            Linear Measurement – Slip gauges, wringing, grades; Surface plate; Dial indicators;
            Height gauges and Vernier calipers. Comparators- mechanical, electrical, optical and
            pneumatic. Angular Measurement – Bevel protractor; Sine Bar, principle and use of sine
            bar, sine centre; Angle gauges. Sprit level; Angle Dekkor; Clinometers.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Limits and Limit gauges – Making to suit, selective assembly, systems of limits and
            fits; Types of fits; Hole basis system and Shaft basis system.
            Standard systems of limits and fits; Shaft and Hole system; Tolerance, allowance and
            deviation (as per BIS).\n
            Simple problems on tolerance and allowance, shaft and hole system.\n
            Limit Gauges – GO and NO GO gauges; types of limit gauges.\n
            Gauge design - Taylor’s principle of gauging; Gauge tolerance, disposition of gauge
            tolerance, wear allowance.\n
            Optical Measuring Instruments: - Benefits of using light waves as standards;
            Monochromatic light; Principle of Interference.\n
            Interference band using optical flat, application in surface measurement.\n
            Interferometers – NPL flatness interferometer, Pitter-NPL gauge interferometer.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Screw thread measurement – Screw thread terminology; Measurement of major diameter;
            Measurement of minor or root diameter.
            Measurement of pitch; Measurement of effective diameter with two wire method and three
            wire method.
            Measurement of flank angle and form by profile projector andmicroscope.
            Measurement of surface texture – Meaning of surface texture, roughness and waviness;
            Analysis of surface traces, peak to valley height, R.M.S. value, Centre Line Average and
            Ra value, Rt, Rz etc.
            Methods of measuring surface roughness – Stylus probe, Tomlinson surface meter,
            Talysurf; Terms used in surface roughness measurement – assessment length, roughness
            width cut-off, sampling length and evaluation length.
            Interference method for measuring surface roughness – using optical flat and
            interferometers.
            Autocollimator, principle and use of autocollimator.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Machine tool metrology – Alignment testing of machine tools like lathe, milling
            machine, drilling machine.
            Advanced measuring devices – Laser interferometers.
            Coordinate Measuring Machine (CMM) – Introduction to CMM; Components and construction of
            CMM.
            Types of CMM; Advantages and application of CMM
            CMM probes, types of probes – contact probes and non contact probes
            Machine Vision – Introduction to machine vision, functions, applications and advantages
            of machine vision.
            Steps in machine vision
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Mechanical Measurement – significance of mechanical measurement;
            Fundamental methods of measurement; Classification of measuring instrument.
            Stages in generalized measuring system – Sensor-Transducer stage, Signal-Conditioning
            stage, Readout-Recording stage; Types of input quantities; Active and Passive
            transducers.
            Performance characteristic of measuring devices –
            Static characteristics – Accuracy, Precision, Repeatability, Sensitivity,
            Reproducibility, Drift, Resolution, Threshold, Hysteresis, Static calibration.
            Dynamic characteristics- different order systems and their response-, Measuring lag,
            Fidelity, Dynamic error; Types of errors in measurement.
            Transducers – Working, Classification of transducers.
            Motion and Dimension measurement – LVDT – Principle, applications, advantages and
            limitations
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Strain and Stress Measurement - Electrical resistance strain gauge - Principle,
            operation.
            Measurement of Force and Torque – Strain-Gauge Load Cells, Hydraulic and Pneumatic load
            cells – basic principle and three component force measurement using piezoelectric quartz
            crystal.
            Torque Measurement – Dynamometers – Mechanical, Hydraulic and Electrical.
            Vibration measurement – Vibrometers and Accelerometers – Basic principles and operation.
            Temperature Measurement – Use of Thermal Expansion – Liquid-in-glass thermometers,
            Bimetallic strip thermometer, Pressure thermometers.
            Thermocouples – Principle, application laws for Thermocouples, Thermocouple materials
            and construction, measurement of Thermocouple EMF.
            Resistance Temperature Detectors (RTD); Thermistors; Pyrometers (Basic Principles).
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me362">

        <item>CSE</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to control systems. Elementary ideas on types of control systems- Open
            loop and closed loop systems, Servo systems, Automatic regulating systems, Process
            control systems, Adaptive control systems, Learning control systems, Discrete control
            systems, Multivariable control systems, Linear and Non-linear systems. Elementary ideas
            on types of controls- proportional, integral, proportional integral, proportional
            integral derivative controls. Direct and indirect controls. Mathematical models of
            physical systems – typical examples of mechanical, thermal, electrical, hydraulic and
            pneumatic systems.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Block diagram, transfer function, reduction of block diagrams, signal flow graphs
            :Manson’s gain formula. Control system components – servomotors, stepper motor,
            synchros, hydraulic pumps and motors, hydraulic valves, pneumatic bellows, pneumatic
            valve, pneumatic relay, pneumatic actuator, gyroscopes ( elementary ideas only. No
            derivations)
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>System response- Time response of first and second order
            systems, steady state errors and error constants, specifications in
            time domain. Effect of pole locations, Concept of stability,
            Routh’s stability criterion
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Root locus method of analysis and design. Lead and lag
            compensation
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Frequency response analysis- relationship between time &amp; frequency response,
            Bode’s plot, stability in frequency domain,
            gain margin and Phase margin
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Polar plots, Nyquist stability criterion, Stability analysis,
            Relative stability concepts, Gain margin and phase margin.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me364">

        <item>Turbomachinery</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Definition of turbomachine, parts of turbomachines, Comparison with positive
            displacement machines, Classification, Dimensionless parameters and their significance,
            Effect of Reynolds number, Unit and specific quantities, model studies.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Application of first and second laws of thermodynamics to turbomachines, Efficiencies
            of turbomachines. Stage velocity triangles, work and efficiency for compressors and
            turbines
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Centrifugal fans and blowers : Types, stage and design
            parameters, flow analysis in impeller blades, volute and
            diffusers, losses, characteristics curves and selection, fan
            drives and fan noise.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Centrifugal Compressors: Construction details, types,
            impeller flow losses, slip factor, diffuser analysis, losses
            and performance curves.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Axial flow compressors : Stage velocity triangles, enthalpyentropy
            diagrams, stage losses and efficiency, work done
            factor, simple stage design problems and performance
            characteristics.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Axial and radial flow turbines : Stage velocity diagrams,
            reaction stages, losses and coefficients blade design
            principles, testing and performance characteristics.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me366">

        <item>AMJT</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Radiant energy welding: Electron Beam Welding- Background of the Process, Guns, Weld
            Environment, Welding in Different Degrees of Vacuum, Equipment and Safety, Joint Design,
            Applications, Laser Beam Welding, Physics of Lasers, Types of Lasers, Process
            Parameters, Applications and Limitations.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Diffusion Welding- theory and Principle of Process, Key Variables, Intermediate
            Materials, Deformation Welding, Equipment and Tooling, Joint Design, Economics,
            Advantages and Limitations, Materials and Applications, Cold Pressure Welding- Process,
            Equipment and Setup, Applications
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Explosive Welding- theory and Key Variables, Parameters, Weld Quality, Equipment and
            Tooling, Advantages and Limitations, Joint Design, Materials and Applications, Adhesive
            Bonding- theory and Key Parameters, Physical Characteristics, Metal Adhesive, Equipment,
            Design, Economics of Process, Materials and Applications.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Ultrasonic welding-Principles of operation, Process Characteristics and Applications,
            Vacuum brazing- Theory, Mechanisms and Key Variables, Equipment and Tooling, Stop-Off
            and Parting Agents, Advantages, Limitations, Economics Materials and Applications.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Plasma arc welding: Plasma Arc Welding- theory and Principles, Transferred arc and
            Non-Transferred arc Techniques, Equipment and Tooling, Joint Design Advantages,
            Disadvantages, Economics, Materials and Applications, Needle Arc Micro Plasma Welding -
            Characteristics of Process, Operating Characteristics, Fixturing and Joint Design,
            Shielding, Weld Penetration and Shape, Applications, Magnetically impelled arc butt
            (MIAB) welding, Under Water Welding- Wet and Dry Under Water Welding
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Friction Welding- Basic Principles, Process Variants, Different Stages of Friction
            Welding, Mechanism of Bonding, Influence of Process Parameters, Weld Quality and Process
            Control, Joining of Dissimilar Materials, Advantages, Limitations and Applications,
            Friction Stir Welding-Metal flow phenomena, tools, process variables and applications,
            Friction Stir Processing- Process, Application
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me368">

        <item>Marketing Management</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to marketing - concept of market and marketing – marketing environment -
            controllable factors - factors directed by top management - factors directed by
            marketing - uncontrollable factors - demography, economic conditions, competition.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Social and Marketing planning - marketing planning process - Boston consultancy group
            model - marketing mix - marketing mix variables. Developing, testing and launching of
            new products.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Market segmentation and market targeting - introduction to
            segmentation - targeting and product positioning. Marketing
            research - need and scope - marketing research process –
            research objectives, developing research plan, collecting
            information, analysis, and findings.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Consumer behaviour - factors influencing consumer behaviour -
            perceived risks Product life cycle - marketing strategies for
            different stages of product life cycle
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Marketing communication - marketing mix variables - steps in
            developing effective communication - identification of target
            audience - determination of communication objectives
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Designing the message - selecting the communication channels -
            promotion mix evaluation - advertising and sales promotion -
            factors in advertising - sales promotion tools. New trends in
            marketing- Brand management - significance of branding to
            consumers and firms
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="me372">

        <item>Operations Research</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Basics of operations research–OR models–applications.\n
            Linear programming – problem formulation\n
            Graphical method\n
            Simplex method\n
            Big-M method \n
            Two–phase method \n
            Duality in linear programming
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Transportation problem – formulation – balanced &amp; unbalanced
            transportation problems\n
            North west corner rule – least cost method
            Vogel’s method –stepping stone method\n
            MODI method\n
            Assignment problem – formulation – optimal solution,\n
            Hungarian algorithm\n
            Variants of assignment problems\n
            Traveling salesman problem.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Sequencing problem– terminology and notations – assumptions –
            problems with n jobs through two machines\n
            Problems with n jobs through three machines\n
            Problems with n jobs through m machines.\n
            Network analysis – basic terms – network construction – time
            analysis\n
            Critical path method (CPM)\n
            Programme evaluation and review technique (PERT)\n
            Cost considerations in network analysis – crashing
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to queuing theory–terminologies– classification of
            queuing models\n
            Single server problems\n
            Multi server problems\n
            Inventory control – variables – deterministic inventory models –
            purchasing model without shortages\n
            Manufacturing model without shortages\n
            Purchasing model with shortages\n
            Manufacturing model with shortages
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Decision theory – steps in decision theory approach – decision
            making conditions\n
            Decisions under conditions of risk\n
            Decisions under uncertainty conditions\n
            Decision tree analysis\n
            Game theory – games with saddle points\n
            Games without saddle points – 2 x 2 games\n
            Graphical method for m x 2 &amp; 2 x n games
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Simulation – types of simulation – phases of simulation –applications– advantages and
            disadvantages\n
            Design of simulation, models &amp; experiments, model validation\n
            Generation of random numbers\n
            Monte Carlo simulation\n
            Queuing simulation model\n
            Inventory simulation model\n
            Simulation languages
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me374">

        <item>TOV</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to mechanical vibrations- Simple harmonic motion- Natural frequency
            -Equation of motion-- Energy method-Rayleigh method\n\n
            Free vibration of single degree of freedom (DOF) systems with damping- Viscous damping-
            Logarithmic decrement.
            Coulomb damping-Energy dissipated by damping- Structural damping -Equivalent viscous
            damping.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Forced harmonic vibration- Magnification factor-Transmissibility-Vibration
            isolation-Base excitation-Rotating unbalance- whirling of shafts- Resonance
            \nVibration measuring instruments. Seismometer-Accelerometer
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Two degree of freedom systems-Normal mode vibration-Principal co-ordinates-Coordinate
            coupling.\n
            Beat phenomenon-Undamped vibration absorbers- Vibration dampers
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Multi degree of freedom systems- Matrix formulation- Influence
            coefficients-Flexibility matrix-Stiffness matrix\n
            Eigen Value problem:Eigen value and Eigen vectors-Frequency mode
            shape -Modal analysis.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Lagrange’s equation- Solution to problems using Lagrange’s equation.\n
            Vibration of continous systems-Vibrating strings- Longitudinal vibration of
            rods—Torsional vibration of rods
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Transient vibrations- Impulse excitation- Convolution integral.\nIntroduction to non
            linear vibrations and random vibrations
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me376">

        <item>Maintenance Engineering</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Maintenance – basic concepts, purpose, functions and
            objectives of maintenance.
            Principles, benefits and effects of maintenance
            Inter-relationship between productivity, quality, reliability and
            maintainability – maintenance productivity –
            quality in maintenance.
            Reliability – basic concepts – bathtub curve – failure rate –
            mean time before failure.
            System reliability – reliability of series and parallel systems.
            Maintainability – mean time to failure – mean time to repair.
            Availability – inherent, achieved and operational availability –
            reliability, availability and maintainability (RAM).
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Maintenance strategies / systems – types – basis for selection.
            Breakdown maintenance – corrective maintenance
            Preventive maintenance – process flow – frequency in
            preventive maintenance.
            Predictive maintenance – components – advantages and
            disadvantages.
            Condition based maintenance and condition monitoring –
            monitoring systems.
            Performance monitoring – visual, tactile and aural monitoring –
            leakage monitoring.
            Temperature monitoring – thermography – advantages.
            Thickness monitoring – acoustic monitoring –
            smell/odour monitoring.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Vibration monitoring – vibration fundamentals – vibration
            analysis.
            Vibration transducers – types.
            Machinery vibration trouble shooting – machinery vibration
            standard, severity chart and acceptable limits.
            Lubricant monitoring – components and techniques – filter
            debris analysis &amp; filtergrams.
            Ferrography – spectroscopic oil analysis program.
            Crack monitoring – techniques.
            Corrosion monitoring – techniques.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Reliability centered maintenance (RCM) – steps – flow diagram – basic guidelines.
            Defect and failure – definitions – basics of failures – failure generation – failure
            analysis.
            Fault tree analysis (FTA)
            Event tree analysis (ETA)
            Root cause analysis (RCA)
            Failure modes and effects analysis (FMEA)
            Failure mode effect criticality analysis (FMECA)
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Terotechnology – definitions – terotechnology system – terotechnology process –
            strategies.
            Total productive maintenance (TPM) – features –methodology – basic systems of TPM – TPM
            and terotechnology.
            Six sigma maintenance.
            Lean maintenance – 5-zero maintenance concept –
            5-S maintenance concept.
            Business centered maintenance (BCM) – six pillars – success factors.
            Maintenance effectiveness – overall equipment effectiveness – key performance indicators
            – maintenance performance measuring indices.
            Quality assured maintenance – need – maintenance work quality – use of c-chart for
            quality control in maintenance.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Maintenance planning and scheduling.
            Maintenance organization – objectives and characteristics – centralized and
            decentralized maintenance.
            Maintenance costs – classification of maintenance costs – maintenance cost analysis –
            cost effectiveness analysis.
            Maintenance budgeting – types of maintenance budget – preparation of maintenance budget.
            Human factor in maintenance – manpower planning for maintenance – objectives and stages
            of manpower planning – training for maintenance personnel.
            Computer-aided maintenance management system (CMMS) – functions, applications and
            advantages of CMMS.
            Maintenance integration – various steps in integration – scheme of integration of
            maintenance function with other functions.
        </item>
    </array>

</resources>