<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <array name="ec201">
        <item>Network Theory</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to circuit variables and circuit elements, Review of Kirchhoff’s Laws,
            Independent and dependent Sources, Source transformations\nNetwork topology, Network
            graphs, Trees, Incidence matrix, Tie-set matrix and Cut-set matrix\nSolution methods
            applied to dc and phasor circuits: Mesh and node analysis of network containing
            independent and dependent sources
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Network theorems applied to dc and phasor circuits: Thevenin’s theorem, Norton’s
            theorem, Superposition theorem, Reciprocity theorem, Millman’s theorem, Maximum power
            transfer theorem Laplace transform, properties Laplace Transforms and inverse Laplace
            transform of common functions, Important theorems: Time shifting theorem, Frequency
            shifting theorem, Time differentiation theorem, Time integration theorem, s domain
            differentiation theorem, s domain integration theorem, Initial value theorem, Final
            value theorem
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Partial Fraction expansions for inverse Laplace transforms, Solution of differential
            equations using Laplace transforms \nTransformation of basic signals and circuits into
            s-domain\nTransient analysis of RL, RC, and RLC networks with impulse, step, pulse,
            exponential and sinusoidal inputs \nAnalysis of networks with transformed impedance and
            dependent sources.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Network functions for the single port and two ports, properties of driving point and
            transfer functions, Poles and Zeros of network functions, Significance of Poles and
            Zeros \nTime domain response from pole zero plot, Impulse Response\nNetwork functions in
            the sinusoidal steady state, Magnitude and Phase response
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Parameters of two port network: impedance, admittance, transmission and hybrid
            parameters, Interrelationship among parameter sets\nSeries and parallel connections of
            two port networks\nReciprocal and Symmetrical two port network\nCharacteristic
            impedance, Image impedance and propagation constant (derivation not required)
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Resonance: Series resonance, bandwidth, Q factor and Selectivity, Parallel resonance
            \nCoupled circuits: single tuned and double tuned circuits, dot convention, coefficient
            of coupling, Analysis of coupled circuits
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec202">
        <item>Signals and Systems</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Elementary Signals, Classification and Representation of Continuous time and Discrete
            time signals, Signal operations. Continuous Time and Discrete Time Systems -
            Classification, Properties.Representation of systems: Differential Equation
            representation of Continuous Time Systems. Difference Equation Representation of
            Discrete Systems.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Continuous Time LTI systems and Convolution Integral.Discrete Time LTI systems and
            linear convolution. Stability and causality of LTI systems. Correlation between signals,
            orthoganality of signals.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Frequency Domain Representation of Continuous Time Signals- Continuous Time Fourier
            Series and its properties. Convergence,Continuous Time Fourier Transform: Properties.
            Laplace Transform, ROC, Inverse transform, properties, unilateral Laplace Transform.
            Relation between Fourier and Laplace Transforms.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Analysis of LTI systems using Laplace and Fourier Transforms. Concept of transfer
            function, Frequency response, Magnitude and phase response. Sampling of continuous time
            signals, Sampling theorem for lowpass signals, aliasing.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Z transform, ROC , Inverse transform, properties, unilateral Z transform. Frequency
            Domain Representation of Discrete Time Signals, Discrete Time Fourier Series and its
            properties.Discrete Time Fourier Transform (DTFT) and its properties .
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Relation between DTFT and Z-Transform, Analysis of Discrete Time LTI systems using Z
            transforms and DTFT, Transfer function, Magnitude and phase response
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec203">
        <item>SSD</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Elemental and compound semiconductors, Fermi-Dirac distribution, Equilibrium and
            steady state conditions, Equilibrium concentration of electrons and holes, Temperature
            dependence of carrier concentration\nCarrier transport in semiconductors, drift,
            conductivity and mobility, variation of mobility with temperature and doping, High Field
            Effects, Hall effect
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Excess carriers in semiconductors: Generation and recombination mechanisms of excess
            carriers, quasi Fermi levels, diffusion, Einstein relations, Continuity equations,
            Diffusion length, Gradient of quasi Fermi level
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>PN junctions : Contact potential, Electrical Field, Potential and Charge density at
            the junction, Energy band diagram, Minority carrier distribution, Ideal diode equation,
            Electron and hole component of current in forward biased p-n junction, piecewise linear
            model of a diode effect of temperature on V-I characteristics
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Diode capacitances, switching transients, Electrical Breakdown in PN junctions, Zener
            and avalanche break down (abrupt PN junctions only), Tunnel Diode basics only, Metal
            Semiconductor contacts, Ohmic and Rectifying Contacts, current voltage characteristics
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Bipolar junction transistor , current components, Minority carrier distributions,
            basic parameters, Evaluation of terminal currents (based on physical
            dimensions),Transistor action, Base width modulation
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Metal Insulator semiconductor devices: The ideal MOS capacitor, band diagrams at
            equilibrium, accumulation, depletion and inversion, surface potential, CV
            characteristics, effects of real surfaces, work function difference, interface charge,
            threshold voltage MOSFET: Output characteristics, transfer characteristics, sub
            threshold characteristics, MOSFET scaling (basic concepts)\nFinFET-structure and
            operation
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ec204">
        <item>AIC</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Differential amplifiers: Differential amplifier configurations using BJT, Large and
            small signal operations, Balanced and unbalanced output differential amplifiers, Input
            resistance, voltage gain, CMRR, non ideal characteristics of differential amplifier.
            Frequency response of differential amplifiers, Current sources, Active load, Concept of
            current mirror circuits, Wilson current mirror circuits, multistage differential
            amplifiers.Operational amplifiers: Introduction, Block diagram, Ideal op-amp parameters,
            Equivalent Circuit, Voltage Transfer curve, open loop op-amp configurations, Effect of
            finite open loop gain, bandwidth and slew rate on circuit performance
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Op-amp with negative feedback: Introduction, feedback configurations, voltage series
            feedback, voltage shunt feedback, properties of Practical op-amp. Op-amp applications:
            Inverting and non inverting amplifier, dc and ac amplifiers, peaking amplifier, summing,
            scaling and averaging amplifiers, instrumentation amplifier.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Op-amp applications: Voltage to current converter, current to voltage converter,
            integrator, differentiator, precision rectifiers, log and antilog amplifier, Phase shift
            and Wien bridge oscillators
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Square, triangular and saw tooth wave generators, Comparators, zero crossing detector,
            Schmitt trigger, characteristics and limitations.Active filters, First and Second order
            Butterworth filter and its frequency response for LPF, HPF, BPF, BSF, and Notch filter.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Specialized IC’s and its applications: Timer IC 555 (monostable and astable
            operation), Voltage controlled oscillator, Analog Multiplier. PLL, operating principles,
            Applications: frequency multiplication/division, Frequency synthesizer, AM and FM
            detection , FM modulator/Demodulator Monolithic Voltage Regulators: Three terminal
            voltage regulators 78XX and 79XX series, IC723 , low voltage and high voltage regulator,
            Current boosting, short circuit and fold back protection.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Data Converters: D/A converter , specifications , weighted resistor type, R-2R Ladder
            type, switches for D/A converters, high speed sample-and-hold circuits. A/D Converters:
            Specifications, Flash type, Counter ramp type, Successive Approximation type, Single
            Slope type, Dual Slope type
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec205">
        <item>EC</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>RC Circuits: Response of high pass and low pass RC circuits to sine, step, pulse and
            square wave inputs, Differentiator, Integrator\nBJT biasing circuits: Types, Q point, Bi
            as stability, Stability factors, RC coupled amplifier and effect of various components,
            Concept of DC and AC load lines, Fixing of operating point, Classification of amplifiers
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Small signal analysis of CE, CB and CC configurations using small signal hybrid π
            model (gain, input and output impedance). Small signal analysis of BJT amplifier
            circuits, Cascade amplifier
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>High frequency equivalent circuits of BJT, Short circuit current gain, cutoff
            frequency, Miller effect, Analysis of high frequency response of CE, CB and CC
            amplifiers\nWide band amplifier: Broad banding techniques, low frequency and high
            frequency compensation, Cascode amplifier.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Feedback amplifiers: Effect of positive and negative feedback on gain, frequency
            response and distortion, Feedback topologies and its effect on input and output
            impedance, Feedback amplifier circuits in each feedback topologies (no analysis
            required) \nOscillators and Tuned Amplifiers: Classification of oscillators, Barkhausen
            criterion, Analysis of RC phase shift and Wien bridge oscillators, Working of Hartley,
            Colpitts and Crystal oscillators; Tuned amplifiers, synchronous and stagger tuning
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Power amplifiers: Classification, Transformer coupled class A power amplifier, push
            pull class B and class AB power amplifiers, efficiency and distortion, Transformer-less
            class B and Class AB power amplifiers, Class C power amplifier (no analysis required)
            \nSwitching Circuits: Simple sweep circuit, Bootstrap sweep circuit, Astable, Bistable,
            and Monostable multivibrators, Schmitt Trigger
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Transistor based voltage regulator: Design and analysis of shunt and series voltage
            regulator, load and line regulation, Short circuit protection \nMOSFET amplifiers:
            Biasing of MOSFET amplifier, DC analysis of single stage MOSFET amplifier, small signal
            equivalent circuit. Small signal voltage and current gain, input and output impedances
            of CS configuration, MOSFETCascade amplifier
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec206">
        <item>Computer Organisation</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Functional units of a computer: Arithmetic Circuits – Adder- Carry propagate adder,
            Ripple carry adder, Basics of carry look ahead and prefix adder, Subtractor, Comparator,
            ALU. Shifters and rotators, Multiplication, Division. Number System- Fixed Point and
            Floating Point.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Architecture – Assembly Language, Instructions, Operands – Registers, Register set,
            Memory, Constants. Machine Language –R-Type, I-Type, J-Type Instructions, Interpreting
            Machine Language code.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Addressing Modes – register only, immediate, base, PCrelative, Pseudo – direct. Steps
            for Executing a Program – Compilation, Assembling, Linking, Loading. Pseudoinstuctions,
            Exceptions, Signed and Unsigned Instructions, Floating Point Instructions
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Microarchitecture- design process. Single cycle processor, Single cycle data path,
            single cycle control. multi cycle processor, multi cycle data path, multi cycle control.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Memory and I/O systems – I/O accessing techniques: programmed, interrupt driven and
            DMA, DMA bus arbitration. Memory Arrays – Bit Cells, Organization, Memory Ports Memory
            types- DRAM, SRAM, Register Files, ROM.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Memory - Hierarchy, Performance analysis. Cache Memory – direct mapped, multi way set
            associate cache, Fully associate cache. Virtual Memory – Address Translation, Page
            Table, Translation Look aside Buffer, Memory Protection, replacement polices
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec207">
        <item>LCD</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Number systems- decimal, binary, octal, hexa decimal, base conversion\n1’s and 2’s
            complement, signed number representation
            Binary arithmetic, binary subtraction using 2’s complement\nBinary codes (grey, BCD and
            Excess-3), Error detection and correcting codes : Parity(odd, even), Hamming code (7,4),
            Alphanumeric codes : ASCII
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Logic expressions, Boolean laws, Duality, De Morgan&amp;apos;s law, Logic functions
            and
            gates\nCanonical forms: SOP, POS, Realisation of logic expressions using K-map (2,3,4
            variables)\nDesign of combinational circuits – adder, subtractor, 4 bit
            adder/subtractor, BCD adder, MUX, DEMUX, Decoder,BCD to 7
            segment decoder, Encoder, Priority encoder, Comparator (2/3 bits)
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to HDL : Logic descriptions using HDL, basics of
            modeling (only for assignments)\nLogic families and its characteristics: Logic levels,
            propagation delay,
            fan in, fan out, noise immunity , power dissipation, TTL subfamilies\nNAND in TTL (totem
            pole, open collector and tri-state),
            CMOS:NAND, NOR, and NOT in CMOS, Comparison of logic
            families (TTL,ECL,CMOS) in terms of fan-in, fan-out, supply voltage,
            propagation delay, logic voltage and current levels, power dissipation
            and noise margin\nProgrammable Logic devices - ROM, PLA, PAL, implementation of
            simple circuits using PLA
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Sequential circuits - latch, flip flop ( SR, JK, T, D), master slave JK FF,
            conversion of FFs, excitation table and characteristic equations\nAsynchronous and
            synchronous counter design, mod N counters,
            random sequence generator
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Shift Registers - SIPO, SISO, PISO, PIPO, Shift registers with parallel
            LOAD/SHIFT
            Shift register counter - Ring Counter and Johnson Counter\nMealy and Moore models, state
            machine ,notations, state diagram, state
            table, transition table, excitation table, state equations
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Construction of state diagram – up down counter, sequence detector\nSynchronous
            sequential circuit design - State equivalence\nState reduction – equivalence classes,
            implication chart
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec208">
        <item>ACE</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction, elements of communication system, time and frequency domains, Need for
            modulation . Noise in communication system, shot noise, thermal noise, white noise,
            partition noise, flicker noise, burst noise, signal to noise ratio, noise figure, noise
            temperature, narrow band noise, representation in terms of in-phase and quadrature
            components, envelope and phase components, sine wave plus narrow band noise.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Amplitude modulation: Sinusoidal AM modulation index, Average power, Effective voltage
            and current, Nonsinusoidal modulation. Amplitude modulator circuits, Amplitude
            demodulator circuit, AM transmitters.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>AM Receiver, super heterodyne receiver, detector, tuning range, tracking, sensitivity
            and gain, Image rejection, double conversion, adjacent channel rejection, Automatic Gain
            Control (AGC). Single Sideband Modulation,Principles, Balanced Modulators, Singly and
            Doubly Balanced Modulators, SSB Generation, Filter Method, Phasing Method and Third
            Method, SSB Reception, Modified SSB Systems , Pilot Carrier SSB and ISB, Companded SSB.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Angle modulation: Frequency modulation, Sinusoidal FM, Frequency spectrum, modulation
            index ,average power, Non-sinusoidal modulation, deviation ratio, comparison of AM and
            FM. Phase modulation, Equivalence between PM and FM, Sinusoidal Phase Modulation,
            Digital Phase Modulation. Angle modulator Circuits : Varactor Diode Modulators,
            Transistors Modulators, FM Transmitters: Direct and Indirect Methods.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>FM receiver, slope detector, balanced slope detector, FosterSeeley discriminator,
            Ratio Detector, Quadrature detector, PLL demodulator, Automatic Frequency Control,
            Amplitude limiters, Pre-emphasis and De-emphasis,Effect of noise in analog communication
            Systems- AM Systems, DSBSC AM, SSB AM, Angle modulation, Threshold Effect in Angle
            modulation.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Telephone systems, standard telephone set, basic call procedures and tones, DTMF,
            cordless telephones.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec303">

        <item>AET</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Review of vector calculus, Spherical and Cylindrical coordinate system, Coordinate
            transformation\nCurl, Divergence, Gradient in spherical and cylindrical coordinate
            system.\nElectric field – Application of Coulomb’s law, Gauss law and Amperes current
            law (proof not required, simple problems only)\nPoisson and Laplace equations (proof not
            required, simple problems only), Determination of E and V using Laplace
            equation.\nDerivation of capacitance and inductance of two wire transmission line and
            coaxial cable. Energy stored in Electric and Magnetic field.\nDisplacement current
            density, continuity equation. Magnetic vector potential. Relation between scalar
            potential and vector potential.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Maxwell’s equation from fundamental laws\nBoundary condition of electric field and
            magnetic field from Maxwell&amp;apos;s equations\nSolution of wave equation\nPropagation
            of plane EM wave in perfect dielectric, lossy medium, good conductor, media-attenuation,
            phase velocity, group velocity, skin depth
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Reflection and refraction of plane electromagnetic waves at boundaries for normal
            &amp; oblique incidence (parallel and perpendicular polarization), Snell’s law of
            refraction, Brewster angle.\nPower density of EM wave, Poynting vector theorem, Complex
            Poynting vector.\nPolarization of electromagnetic wave-linear, circular and elliptical
            polarisation.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Uniform lossless transmission line - line parameters\nTransmission line equations,
            Voltage and Current distribution of a line terminated with load\nReflection coefficient
            and VSWR. Derivation of input impedance of transmission line.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Transmission line as circuit elements (L and C).\nHalf wave and quarter wave
            transmission lines\nDevelopment of Smith chart - calculation of line impedance and VSWR
            using smith chart\nSingle stub matching (Smith chart and analytical method).
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Parallel-Plate Waveguide - TE &amp; TM waves.\nThe hollow rectangular wave guide –
            modes of propagation of wave- dominant mode, group velocity and phase velocity
            derivation and simple problems only.\nAttenuation in wave guides, guide wavelength and
            impedance -derivation and simple problems only
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ec365">

        <item>BE</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to bio-medical instrumentation system, overview of anatomy and
            physiological systems of the body.\nSources of bio-electric potential: Resting and
            action potential, propagation of action potentials. Bioelectric potentials examples
            (ECG, EEG, EMG, ERG, EOG, EGG, etc introduction only.)\nElectrode theory: Nernst
            relation Bio potential electrodes: Microelectrodes, skin surface electrodes, needle
            electrodes.\nInstrumentation for clinical laboratory: Bio potential
            amplifiersinstrumentation amplifiers, carrier amplifiers, isolation amplifiers, chopper
            amplifiers
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Heart and cardiovascular system (brief discussion), electro conduction system of the
            heart. Electrocardiography, ECG machine block diagram, ECG lead configurations, ECG
            recording system, Einthoven triangle, analysis of ECG signals\nMeasurement of blood
            pressure: Direct, indirect and relative methods of blood pressure measurement,
            auscultatory method, oscillometric and ultrasonic non-invasive pressure
            measurements\nMeasurement of blood flow: Electromagnetic blood flow meters and
            ultrasonic blood flow meters
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>The human nervous system. Neuron, action potential of brain, brain waves, types of
            electrodes, placement of electrodes, evoked potential, EEG recording, analysis of
            EEG\nElectromyography: Nerve conduction velocity, instrumentation system for
            EMG\nPhysiology of respiratory system (brief discussion), Respiratory parameters,
            spirometer, body plethysmographs, gas exchange and distribution.\nInstruments for
            clinical laboratory: Oxymeters, pH meter, blood cell counter, flame photometer,
            spectrophotometer
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Therapeutic Equipments: Principle, block schematic diagram, working and applications
            of : pacemakers, cardiac defibrillators, heart–lung machine, dialyzers, surgical
            diathermy equipment, ventilators
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Medical Imaging systems (Basic Principle only): X-ray imaging - Properties and
            production of X-rays, X-ray machine, applications of X-rays in medicine.\nComputed
            Tomograpy: Principle, image reconstruction, scanning system and
            applications.\nUltrasonic imaging systems: Basic pulse echo system, propagation of
            ultrasonic through tissues and reflections, display types, A-Scan, B-Scan, M-Scan,
            applications, realtime ultrasonic imaging systems and probes
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Magnetic Resonance Imaging – Basic NMR components, Biological effects and advantages
            of NMR imaging\nBiomedical Telemetry system: Components of biotelemetry system,
            application of telemetry in medicine, single channel telemetry system for ECG and
            temperature\nPatient Safety: Electric shock hazards, leakage current, safety codes for
            electro medical equipments
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ec301">

        <item>DSP</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>The Discrete Fourier Transform: DFT as a linear transformation, Relationship of the
            DFT to other transforms, IDFT \nProperties of DFT and examples Circular
            convolution\nLinear Filtering methods based on the DFT- linear convolution using
            circular convolution, overlap save and overlap add methods\nFrequency Analysis of
            Signals using the DFT
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Computation of DFT: Radix-2 Decimation in Time and Decimation in Frequency FFT
            Algorithms\nIDFT computation using Radix-2 FFT Algorithms\nEfficient computation of DFT
            of Two Real Sequences and a 2N-Point Real Sequence
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Design of FIR Filters- Symmetric and Anti-symmetric FIR Filters \nDesign of linear
            phase FIR Filters using Window methods (rectangular, Hamming and Hanning) and frequency
            sampling Method \nComparison of Design Methods for Linear Phase FIR Filters
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Design of IIR Digital Filters from Analog Filters (Butterworth)\nIIR Filter Design by
            Impulse Invariance, and Bilinear Transformation\nFrequency Transformations in the Analog
            and Digital Domain
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Block diagram and signal flow graph representations of filters\nFIR Filter Structures:
            (Linear structures), Direct Form, Cascade Form and Lattice Structure\nIIR Filter
            Structures: Direct Form, Transposed Form, Cascade Form and Parallel Form \nComputational
            Complexity of Digital filter structures\nComputer architecture for signal processing :
            Introduction to TMS320C67xx digital signal processor
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Multi-rate Digital Signal Processing: Decimation and Interpolation (Time domain and
            Frequency Domain Interpretation without proof)\nFinite word length effects in DSP
            systems: Introduction (analysis not required), fixed-point and floating-point DSP
            arithmetic, ADC quantization noise\nFinite word length effects in IIR digital filters:
            coefficient quantization errors\nFinite word length effects in FFT algorithms: Round off
            errors
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec361">

        <item>DSD</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Analysis of clocked Synchronous Sequential Networks(CSSN)\nModelling of CSSN – State
            assignment and reduction\nDesign of CSSN\nIterative circuits\nASM Chart and its
            realization
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Analysis of Asynchronous Sequential Circuits (ASC)\nFlow table reduction- Races in
            ASC\nState assignment problem and the transition table-Design of AS\nDesign of Vending
            Machine controller
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Hazards – static and dynamic hazards – essential\nDesign of Hazard free circuits –
            Data synchronizers\nMixed operating mode asynchronous circuits\nPractical issues- clock
            skew and jitter\nSynchronous and asynchronous inputs – switch bouncing
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Fault table method – path sensitization method – Boolean difference method\nKohavi
            algorithm\nAutomatic test pattern generation – Built in Self Test(BIST)
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>PLA Minimization - PLA folding\nFoldable compatibility Matrix-Practical PLA\nFault
            model in PLA\nTest generation and Testable PLA Design
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>CPLDs and FPGAs - Xilinx XC 9500 CPLD family, functional block diagram– input output
            block architecture - switch matrix\nFPGAs – Xilinx XC 4000 FPGA family – configurable
            logic block - input output block, Programmable interconnect
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec305">

        <item>MAM</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Microprocessors: Introduction, organization of a microprocessor based system,
            evolution of microprocessors, 8085 architecture and its operation, microprocessor
            initiated operations and bus organization, pin configuration and functions, generation
            of control signals for external operations- fetch, IO/M, read/write
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Machine cycles and bus timings, Addressing modes, instruction set instruction
            classification.\nOverview/concept of peripheral IC interfacing with 8085 microprocessor
            (8251, 8253, 8255, 8279)\nSimple examples in assembly language programming for 8085
            (only for internal examination)\nIntroduction to development tools: IDE, cross
            assembler, builder, linker and debugger.( not required for exam)
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to 8086 and comparison between 8086,80286,80386,80486 and
            Pentium\nMicrocontrollers: Introduction, comparison between microprocessors and
            microcontrollers, microcontroller families, 8051- features, architecture, memory
            organization, registers, I/O ports, pin configuration and functions
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Addressing modes, instruction set, instruction classification\nAssembly language
            programming examples for 8051
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Interrupts in 8051: Types, interrupt source, interrupt handling and
            programming\nTimer/Counter programming: Operating modes, time delay generation, waveform
            generation\nSerial communication: RS 232 interface, registers in UART, modes of
            operation, programming examples for serial data transmission and reception
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Interfacing: Interfacing (block schematic and assembly language programming) of DIP
            switch, stepper motor, ADC, DAC, LEDs and seven segment displays, alphanumeric LCD
            module with 8051.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ec363">

        <item>OT</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction: Engineering applications of optimization, Formulation of design problems
            as mathematical programming problems, objective function, constraints, classification of
            optimization problems/techniques.\nOptimization techniques: Classical optimization,
            unconstrained single and multivariable minimization- necessary and sufficient conditions
            for optimality, uni-modality, convexity
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Linear programming problems-I: Mathematical formulation of LP Problems, slack, surplus
            and artificial variables. Reduction of a LPP to the standard form, feasible solutions.
            Graphical solution method, simplex algorithm and solution using tabular method,
            optimality conditions and degeneracy. Duality in linear programming
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Transportation Problem: Formulation of transportation problem, Basic feasible solution
            using different methods- East West corner method, Vogel approximation method, Optimality
            methods, MODI method, Unbalanced transportation problem
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Game Theory: Introduction, 2- person zero – sum game; Saddle point; Mini-Max and
            Maxi-Min Theorems (statement only); Graphical solution (2x n, m x 2 game), dominance
            property. Network path Models: Tree Networks – Minimal Spanning Tree - Prim’s Algorithm.
            Shortest path problems- solution methods – Dijkstra’s Method.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Nonlinear unconstrained optimization: Single variable optimization methods- Fibonacci
            search method, NewtonRaphson method.\nMulti-variable methods- Hook-Jeeves pattern search
            method, Cauchy’s (steepest descent) method.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Modern methods of optimization: Introduction to Genetic algorithm, Cross over,
            Mutation, Reproduction, Simple examples of applications in electronics
            engineering\nIntroduction to optimization tools and softwares. Solution of optimization
            Problems using MATLAB
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec307">

        <item>PEI</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Linear Electronics versus Power Electronics - Power semiconductor switches\nPower
            diodes-structure, static and dynamic characteristics\nPower transistors - Power BJT,
            Power MOSFET, GTO and IGBT\nSteady state and switching characteristics of Power BJT,
            Power MOSFET and IGBT.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Switched mode regulators\nBuck, Boost and Buck-Boost DC-DC
            converters\nWaveforms and expression of DC-DC converters for output voltage, voltage and
            current ripple under continuous conduction mode. (Derivation not required)\nIsolated
            converters - Flyback, Forward, Push Pull, Half Bridge and Full Bridge Converters -
            waveforms and governing equations. (Derivation not required)
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Overview of SMPS, Switched mode inverters- Principles of PWM switching
            schemes.\nSingle phase inverters - half bridge, full bridge and push pull.\nUPS - on
            line and off line.\nThree phase inverters - PWM and Space vector modulation in three
            phase inverters.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Generalized configurations of instruments - Functional elements. Classification of
            instruments\nGeneralized performance characteristics of instruments - Static
            characteristics and Dynamic characteristics.\nMeasurement of: resistance using
            Wheastone’s bridge, inductance using Maxwell-Wien bridge, and capacitance using
            Schering’s bridge.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Transducers - Classification, Selection of transducers.\nResistance transducers -
            Principle of operation, strain gauge.\nInductive Transducers: LVDT\nCapacitive
            transducers - different types, capacitor microphone, Hall Effect transducer, proximity
            transducers.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Electronic Multimeter, Audio Power Meter, RF power meter\nDigital Instruments -
            Basics, digital measurement of time, phase, frequency and digital voltmeter.\nFrequency
            synthesizer, Spectrum analyzers, Logic State analyzers (block diagram only).\nDigital
            storage oscilloscope – Working Principle, controls and applications.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ec360">

        <item>SC</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Soft computing: Introduction, soft computing vs hard computing, Fuzzy Computing,
            Neural Computing, Genetic Algorithms. applications of soft computing\nIntroduction to
            fuzzy sets and systems -crispness, vagueness, uncertainty and fuzziness. Basics of fuzzy
            sets, membership functions, support of a fuzzy set height, normalized fuzzy set, alpha
            cuts
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Type- 2 fuzzy sets. Operation on fuzzy set-complement, intersection, union, Demorgan&amp;apos;s
            Law Equality &amp; subset hood\nExtension Principle and its application, Fuzzy relation
            - operations, projection, max-min, min-max composition, cylindrical extension.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Reflexivity, symmetry and transitivity of fuzzy relations. Fuzzy prepositions, fuzzy
            connectives, linguistic variables, hedges.\nApproximate reasoning or fuzzy inference,
            Fuzzy rule based system. Fuzzification and defuzzification using centroid, centre of
            sums.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Neural Networks - Applications –Biological neuron- Typical
            architecture of Artificial Neural Networks - Common activation function\nMcCulloh Pitts
            Neuron – Architecture, logic implementatons. Supervised and Unsupervised learning
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Linear Separability, Pattern Classification: Perceptrons\nBack propagation network and
            its architecture, Back propagation learning, back propagation algorithm
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Genetic Algorithm Basic concepts, Initialization and selection, Survival of the
            Fittest - Fitness Computation\nOperators - Cross over, Mutation
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec306">

        <item>AWP</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Basic antenna parameters - gain, directivity, beam solid angle,
            beam width and effective aperture calculations. Effective height
            - wave polarization - antenna temperature - radiation resistance
            - radiation efficiency - antenna field zones - principles of
            reciprocity. Duality of antennas.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Concept of retarded potential. Field, directivity and radiation
            resistance of a short dipole and half wave dipole. Measurement
            of radiation pattern, gain, directivity and impedance of antenna
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Arrays of point sources - field of two isotropic point sources -
            principle of pattern multiplication - linear arrays of ‘n’ isotropic
            point sources. Grating lobes.
            \n Design of Broadside, Endfire &amp; Binomial arrays. Design of
            DolphChebyshev arrays
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Basic principle of beam steering. Travelling wave antennas.
            Principle and applications of V and rhombic antennas.
            Principles of Horn, Parabolic dish antenna, Cassegrain antenna
            (expression for E, H andGain without derivation).
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Principle of Log periodic antenna array and Helical antenna.
            Antennas for mobile base station and handsets.
            \n Design of rectangular Patch antennas. Principle of smart
            antenna.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Radio wave propagation , Modes , structure of atmosphere, sky
            wave propagation , effect of earth‘s magnetic field, Ionospheric
            abnormalities and absorption, space wave propagation, LOS
            distance
            \n Field strength of space wave, duct propagation, VHF and UHF
            Mobile radio propagation, tropospheric scatter propagation,
            fading and diversity techniques.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ec308">

        <item>ES</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Embedded Systems– Components of embedded
            system hardware–Software embedded into the system –
            Embedded Processors - CPU architecture of ARM processor
            (ARM9) – CPU Bus Organization and Protocol.
            \n Design and Development life cycle model - Embedded system
            design process – Challenges in Embedded system design
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Serial Communication Standards and Devices - UART, HDLC,
            SCI and SPI.
            \n Serial Bus Protocols - I2C Bus, CAN Bus and USB Bus.
            Parallel communication standards ISA, PCI and PCI-X Bus.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Memory devices and systems - memory map – DMA - I/O
            Devices – Interrupts - ISR – Device drivers for handling ISR –
            Memory Device Drivers – Device Drivers for on-board bus.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Programming concepts of Embedded programming – Features
            of Embedded C++ and Embedded Java (basics only). Software
            Implementation, Testing, Validation and debugging, system-onchip
            \n Design Examples: Mobile phones, ATM machine, Set top box
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Inter Process Communication and Synchronization -Process,
            tasks and threads –Shared data– Inter process communication -
            Signals – Semaphore – Message Queues – Mailboxes – Pipes –
            Sockets – Remote Procedure Calls (RPCs).
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Real time operating systems - Services- Goals – Structures -
            Kernel - Process Management – Memory Management –
            Device Management – File System Organization.
            Micro C/OS-II RTOS - System Level Functions – Task Service
            Functions – Memory Allocation Related Functions –
            Semaphore Related Functions.
            Study of other popular Real Time Operating Systems.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec312">

        <item>OOP</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Concepts of OOP – Introduction to OOP, Procedural Vs. Object
            Oriented Programming, Principles of OOP, Benefits and
            applications of OOP.
            \n Beginning with C++: Overview and Structure of C++ Program,
            Classes and Objects, Constructors and Destructors.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Operator Overloading and Inheritance – Overloading Unary
            Operators, Overloading Binary Operators, Overloading Binary
            Operators using Friends, Manipulation of Strings Using
            Operators.
            \n Inheritance – Multilevel Inheritance, Multiple Inheritance,
            Hierarchical Inheritance, Hybrid Inheritance. Virtual Base
            Classes, Abstract Classes, Constructors in Derived Classes,
            Member Classes: Nesting of Classes
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Virtual Functions and Polymorphism – Pointers to objects, this
            pointer, Pointers to derived classes, Virtual functions, Virtual
            Constructors and Destructors.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Programming with JAVA – Overview of Java Language,
            Classes Objects and Methods, Method Overloading and
            Inheritance, Overriding Methods, Final Variables and Methods.
            Interfaces, Packages, Multithreaded programming, Managing
            Errors and Exceptions
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Android : Setting up Development
            Environment, Basic Building blocks – Activities, Services,
            Broadcast Receivers &amp; Content providers, UI Components –
            Views &amp; notifications, Components for communication –
            Intents &amp; Intent Filters,
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Application Structure-Android Manifest.xml, uses-permission &amp; uses-sdk, Layouts
            &amp; Drawable Resources, First sample
            Application, Emulator-Android Virtual Device, Basic UI
            design, Styles &amp; Themes, Content Providers-SQLite
            Programming, Case study –Develop an App to demonstrate
            database usage.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec362">

        <item>MSCS</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Simulation and Modelling Methodology: Review of Random
            Processes, Univariate and multivariate models, Transformation
            of random variables
            \n Bounds and approximations, Random process models, Markov 15
            and ARMA Sequences, Poisson Process, Gaussian Process
            \n Random Number Generation, Generation of Random sequences
            \n Testing Random Number Generators
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Modelling of Transmitter and Receiver subsystems:
            Information sources
            \n Channel coding, Radio frequency and optical modulation
            \n Demodulation and detection, Filtering
            \n Multiple Access : Issues in the simulation of Multiple Access
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Communication channels and models: Fading and multipath
            channels, The Almost Free space channel
            \n Conducting and Guided wave media
            \n Finite state channel models, Methodology for simulating
            Communication systems operating over Fading Channels.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Estimation of parameters in simulation: Quality of an estimator,
            Estimating the average level of a waveform,
            \n Estimating the average power of a waveform, Estimating the
            power spectral density of a process
            \n Estimating Delay and Phase
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Estimation of performance measures from simulation:
            Estimation of SNR
            \n Estimating Performance measures for digital systems-The
            Monte Carlo Method
            \n Importance sampling method
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Analysis of simulation results: Model Verification Techniques,
            Model Validation Techniques
            \n Transient Removal, Terminating Simulations
            \n Stopping Criteria, Variance Reduction
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec366">

        <item>RTOS</item>


        <item></item>
        <item>Operating system objectives and functions, Virtual Computers,
            Interaction of O. S. &amp; hardware architecture, Evolution of
            systems
            \n Architecture of OS (Monolithic, Microkernel, Layered, Exo- 15
            kernel and Hybrid kernel structures)
            \n Batch, Multi programming, Multitasking, Multiuser, parallel,
            distributed &amp; real ľtime O.S.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Uniprocessor Scheduling: Types of scheduling
            \n Scheduling algorithms: FCFS, SJF, Priority, Round Robin
            \n UNIX Multi-level feedback queue scheduling, Thread
            Scheduling, Multiprocessor Scheduling concept
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Concurrency: Principles of Concurrency, Mutual Exclusion
            H/W Support, software approaches, Semaphores and Mutex,
            Message Passing techniques
            \n Classical Problems of Synchronization: Readers-Writers
            Problem, Producer Consumer Problem, Dining Philosopher
            problem.
            \n Deadlock: Principles of deadlock, Deadlock Prevention,
            Deadlock Avoidance, Deadlock Detection, An Integrated
            Deadlock Strategies
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Memory Management requirements, Memory partitioning:
            Fixed, dynamic, partitioning
            \n Memory allocation Strategies (First Fit, Best Fit, Worst Fit,
            Next Fit), Fragmentation, Swapping, Segmentation, Paging,
            Virtual Memory, Demand paging
            \n Page Replacement Policies (FIFO, LRU, Optimal, clock),
            Thrashing, Working Set Model
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>I/O Management and Disk Scheduling: I/O Devices,
            Organization of I/O functions
            \n Operating System Design issues, I/O Buffering, Disk
            Scheduling (FCFS, SCAN, C-SCAN, SSTF), Disk Caches
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Comparison and study of RTOS: Vxworks and ÁCOS
            \n Case studies: RTOS for Control Systems.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ec302">

        <item>DC</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Overview of Random variables and Random process: Random variables–continuous and
            Discrete, random process- Stationarity, Autocorrelation and power spectral density,
            Transmission of Random Process through LTI systems, PSD, AWGN\nPulse Code Modulation
            (PCM): Pulse Modulation, Sampling process, Performance comparison of various sampling
            techniques Aliasing, Reconstruction, PAM, Quantization, Noise in PCM
            system\nModifications of PCM: Delta modulation, DPCM, ADPCM, ADM, Performance comparison
            of various pulse modulation schemes, Line codes, PSD of various Line codes
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Transmission over baseband channel: Matched filter, Inter Symbol Interference (ISI),
            Nyquist Criteria for zero ISI, Ideal solution, Raised cosine spectrum, Eye
            Pattern\nCorrelative Level Coding - Duobinary coding, precoding, Modified duobinary
            coding, Generalized Partial response signalling.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Signal Space Analysis: Geometric representation of signals, Gram Schmidt
            orthogonization procedure.\nTransmission Over AWGN Channel : Conversion of the
            continuous AWGN channel into a vector channel, Likelihood function, Maximum Likelihood
            Decoding, Correlation Receiver
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Digital Modulation Schemes: Pass band transmission model, Coherent Modulation Schemes-
            BPSK, QPSK, BFSK. NonCoherent orthogonal modulation schemes, Differential Phase Shift
            Keying (DPSK)\nDetection of Binary modulation schemes in the presence of noise, BER for
            BPSK, QPSK, BFSK
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Pseudo–noise sequences: Properties of PN sequences. Generation of PN Sequences,
            generator polynomials, Maximal length codes and Gold Codes.\nImportance of
            synchronization: Carrier, frame and symbol/chip synchronization techniques\nSpread
            spectrum communication: Direct sequence spread spectrum with coherent binary phase shift
            keying, Processing gain, Probability of error, Anti-jam Characteristics, Frequency Hop
            spread spectrum with MFSK, Slow and Fast frequency hopping
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Multipath channels: classification, Coherence time, Coherence bandwidth, Statistical
            characterization of multi path channels, Binary signalling over a Rayleigh fading
            channel.\nDiversity techniques : Diversity in time, frequency and space. \nMultiple
            Access Techniques: TDMA, FDMA, CDMA and SDMA – RAKE receiver, Introduction to
            Multicarrier communication- OFDM
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec370">

        <item>DIP</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Digital Image Fundamentals: Image representation, basic relationship between pixels,
            elements of DIP system, elements of visual perception-simple image formation
            model\nVidicon and Digital Camera working principles\nBrightness, contrast, hue,
            saturation, mach band effect\nColour image fundamentals-RGB, CMY, HIS models\n2D
            sampling, quantization.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Review of matrix theory: row and column ordering- Toeplitz, Circulant and block
            matrix\n2D Image transforms : DFT, its properties, Walsh transform, Hadamard transform,
            Haar transform\nDCT, KL transform and Singular Value Decomposition
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Image Enhancement: Spatial domain methods: point processing- intensity
            transformations, histogram processing, image subtraction, image averaging\nSpatial
            filtering - smoothing filters, sharpening filters\nFrequency domain methods: low pass
            filtering, high pass filtering, homomorphic filter.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Image Restoration: Degradation model, Unconstraint restoration- Lagrange multiplier
            and constraint restoration\nInverse filtering - removal of blur caused by uniform linear
            motion, Weiner filtering\nGeometric transformations-spatial transformations
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Image segmentation: Classification of Image segmentation techniques, region approach,
            clustering techniques\nSegmentation based on thresholding, edge based
            segmentation\nClassification of edges, edge detection, Hough transform, active contour
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Image Compression: Need for compression, redundancy, classification of image
            compression schemes, Huffman coding, arithmetic coding, dictionary based compression,
            transform based compression\nImage compression standards- JPEG&amp;amp; MPEG, vector
            quantization, wavelet based image compression.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec368">

        <item>Robotics</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction – Definition and origin of robotics, Robot Anatomy, Robot specifications,
            Robot characteristics – accuracy, precision, and repeatability, Areas of application,
            classification of robots.\nRobotic arm – Components and structure, Types of joints and
            workspace, Common kinematic arrangements, Wrists, End effectors.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Sensors: Types and applications of sensors in Robotics, position and displacement
            sensors, Strain gauge based forcetorque sensors, Tachometers.\nRobotic drive systems and
            actuators: Hydraulic, Pneumatic and Electric drives. Specification, principle of
            operation and areas of application of: Stepper motor, Servo motor and brushless DC
            motor. Microprocessor control of electric motors, speed control using PWM and direction
            control using H- Bridge
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Robotic vision systems: Imaging, Sensing and Digitization, Image processing
            techniques, Areas of application in robotics.\nIntroduction to kinematics: Position and
            orientation of objects, Rotation, Euler angles, Rigid motion representation using
            Homogenous Transformation matrix.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Forward kinematics: Link coordinates, Denavit-Hartenberg Representation, Application
            of DH convention to different serial kinematic arrangements fitted with spherical
            wrist.\nInverse kinematics – General properties of solutions, Kinematic Decoupling,
            Inverse kinematic solutions for all basic types of three-link robotic arms fitted with a
            spherical wrist.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Velocity kinematics – Derivation of the Jacobian, Application of velocity kinematics
            for serial manipulators, importance of Singularities.\nManipulator Dynamics.
            Introduction to Legrangian mechanics and Dynamic equation for 2 DOF robots, Introduction
            to position control and force control of robotic manipulators, Robot actuation and
            control using PID controllers.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Robot Programming – Programming methods, Robot language classification, Robot language
            structure, elements and its functions. Motion, End-effecter and Sensor commands in VAL
            programming language. Simple programs.\nIndustrial applications of Robots in material
            handling and assembly. Mobile robots, Recent developments in Robotics
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ec304">

        <item>VLSI</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Material Preparation- Purification, Crystal growth (CZ and FZ process), wafer
            preparation \nThermal Oxidation- Growth mechanisms, Dry and Wet oxidation, Deal Grove
            model.\nDiffusion- Fick‘s Laws, Diffusion with constant surface concentration and from a
            constant source, diffusion techniques.\nIon implantation-Technique, Range Theory,
            annealing
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Epitaxy : Vapour phase epitaxy and molecular beam epitaxy\nLithography- Photo
            lithographic sequence, Electron Beam Lithography, Etching and metal deposition\nMethods
            of isolation Circuit component fabrication: transistor, diodes, resistors, capacitors,
            N-well CMOS IC Fabrication Sequence
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>CMOS inverters- DC characteristics, switching characteristics, power
            dissipation\nLayout Design rules, Stick Diagram and layout of CMOS Inverter, two input
            NAND and NOR gates
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>MOSFET Logic Design -Pass transistor logic, Complementary pass transistor logic and
            transmission gate logic , realization of functions
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Read Only Memory-4x4 MOS ROM Cell Arrays(OR,NOR,NAND)\nRandom Access Memory –SRAM-Six
            transistor CMOS SRAM cell, DRAM –Three transistor and One transistor Dynamic Memory
            Cell\nSense amplifiers –Differential Voltage Sensing Amplifiers Introduction to PLDs and
            FPGAs, Design of PLAs.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Adders- Static adder, Carry-By pass adder, Linear Carry- Select adder, Square- root
            carry- select adder\nMultipliers-Array multiplier
        </item>
    </array>
</resources>