<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <array name="ee201">
        <item>CN</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Network theorems – Superposition theorem – Thevenin’s theorem – Norton’s theorem –
            Reciprocity Theorem – Maximum power transfer theorem – dc and ac steady state analysis –
            dependent and independent sources
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Network topology – graph, tree, incidence matrix – properties of incidence matrix –
            fundamental cut sets – cut set matrix – tie sets – fundamental tie sets – tie set matrix
            – relationships among incidence matrix, cut set matrix and tie set matrix – Kirchoff’s
            laws in terms of network topological matrices – formulation and solution of network
            equations using topological methods
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Steady state and transient response – DC response and sinusoidal response of RL, RC
            and RLC series circuits
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Application of Laplace transform in transient analysis – RL, RC and RLC circuits
            (Series and Parallel circuits) – step and sinusoidal response

            Transformed circuits – coupled circuits - dot convention - transform
            impedance/admittance of RLC circuits with mutual coupling – mesh analysis and node
            analysis of transformed circuits – solution of transformed circuits including mutually
            coupled circuits in s-domain
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Two port networks – Z, Y , h, T parameters – relationship between parameter sets –
            condition for symmetry and reciprocity – interconnections of two port networks – driving
            point and transfer immittance – T-π transformation.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Network functions–Network synthesis-positive real functions and Hurwitz
            polynomial-synthesis of one port network with two kinds of elements-Foster form I and
            II-Cauer form I and II.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee202">
        <item>SIM</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Alternators - basic principle, constructional features of salient pole type and
            cylindrical type alternators, advantages of stationary armature, turbo-alternator.
            Armature winding – types of armature winding- single layer, double layer, full pitched
            and short pitched winding,slot angle, pitch factor and distribution factor – numerical
            problems. Effect of pitch factor on harmonics – advantages of short chorded winding, EMF
            Equation – numerical problems. Harmonics in generated EMF – suppression of harmonics.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Performance of an alternator – Causes for voltage drop in alternators – armature
            resistance, armature leakage reactance – armature reaction, synchronous reactance,
            synchronous impedance, experimental determination – phasor diagram of a loaded
            alternator. Voltage regulation – EMF, MMF, ZPF and ASA methods – numerical problems.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Theory of salient pole machine – Blondel’s two reaction theory – direct axis and
            quadrature axis synchronous reactances – phasor diagram and determination of Xd and Xq
            by slip test. Parallel operation of alternators – necessity of parallel operation of
            alternators, methods of synchronisation– dark lamp method and bright lamp method,
            synchroscope, Synchronising current, synchronising power, synchronising torque. Effects
            of changing excitation of alternators, load sharing of two alternators in parallel
            operation.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Synchronous motor – construction and principle of synchronous motor, methods of
            starting. Effects of excitation on armature current and power factor, v-curve and
            inverter v-curve, load angle, torque and power relationship, phasor diagram, losses and
            efficiency calculations. Three phase induction motor – constructional features, slip
            ring and cage types. Theory of induction motor with constant mutual flux, slip, phasor
            diagram, expression for mechanical power and torque, torque-slip characteristics,
            starting torque, full load and pull out torque, equivalent circuit.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Circle diagrams – tests on induction motors for determination of equivalent circuit
            and circle diagram. Cogging, crawling and noise production in cage motors – remedial
            measures. Double cage induction motor – principle, torque-slip curves. Starting of
            induction motors – types of starters – DOL starter, autotransformer starter, star-delta
            starter, rotor resistance starter – starting torque and starting currentnumerical
            problems. Braking of induction motors – plugging, dynamic braking and regenerative
            braking (no numerical problems). Speed control – stator voltage control, V/f control,
            rotor resistance control.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Induction generator – principle of operation, grid connected and self excited
            operation, comparison of induction generator with synchronous generators. Synchronous
            induction motor – principle of operation. Single-phase induction motor – double field
            revolving theory, equivalent circuit, torque slip curve. Types of single phase induction
            motor – split phase, capacitor start, capacitor start and run types. Principle of shaded
            pole motor – applications.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee203">
        <item>AEC</item>
        <item>Diode Circuits and Bipolar Junction Transistors</item>
        <item>Diode Circuits: Diode clipping circuits - Single level and two level clippers -
            Clamping circuits – Design of Zener Voltage Regulators.
            Bipolar Junction Transistors : Review of BJT characteristics- Operating point of a BJT –
            Factors affecting stability of Q point and DC Biasing – Biasing circuits: fixed bias,
            collector to base bias, voltage division bias and self bias. (Derivation of stability
            factors for Voltage Divider Biasing only) –Bias compensation using diode and thermistor.

            Low frequency equivalent circuit of BJT. Common Emitter amplifier - AC Equivalent
            Circuit – Role of coupling and emitter bypass capacitors – h parameter model of BJT
            -Amplifier gains and impedances calculations using h equivalent circuit.
        </item>
        <item>Field Effect Transistors and Frequency response of Amplifiers</item>
        <item>Field Effect Transistors : Review of JFET and MOSFET construction, working and
            characteristics- Biasing a JFET and MOSFET using voltage divider bias–- CS and CD
            amplifiers – small signal models-FET as switch and voltage controlled resistance.
            Frequency response of Amplifiers : Miller’s Theorem- BJT Internal Capacitances at high
            frequency operationsHigh frequency analysis of CE Amplifier using hybrid Pi Model -Low
            Frequency Response of Common Emitter amplifier -– CE High frequency response-Gain
            bandwidth product- –––Low and High Frequency response of FET amplifiers
        </item>
        <item>Multistage amplifiers,Power amplifiers using BJT and Feedback Amplifiers</item>
        <item>Multistage amplifiers : Direct, RC, transformer coupled amplifiers – Power amplifiers
            using BJT : Class A, Class B and Class AB and class C- Conversion efficiency and
            distortion in power amplifiers. Feedback Amplifiers- Effect of positive and negative
            feedbacks- Basic feedback topologies and their properties
        </item>
        <item>Oscillators and Operational Amplifiers</item>
        <item>Oscillators : Bark Hausen’s criterion – RC oscillators (RC Phase shift oscillator and
            Wein Bridge oscillator) –LC oscillators (Hartley and Colpitt’s)- Derivation of frequency
            of oscillation for the above mentioned oscillators- Crystal oscillator. Operational
            Amplifiers: Review of Operational Amplifier basics - Analysis of fundamental
            differential amplifier- Properties of ideal and practical Op-Amp - Gain, CMRR and Slew
            rate of IC 741 and LM 301– Drift and frequency compensation in OP Amps- Open loop and
            Closed loop Configurations-Concept of virtual short and its relation to negative
            feedback
        </item>
        <item>OP-AMP Circuits</item>
        <item>OP-AMP Circuits : Review of inverting and noninverting amplifier circuits- Summing and
            difference amplifiers, Differentiator and Integrator circuits- Logarithmic amplifier-
            Half Wave Precision rectifier - Instrumentation amplifier.

            Comparators: Zero crossing and voltage level detectors, Schmitt trigger.
        </item>
        <item>Wave form genereation using OP-Amps, Timer 555 IC and Oscillator Circuits using
            OP-amps
        </item>
        <item>Wave form generation using Op-Amps: Square, triangular and ramp generator circuits
            using Op-Amp - Effect of slew rate on waveform generation.
            Timer 555 IC : Internal diagram of 555 IC– Astable and Monostable multivibrators using
            555 IC.
            Oscillator circuits using Op-amps : RC Phase shift oscillator, Wein Bridge oscillator,
            LC Oscillators- (Derivation not required) - Crystal oscillator.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ee204">
        <item>DELD</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Number Systems and Codes : Binary, Octal and hexadecimal conversions- ASCII code,
            Excess -3 code, Gray code, Error detection and correction - Parity generators and
            checkers – Fixed point and floating point arithmetic. Binary addition and subtraction,
            unsigned and signed numbers, 1&amp;apos;s complement and 2’s complement arithmetic
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>TTL logic and CMOS logic - Logic gates, Universal gates - Boolean Laws and theorems,
            Sum of Products method, Product of Sum method – K map representation and
            simplification(upto four variables) - Pairs, Quads, Octets, Dont care conditions.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Combinational circuits: Adders _ Full adder and half adder – Subtractors,
            halfsubtractor and fullsubtractor – Carry Look ahead adders – ALU(block diagram only).
            Multiplexers, Demultiplexers, Encoders, BCD to decimel decoders.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Sequential circuits: Flip-Flops, SR, JK, D and T flip-flops, JK Master Slave
            Flip-flop, Conversion of flip-flops, Registers -SISO,SIPO, PISO, PIPO. Counters :
            Asynchronous Counters – Modulus of a counter – Mod N counters.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Synchronous counters: Preset and clear modes, Counter Synthesis: Ring counter, Johnson
            Counter, Mod N counter, Decade counter. State Machines: State transition diagram, Moore
            and Mealy Machines – Design equation and circuit diagram.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Digital to Analog conversion – R-2R ladder, weighted resistors. Analog to Digital
            Conversion - Flash ADC, Successive approximation, Integrating ADC. Memory Basics, Read
            and Write, Addressing, ROMs, PROMs and EPROMs, RAMs, Sequential Programmable Logic
            Devices - PAL, PLA, FPGA (Introduction and basic concepts only) Introduction to VHDL,
            Implementation of AND, OR, half adder and full adder.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee205">
    <item>DC MAT</item>

    <item></item>
    <item>Electromagnetic principles for Machines
        Electro dynamical equations and their solution – rotational
        motion system – mutually coupled coils – construction of DC
        machines – energy conversion in rotating electrical machines –
        eddy currents and eddy current losses – flux distribution curve
        in the airgap – armature windings – lap and wave windings –
        selection criteria – equalizer rings – dummy coils.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>DC generators – EMF equation – methods of excitation –
        separately and self excited – shunt, series, compound –
        armature reaction – effects of armature reaction –
        demagnetizing &amp; cross magnetizing ampere-turns –
        compensating windings – interpoles – commutation – methods
        to improve commutation – voltage build-up – no loadcharacteristics – load characteristics – losses and efficiency –
        power flow diagram – parallel operation – applications of dc
        generators</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>DC motor – principle of operation – back emf – classification
        – torque equation – losses and efficiency – power flow
        diagram – performance characteristics of shunt, series and
        compound motors – starting of dc motors – necessity and
        types of starters – speed control – methods of speed control –
        testing – Swinburne’s test – Hopkinson’s test – separation of
        losses – retardation test – applications of dc motors.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Transformer losses and efficiency – voltage regulation – OC &amp; SC test – Sumpner’s test
        – all day efficiency
        Autotransformer – saving of copper – current rating and kVA
        rating of autotransformers, parallel operation of single phase
        transformers, necessary and desirable conditions of parallel
        operation, on load and off load tap changers.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>Transformer losses and efficiency – voltage regulation – OC &amp; SC test – Sumpner’s test
        – all day efficiency
        Autotransformer – saving of copper – current rating and kVA
        rating of autotransformers, parallel operation of single phase
        transformers, necessary and desirable conditions of parallel
        operation, on load and off load tap changers.</item>
    <item></item>
    <item>3-phase transformer – 3-phase transformer connections – Δ-Δ,
        Y-Υ , Δ-Y , Y-Δ, V-V – vector groupings Yy0, Dd0, Yd1,
        Yd11, Dy1, Dy11 – Scott connection – three winding
        transformer – tertiary winding – percentage and per unit
        impedance – parallel operation of three phase transformers.</item>
</array>
    <array name="ee206">
        <item>Material Science</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Conducting Materials: Conductivity- dependence on temperature and composition –
            Materials for electrical applications such as resistance, machines, solders etc.
            Semiconductor Materials: Concept, materials and properties– Basic ideas of Compound
            semiconductors, amorphous and organic semiconductors- applications. Dielectrics:
            Introduction to Dielectric polarization and classification –Clausius Mosotti relation-
            Behavior of dielectric in static and alternating fields
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Insulating materials and classification- properties- Common insulating materials used
            in electrical apparatus-Inorganic, organic, liquid and gaseous insulators- capacitor
            materials- Electro-negative gases- properties and application of SF6 gas and its
            mixtures with nitrogen Ferro electricity.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Dielectric Breakdown: Mechanism of breakdown in gases, liquids and solids –basic
            theories including Townsend&amp;apos;s criterion, Streamer mechanism, suspended particle
            theory,
            intrinsic breakdown, electro-mechanical breakdown- Factors influencing Ageing of
            insulatorsApplication of vacuum insulation- Breakdown in high vacuum-Basics of treatment
            and testing of transformer oil
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Magnetic Materials: Origin of permanent magnetic dipoles- Classification of magnetic
            materials -Curie-Weiss law- Properties and application of iron, alloys of iron- Hard and
            soft magnetic materials– Ferrites- Magnetic materials used in electrical machines,
            instruments and relays-
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Superconductor Materials:-Basic Concept- typescharacteristics-applications Solar
            Energy Materials: Photo thermal conversion- Solar selective coatings for enhanced solar
            thermal energy collection –Photovoltaic conversion – Solar cells -Silicon, Cadmium
            sulphide and Gallium arsenic – Organic solar cells.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Modern Techniques for materials studies: Optical microscopy – Electron microscopy –
            Photo electron spectroscopy – Atomic absorption spectroscopy – Introduction to
            Biomaterials and Nanomaterials.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee207">
        <item>CP</item>
        <item>Intro to Programming and Basic Elements of C</item>
        <item>Introduction to Programming: Machine language, assembly language, and high level
            language. Compilers and assemblers. Flow chart and algorithm – Development of algorithms
            for simple problems. Basic elements of C: Structure of C program –Keywords, Identifiers,
            data types, Operators and expressions – Input and Output functions
        </item>
        <item>Control Statements</item>
        <item>if, if-else, while, do-while and for statements, switch, break, continue, go to, and
            labels. Programming examples.
        </item>
        <item>Arrays and Strings</item>
        <item>Declaration, initialisation, processing arrays and strings– two dimensional and
            multidimensional arrays –application of arrays. Example programs
        </item>
        <item>Functions and Storage Classes</item>
        <item>Functions : Functions – declaring, defining, and accessing functions –parameter
            passing methods – – passing arrays to functions , Recursion . Storage classes – extern,
            auto, register and static. Example programs.
        </item>
        <item>Structures and Pointers</item>
        <item>Structures – declaration, definition and initialization of structures, unions
            Pointers: Concepts, declaration, initialization of pointer variables, Accessing a
            Variable through its Pointer Chain of Pointers, Pointer Expressions, Pointer Increments
            and Scale Factor, Pointers and Arrays, examples
        </item>
        <item>File management and Intro to Python</item>
        <item>File Management – File operations, Input/Output Operations on Files, Random Access to
            Files ,File pointer. Introduction to Python :Basic Syntax, Operators, control
            statements, functions-examples.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee208">
        <item>MI</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>General principles of measurements – measurement system- measurement standards –
            characteristics - errors in measurement- calibration of meters- significance of IS
            standards of Instruments. Classification of meters - operating forces - essentials of
            indicating instruments - deflecting, damping, controlling torques. Ammeters and
            voltmeters - moving coil, moving iron, constructional details and operating, principles
            shunts and multipliers – extension of range.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Measurement of resistance: measurement of insulation resistance - loss of charge
            method, measurement of earth resistance. Measurement of power and energy: Dynamometer
            type wattmeter – 1-phase and 3-phase power measurement – 1-phase and 3-phase energy
            meters (induction type) – electronic energy meter, TOD meter.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to high voltage and high current measurements: Measurement of high DC
            voltages - measurement of high AC voltages - electrostatic voltmeters – sphere gaps - DC
            Hall effect sensors - high current measurements. Study of Phasor Measurement Units
            (PMU). Current transformers and potential transformers – principle working, ratio and
            phase angle errors – numerical problems, Clamp on meters.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Magnetic Measurements: Measurement of flux and permeability - flux meter - hall effect
            Gaussmeter - BH curve and permeability measurement - hysteresis measurement- ballistic
            galvanometer – principle- determination of BH curve - hysteresis loop. Lloyd Fisher
            square — measurement of iron losses Measurement of rotational speed using proximity
            sensors and optical sensors.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>DC and AC potentiometers - General Principle - calibration of ammeter, voltmeter and
            wattmeter using potentiometer. AC Bridges: Maxwell’s bridge- Schering bridge and Wien’s
            bridge Oscilloscopes – Basic principle of signal display - Block diagram and principle
            of operation of general purpose CRO - vertical deflecting system - horizontal deflection
            system - basic sweep generator - XY mode and Lissajous patterns - applications of CRO -
            dual trace oscilloscope. digital storage oscilloscope
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Transducers - Definition and classification - common transducers for measurement of
            displacement, velocity, flow, liquid level, force, pressure, strain and temperature -
            basic principles and working of LVDT, electromagnetic and ultrasonic flow meters,
            piezoelectricforce transducer, load cell, strain gauge- bridge configuration for four
            strain gauges, RTD, Thermistors, thermocouple, Need for instrumentation system, data
            acquisition system.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee216">
        <item>EE</item>
        <item>Transformers</item>
        <item>Transformers- Principle of operation - emf equation - Phasor diagram - Equivalent
            circuit - OC and SC tests – Basic principles of auto transformer and three phase
            transformer
        </item>
        <item>DC Generator</item>
        <item>DC Generator – E.M.F equation- Armature reaction – Commutation - interlopes – power
            flow diagram – losses and efficiency – voltage regulation – parallel operation – load
            sharing
        </item>
        <item>DC Motor</item>
        <item>DC Motor- back E.M.F. – speed equation – torques – performance characteristics – power
            flow diagram losses and efficiency – starter- two point and three point – swinburns test
            – thyristor control of series and shunt motor.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Alternator- Rotating field - Frequency effect of distribution of winding - emf
            equation – Basic principles of synchronous motor – Losses and Efficiency - Torque
            equation - Starting methods - induction motor - Constructional features - Principle of
            operation of 3 phase induction motor – Vector diagram and equivalent circuits - Starting
            and speed control of squirrel cage and wound rotor induction motor
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Three phase Induction motor- types – torque equations- torque slip and torque speed
            characteristics- power flow diagram – efficiency – equivalent circuit- induction
            generator Special machines – single phase FHP motor starting methods- double field
            revolving theory-types and applications – stepper motor –classifications and
            applications – servomotors – classifications and applications –shaded pole motors
            –applications
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Principle of Indicating instruments- moving coil, moving iron and dynamometer type
            instruments- Extension of range of voltmeter and ammeter - Measurement of 3 phase power
            by two wattmeter method – Principle and working of Induction type energy meter- DC slide
            wire, potentiometer
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee301">

        <item>PTP</item>

        <item>Introduction</item>
        <item>Typical layout of Power system Network Generation of Electric Power:\n Overview of
            conventional (Hydro, Thermal and Nuclear) and Nonconventional Sources (Solar and Wind)
            (Block Diagram and Brief Description Only)\nEconomics of Generation: Load factor,
            diversity factor, Load curve (Brief description only) Numerical Problems. Methods of
            power factor improvement using capacitors
        </item>

        <item>Power Transmission</item>
        <item>Transmission Line Parameters: Resistance, inductance and capacitance of 1-Φ, 2 wire
            lines-composite conductors(Derivation Required).\nInductance and capacitance of 3-Φ
            lines. Symmetrical and unsymmetrical spacing-transposition-double circuit linesbundled
            conductors (Derivation Required) .Numerical Problems\nModelling of Transmission Lines:
            Classification of lines-short lines-voltage regulation and efficiency-medium
            lines-nominal T and Π configurations-ABCD constants- long lines- rigorous solution-
            interpretation of long line equation-Ferranti effect. Tuned power lines-power flow
            through lines-Basics only
        </item>

        <item>Introduction of Overhead transmission and underground transmission</item>
        <item>Conductors -types of conductors -copper, Aluminium and ACSR conductors -Volume of
            conductor required for various systems of transmission-Choice of transmission voltage,
            conductor size -Kelvin's law. \nMechanical Characteristics of transmission lines –
            configuration-Types of Towers. Calculation of sag and tension- supports at equal and
            unequal heights -effect of wind and ice- sag template \nInsulators -Different types
            -Voltage distribution, grading and string efficiency of suspension insulators. Corona
            -disruptive critical voltage -visual critical voltage -power loss due to corona -Factors
            affecting corona - interference on communication lines. \nUnderground Cables -types of
            cables -insulation resistance voltage stress -grading of cables -capacitance of single
            core and 3 -core cables -current rating
        </item>

        <item>Systems</item>
        <item>HVDC Transmission: Comparison between AC&amp;DC Transmission ,Power flow equations and
            control, Types of DC links\nFlexible AC Transmission systems: Need and Benefits, SCV,
            Configuration of FC + TCR, Series compensation, Configuration of TCSC \nPower
            distribution systems –Radial and Ring Main Systems DC and AC distribution: Types of
            distributors- bus bar arrangement -Concentrated and Uniform loading -Methods of solving
            distribution problems.
        </item>

        <item>Need for power system protection</item>
        <item>Circuit breakers – principle of operation- formation of arcArc quenching theory-
            Restriking Voltage-Recovery voltage, RRRV (Derivation Required). Interruption of
            Capacitive currents and current chopping (Brief Description Only). \nTypes of Circuit
            Breakers: Air blast CB – Oil CB – SF6 CB – Vacuum CB – CB ratings.\nProtective Relays-
            Zones of Protection, Essential QualitiesClassification of Relays -Electro mechanical,
            Static Relays, Microprocessor Based Relay.\nElectromechanical Relays-Attracted Armature,
            Balanced Beam, Induction disc, Thermal Relays (Brief Description only) \nStatic
            Relays-Merits and Demerits, Basic components, Comparison and duality of Amplitude and
            Phase comparators. Static overcurrent, Differential, Distance Relays, Directional
            Relay-(principle and Block diagram only) \nMicroprocessor Based Relay-Block diagram and
            flow chart of Over current Relay, Numerical Relay(Basics Only)
        </item>

        <item>Protection &amp; Causes</item>
        <item>Protection of alternator: Stator inter turn, Earth fault Protection and Differential
            protection\nProtection of transformers- Percentage Differential Protection-Buchholz
            Relay\nProtection of transmission lines-Differential Protectioncarrier current
            protection\nCauses of over voltages – surges and traveling waves – voltage waves on loss
            less transmission lines, Bewley Lattice diagram. Protection against over voltages -
            Surge diverters - Insulation co-ordination
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee302">

        <item>ELECTROMAGNETICS</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>STATIC ELECTRIC FIELDS: Introduction to Co-ordinate System –
            Rectangular – Cylindrical and Spherical Co- ordinate System – Gradient of a Scalar
            field, Divergence of a Vector field and Curl of a Vector
            field- Their Physical interpretation. Divergence Theorem, Stokes’
            Theorem . Numerical problems
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Coulomb’s Law, Electric field intensity. Field due to a line charge,
            Sheet Charge and Continuous Volume Charge distribution. Electric
            Flux and Flux Density; Gauss’s law and its application. Electric
            Potential-The Potential Gradient. The Electric dipole. The
            Equipotential surfaces. Capacitance - capacitance of co-axial cable ,
            two wire line. Poisson’s and Laplace’s equations
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>STATIC MAGNETIC FIELD: Biot-Savart Law, Amperes Force Law.– Magnetic Field intensity
            due to a finite and infinite wire carrying a
            current–Magnetic field intensity on the axis of a circular and
            rectangular loop carrying a current –Magnetic vector potential,
            Magnetic flux Density and Ampere’s circuital law and simple
            applications.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>ELECTRIC AND MAGNETIC FIELDS IN MATERIALS-–E lectric
            Polarization-Nature of dielectric materials-Electrostatic energy and
            energy density–Boundary conditions for electric fields and magnetic
            fields–Conduction current and displacement current densities–
            continuity equation for current.
            \nMaxwell’s Equation in Differential and integral form from Modified
            form of Ampere’s circuital law, Faraday\'s Law and Gauss Law
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>TIME VARYING ELECTRIC AND MAGNETIC FIELDS: . Poynting
            Vector and Poynting Theorem – Power flow in a co-axial cable –
            Complex Average Poynting Vector.
            \n\nELECTROMAGNETIC WAVES: W ave Equation from Maxwell\'s
            Equation – Uniform Plane Waves –Wave equation in Phasor form
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Plane waves propagation in loss less and lossy dielectric medium and
            conducting medium. Plane wave in good conductor, surface
            resistance, Skin depth, Intrinsic Impedance and Propagation Constant
            in all medium. Phase and group velocity.
            \n\nTransmission lines: waves in transmission line –solution for loss less
            lines –characteristic impedance – VSWR – impedance matching.
            Introduction to Electromagnetic interference and compatibility.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee303">

        <item>LCS</item>


        <item></item>
        <item>Open loop-and closed loop control systems: Transfer function of LTI
            systems-Mechanical and Electromechanical systems – Force voltage and
            force current analogy - block diagram representation - block diagram
            reduction - signal flow graph - Mason\'s gain formula - characteristic
            equation.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Control system components: DC and AC servo motors – synchro -
            gyroscope - stepper motor - Tacho generator.
            \n\nTime domain analysis of control systems: Transient and steady state
            responses - time domain specifications - first and second order systems -
            step responses of first and second order systems.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Error analysis - steady state error analysis - static error coefficient of type
            0,1, 2 systems - Dynamic error coefficients.
            \n\nConcept of stability: Time response for various pole locations - stability of
            feedback system - Routh\'s stability criterion
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Root locus - General rules for constructing Root loci – stability from root
            loci - effect of addition of poles and zeros.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Frequency domain analysis: Frequency domain specifications- Analysis
            based on Bode plot - Log magnitude vs. phase plot,
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Polar plot- Nyquist stability criterion-Nichols chart - Non-minimum phase
            system - transportation lag
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee304">

        <item>ACT</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Types of controller- Feedforward-feedback-cascade-P, PI and
            PID. Compensator design: Realization of compensators – lag,
            lead and lag-lead -Design of compensator using bode plot.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Compensator design: Realization of compensators – lag, lead
            and lag-lead. Design of compensator using rootlocus. Design of
            P, PI and PID controller using Ziegler-Nichols tuning method.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>State space analysis of systems: Introduction to state concept -
            state equation of linear continuous time systems, matrix
            representation of state equations. Phase variable and canonical
            forms of state representation-controllable, observable, diagonal and Jordan canonical
            forms- solution of time invariant
            autonomous systems, forced system-state transition matrix-
            relationship between state equations and transfer function.
            Properties of state transition matrix-Computation of state
            transition matrix using Laplace transform-Cayley-Hamilton
            method. Conversion from canonical form to phase variable form.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>State feedback controller design: Controllability &amp; observability.
            State feed-back design via pole placement technique.
            Sampled data control system: Pulse Transfer function-Stability of
            sampled data system -Routh Hurwitz criterion and Jury\'s test.
            Introduction to state-space representation of sampled data
            systems.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Nonlinear systems: Introduction - characteristics of nonlinear
            systems. Types of nonlinearities. Analysis through harmonic
            linearisation - Determination of describing function of
            nonlinearities (relay, dead zone and saturation only) - application
            of describing function for stability analysis of autonomous
            system with single nonlinearity.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Phase Plane Analysis: Concepts- Construction of phase
            trajectories for nonlinear systems and linear systems with static
            nonlinearities - Singular points – Classification of singular
            points. Definition of stability- asymptotic stability and instability
            Liapunov methods to stability of linear and nonlinear, continuous
            time systems.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee305">

        <item>PE</item>


        <item></item>
        <item>SCR-Structure, static characteristics &amp; switching (turn-on &amp; turn-
            off) characteristics - di/dt &amp; dv/dt protection – turn-on methods of SCR - two
            transistor analogy - series and parallel connection of SCRs
            Structure and principle of operation of power diode, TRIAC, GTO,
            Power MOSFET &amp; IGBT – Comparison
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Gate triggering circuits – R, RC, UJT triggering circuits –
            natural and forced commutation (concept only). Requirements of
            isolation and synchronisation in gate drive circuits- Opto and pulse transformer based
            isolation. \n\nControlled rectifiers – half-wave controlled rectifier with R load
            – 1-phase fully controlled bridge rectifier with R, RL and RLE
            loads (continuous &amp; discontinuous conduction) – output voltage equation – 1-phase
            half controlled bridge rectifier with R, RL and
            RLE loads – displacement power factor – distortion factor.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>3-phase half-wave controlled rectifier with R load – 3-phase fully
            controlled &amp; half-controlled converter with RLE load (continuous
            conduction, ripple free) – output voltage equation-waveforms for
            various triggering angles (no analysis) – 1-phase &amp; 3-phase dual
            converter with &amp; without circulating current – four-quadrant
            operation
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Inverters – voltage source inverters– 1-phase half-bridge &amp; full
            bridge inverter with R &amp; RL loads – THD in output voltage – 3-
            phase bridge inverter with R load – 120° &amp; 180° conduction mode
            – current source inverters.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Voltage control in inverters – Pulse Width Modulation – single
            pulse width, multiple pulse width &amp; sine PWM – modulation index &amp; frequency
            modulation ratio.
            \n\nAC voltage controllers (ACVC) – 1-phase full-wave ACVC with
            R, &amp; RL loads – waveforms – RMS output voltage, input power
            factor with R load – sequence control (two stage) with R load
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>DC-DC converters – step down and step up choppers – single-
            quadrant, two-quadrant &amp; four quadrant chopper – pulse width
            modulation &amp; current limit control in dc-dc converters. Switching
            regulators – buck, boost &amp; buck-boost - continuous conduction
            mode only – waveforms – design of filter inductance &amp; capacitance
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee306">

        <item>PSA</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Per unit quantities-single phase and three phase-selection of
            base quantities -advantages of per unit system –changing the
            base of per unit quantities-Simple problems.
            \n\nModelling of power system components - single line diagram –
            per unit quantities. Symmetrical components- sequence
            impedances and sequence networks of generators, transformers
            and transmission lines.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Methods of analyzing faults in symmetrical and unsymmetrical
            case- effects of faults - Power system faults - symmetrical
            faults - short circuit MVA - current limiting reactors- Unsymmetrical faults - single
            line to ground, line to line,
            double line to ground faults -consideration of prefault current-
            problems.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Load flow studies – Introduction-types-network model
            formulation - formation of bus impedance and admittance
            matrix, Gauss-Siedel (two iterations), Newton-Raphson
            (Qualitative analysis only) and Fast Decoupled method (two
            iterations) - principle of DC load flow.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Automatic Generation Control: Load frequency control: single
            area and two area systems -
            \n\nAutomatic voltage control.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Economic Operation - Distribution of load between units
            within a plant - transmission loss as a function of plant
            generation - distribution of load between plants - Method of
            computing penalty factors and loss coefficients.
            \n\nUnit commitment: Introduction — Constraints on unit
            commitments: Spinning reserve, Thermal unit constraints-
            Hydro constraints. -
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Power system stability - steady state, dynamic and transient
            stability-power angle curve-steady state stability limit
            \n\nMechanics of angular motion-Swing equation – Solution of
            swing equation - Point by Point method - RK method - Equal
            area criterion application - Methods of improving stability
            limits.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee307">

        <item>SS</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to signals and systems - Classification of signals -
            Basic operations on signals – Elementary signals –
            Concept of system - Properties of systems - Stability,
            inevitability- time invariance- Linearity -Causality – Memory-
            Convolution- Impulse response- Representation of LTI
            systems - Differential equation representations of LTI systems
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Laplace transform analysis of systems - Relation between the
            transfer function and differential equation –Causality and
            stability - Inverse system - Determining the time domain and
            frequency response from poles and zeros
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Fourier representation of continuous time signals –Fourier Series-Harmonic analysis of
            common signals-
            Fourier transform - Existence –properties of FT- Energy
            spectral density and power spectral density - Frequency
            response of LTI systems -
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Sampled data systems- Sampling process-sampling theorem-
            signal re construction- Zero order and First order hold circuits-
            Difference equation representations of LTI systems -
            Discrete form of special functions- Discrete convolution and
            its properties
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Z Transform - Region of convergence- Properties of the Z
            transform –
            Inverse ZT-methods
            Z-transfer function- Analysis of difference equation of LTI
            systems – Basic idea on Stability and causality conditions-
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Fourier representation of discrete time signals - Discrete
            Fourier series–properties- Frequency response of simple DT
            systems
            Basics of Non linear systems-types and properties
            Introduction to random signals and processes (concepts only)
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee308">

        <item>ED</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to electric drives – Block diagram – advantages of electric
            drives – Dynamics of motor load system, fundamental equations, and
            types of load – classification of load torque, four quadrant operation of
            drives. Steady state stability. Introduction to closed loop control of
            drives.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>DC motor drives- constant torque and constant power operation,
            separately excited dc motor drives using controlled rectifiers, single
            phase semi converter and single phase fully controlled converter drives.
            Three phase semi converter and fully controlled converter drives. Dual
            converters, applications of dual converter for speed control of DC
            motor. Closed loop control of separately excited dc motor drive. DC
            series motor drive for traction application.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Chopper controlled DC drives. Analysis of single quadrant chopper
            drives. Regenerative braking control. Two quadrant chopper drives.
            Four quadrant chopper drives.
            Cycloconverters for drive applications – different types – basic
            principle.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Three phase induction motor speed control. Using semiconductor
            devices. Stator voltage control – stator frequency control - Stator
            voltage and frequency control (v/f). Rotor chopper speed control - slip
            power recovery control schemes – sub synchronous and super
            synchronous speed variations.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Voltage source inverter fed induction motor drives, Current source
            inverter fed induction motor drives. Concept of space vector – Basic
            transformation in reference frame theory – field orientation principle.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Synchronous motor drives – introduction to v/f control.
            Permanent Magnet synchronous motor drives – different types –
            control requirements, converter circuits, modes of operation.
            Microcontroller based permanent magnet synchronous motor
            drives (schematic only).
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee309">

        <item>MES</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Internal architecture of 8085 microprocessor –Instruction set - Addressing modes –
            Classification of instructions. Assembly language programming –standard programs in
            assembly language – code conversion, sorting – binary and BCD arithmetic
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Stack and Subroutines – CALL and RETURN instructions – Delay subroutines. Timing and
            control – Machine cycles, instruction cycle and T states – fetch and execute cycles –
            Timing diagram for instructions
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>IO and memory interfacing – Address decoding– interrupt structure of 8085. I/O ports-
            Programmable peripheral interface PPI 8255 - Modes of operation. Interfacing of LEDs,
            ADC and DAC with 8085
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Embedded Systems-Application domain of embedded systems, features and
            characteristics, System model, Microprocessor Vs Microcontroller, current trends and
            challenges, hard and soft real time systems, Embedded product development, Life Cycle
            Management (water fall model), Tool Chain System, Assemblers, Compilers, linkers,
            Loaders, Debuggers Profilers &amp; Test Coverage Tools
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>8051- Microcontrollers Hardware: Microcontroller Architecture: IO Port structure,
            Register organization, general purpose RAM, Bit Addressable RAM, Special Function
            Registers (SFRs). Instruction Set, addressing modes Instruction Types.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>8051- assembly language programming, data types and directives, Time delay and I/O
            port programming, Embedded Programming in C, data type and time delay in C, I/O port
            programming, Timer / counter programming, serial port programming, Interfacing – LCD,
            ADC, Stepper motor, and DAC
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee311">
        <item>EDCA</item>

        <item>DC Machines</item>
        <item>Principle of operation-emf equation-types of excitations. Separately excited, shunt
            and series excited DC generators, compound generators. General idea of armature
            reaction, OCC and load characteristics - simple numerical problems.
        </item>
        <item>Principles of DC motors</item>
        <item>Torque and speed equations-torque speed characteristics- variations of speed, torque
            and power with motor current. Applications of dc shunt series and compound motors.
            Principles of starting, losses and efficiency – load test- simple numerical problems
        </item>
        <item>Transformers</item>
        <item>Principles of operations – emf equation- vector diagrams- losses and efficiency – OC
            and SC tests. Equivalent circuits-efficiency calculations- maximum efficiency – all day
            efficiency –simple numerical problems. Auto transformers constant voltage transformer-
            instrument transformers
        </item>
        <item>Three phase induction motors</item>
        <item>Slip ring and squirrel cage types-principles of operation – rotating magnetic field-
            torque slip
            characteristics- no load and blocked rotor tests. Circle diagrams- methods of starting –
            direct online – auto transformer starting
        </item>
        <item>Single phase motors</item>
        <item>Principle of operation of single phase induction motor – split phase motor – capacitor
            start motor- stepper motor-universal motor Synchronous machines types – emf equation of
            alternator – regulation of alternator by emf method. Principles of operation of
            synchronous motors- methods of starting- V curves-synchronous condenser
        </item>
        <item>Stepper motors</item>
        <item>Principle of operation, multistack variable reluctance motors, single-stack variable
            reluctance motors, Hybrid stepper motors,Linear stepper motor, comparison, Torque-speed
            characteristics,control of stepper motors
            Controllers for automation, servo control, Digital controllers, Advanced control
            systems, Digital signal processors, motor controllers,Axis controllers, Machine tool
            controllers, Programmable Logic Controllers
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee312">

        <item>EEE</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Transformers-Operating principle, ideal and practical
            transformers, EMF equation, No load phasor diagram,
            equivalent circuit, phasor diagram of a transformer on load.
            Approximate equivalent circuit of transformer and its
            simplification. Voltage regulation, efficiency, condition for
            maximum efficiency, transformer tests.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Three phase Induction motors- principle of action, frequency of
            rotor emf and current. Factors determining the torque. Torque-
            slip curve, comparison of slip ring and cage rotors.
            Single phase induction motors-capacitor run induction motor,
            split phase motors, shaded pole motors.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Direct current machines-general arrangement of a dc machine,
            calculation of e.m.f. generated in an armature winding, armature
            reaction, commutation. Armature and field connections. A dc
            machine as generator or motor. Speed of a motor, speed
            characteristics of shunt, series and compound motors. Torque
            characteristics of shunt, series and compound motors.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Control system motors-Motors for regulators, RPC system
            requirements, Geneva cam, stepper motor, variable reluctance
            motor, hybrid stepping motor, drive circuits.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Motor selection-Factors affecting the selection motors-speed,
            power rating and duty cycles, load torques. The motor and its
            environment.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Power electronics- introduction to power electronics, thyristor
            circuits, limitations to thyristor operation, thyristors in practice,
            The fully controlled a.c./d.c. converter, ac/dc inversion.
            Switching devices in inverters.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee372">

        <item>BI</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Development of biomedical instrumentation, biometrics, man instrument system
            components block diagram, physiological systems of the body (brief discussion on Heart
            and cardio vascular system, Anatomy of nervous system, Physiology of respiratory
            systems) problems encountered in biomedical measurements. Sources of bioelectric
            potentials resting and action potentials - propagation of action potentials bio electric
            potentials example (ECG, EEG, EMG, ERG, EOG,EGG etc.)
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Bio potential electrodes theory microelectrodes skin surface electrodes needle
            electrodes biochemical transducers transducers for biomedical
            applications.\neElectro-conduction system of the heart. Electro cardiography electrodes
            and leads Einthoven triangle, ECG read out devices, ECG machine - block diagram.
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Measurement of blood pressure direct and indirect measurement oscillometric
            measurement ultrasonic method, measurement of blood flow and cardiac output,
            plethysmography photo electric and impedance plethysmographs\nMeasurement of heart
            sounds phonocardiography
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Cardiac pacemakers internal and external pacemakers, defibrillators.\nElectro
            encephalogram neuronal communication EEG measurement. Muscle response Electromyogram
            (EMG) Nerve Conduction velocity measurements- Electromyogram Measurements. Respiratory
            parameters Spiro meter, pneumograp
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Ventilators, heart lung machine, hemodialysis, lithotripsy, infant incubator\nX-rays-
            principles of generation, uses of X-rays- diagnostic still picture, fluoroscopy,
            angiography, endoscopy, diathermy. Basic principle of computed tomography, magnetic
            resonance imaging system and nuclear medicine system radiation therapy. Ultrasonic
            imaging system - introduction and basic principle
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Instruments for clinical laboratory test on blood cells chemical tests - Electrical
            safety physiological effects of electric current shock hazards from electrical equipment
            method of accident prevention, introduction to tele- medicine
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee363">

        <item>COD</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Basic Structure of computers – functional units – Historical Perspective -Basic
            operational concepts – bus structures, Measuring performance: evaluating, comparing and
            summarizing performance
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Memory locations and addresses – memory operations – instructions and instruction
            sequencing ,Instruction sets- RISC and CISC paradigms, Addressing modes
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Computer arithmetic - Signed and unsigned numbers - Addition and subtraction - Logical
            operations - Constructing an ALU - Multiplication and division – faster versions of
            multiplication- floating point representation and arithmetic
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>The processor: Building a data path - Simple and multi-cycle implementations -
            Microprogramming – Exceptions
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to pipelining-pipeline Hazards, Memory hierarchy - Caches - Cache
            performance - Virtual memory - Common framework for memory hierarchies
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Input/output - I/O performance measures – I/O techniques - interrupts, polling, DMA;
            Synchronous vs. Asynchronous I/O; Controllers. Types and characteristics of I/O devices
            - Buses - Interfaces in I/O devices - Design of an I/O system
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ee362">

        <item>DSA</item>

        <item>Linear Structures</item>
        <item>Abstract data types(ADT), List ADT, Array based implementation, Linked list
            implementation, Curser based linked lists, Doubly linked lists, Applications of lists,
            Stack ADT, Queue ADT, Circular queue implementation, Applications of stacks and queues
        </item>

        <item>Tree Structures</item>
        <item>Need for nonlinear structures, Tree ADT, Tree traversals, Left child right sibling
            data structures for general trees, Binary tree ADT, Expression trees, Applications of
            trees, Binary search tree ADT
        </item>

        <item>Balanced Search Trees and Indexing</item>
        <item>AVL trees, Binary heaps, Btrees, Hashing, Separate chaining, Open addressing, Linear
            probing
        </item>

        <item>Graphs</item>
        <item>Definitions, Topological sort, Breadth-first traversal, Shortest-path algorithms,
            Minimum spanning tree, Prim’s and Kruskal’s algorithms, Depth-first traversal, Bio
            connectivity, Euler circuits, Applications of graphs
        </item>

        <item>Algorithm Design</item>
        <item>Greedy algorithm, Divide and conquer, Dynamic programming, Backtracking, Branch and
            bound, Randomized algorithms
        </item>

        <item>Algorithm Analysis</item>
        <item>Asymptotic notations, Recurrences, NP complete problems</item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee365">

        <item>DSD</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction : Modern Digital Design, CMOS Technology, Programmable Logic ,Electrical
            Properties\nCombinational Logic Design : Boolean Algebra , Logic Gates, Combinational
            Logic Design, Timing, Number codes
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Combinational Logic using VHDL Gate Models : Entities and Architectures ,Identifiers ,
            Spaces and Comments ,Net lists , Signal Assignments ,Generics ,Constant and Open Ports
            ,Test benches, Configurations\nCombinational Building Blocks : Three-Stat Buffers ,
            Decoders ,Multiplexers, Priority Encoders , Adders, Parity Checkers , Test benches for
            Combinational blocks
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Synchronous Sequential Design : Synchronous Sequential Systems , Models of Synchronous
            Sequential Systems, Algorithmic State Machines ,Synthesis from ASM chart , State
            Machines in VHDL , VHDL Test benches for State Machines
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>VHDL Models of Sequential Logic Blocks : Latches , Flip-Flops , J K and T Flip Flop ,
            Registers and Shift Registers ,Counters , Memory, Sequential Multiplier, Test benches
            for Sequential Building Blocks\nComplex Sequential Systems : Data path / Control
            Partitioning ,Instructions, A Simple Microprocessor, VHDL model of a Simple
            Microprocessor
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>VHDL Simulation: Event Driven Simulation, Simulation of VHDL models , Simulation
            modelling issues , Fire Operations\nVHDL Synthesis : RTL Synthesis , Constraints
            ,Synthesis for FPGAs ,Behavioural Synthesis , Verifying Synthesis Results
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Testing Digital Systems : Need for Testing , Fault Models , Fault oriented Test
            Pattern Generation , Fault Simulation, Fault Simulation in VHDL\nDesign for Testability
            : Ad Hoc Testability improvements , Structured Design for Test , Built-in-Self-Test ,
            Boundary scan ( IEEE 1149 .1 )
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee369">

        <item>HVE</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Generation and transmission of electric energy – voltage stress – testing voltages-AC
            to DC conversion – rectifier circuits – cascaded circuits – voltage multiplier circuits
            – Cockroft-Walton circuits – voltage regulation – ripple factor – Van de-Graaff
            generator
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Generation of high AC voltages-Testing transformer – single unit testing transformer,
            cascaded transformer – equivalent circuit of cascaded transformer – generation of high
            frequency AC voltagesseries resonance circuit – resonant transformer – voltage
            regulation
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Generation of impulse voltages-Marx generator – Impulse voltage generator circuit
            –analysis of various impulse voltage generator circuits - multistage impulse generator
            circuits – Switching impulse generator circuits – impulse current generator circuits
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Peak voltage measurements by sphere gaps – Electrostatic voltmeter – generating
            voltmeters and field sensors – Chubb-Fortescue method – voltage dividers and impulse
            voltage measurements- measurement of impulse currents
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Objectives of high voltage testing, Classification of testing methods- self
            restoration and non-self restoration systems-standards and specifications, Measurement
            of dielectric constant and loss factor, Partial discharge measurements-Basic partial
            discharge(PD) circuit – PD currents- PD quantities - Corona and RIV measurements
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Testing of insulators, bushings, air break switches, isolators, circuit breakers,
            power transformers, surge diverters, cables -testing methodology\nClassification of high
            voltage laboratories, Voltage and power rating of test equipment, Layout of high voltage
            laboratories, Grounding of impulse testing laboratories
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee366">

        <item>IE</item>

        <item>Introduction of Light</item>
        <item>Types of illumination, Day lighting, Supplementary artificial lighting and total
            lighting, Quality of good lighting, Factors affecting the lighting-shadow, glare,
            reflection, Colour rendering and stroboscopic effect, Methods of artificial lighting,
            Lighting systems-direct, indirect, semi direct, semi indirect, Lighting scheme, General
            and localised
        </item>

        <item>Measurement of Light</item>
        <item>Definition of luminous flux, Luminous intensity, Lumen, Candle power, Illumination,
            M.H.C.P, M.S.C.P, M.H.S.C.P, Lamp efficiency, Brightness or luminance, Laws of
            illumination, Inverse square law and Lambert’s Cosine law, Illumination at horizontal
            and vertical plane from point source, Concept of polar curve, Calculation of luminance
            and illumination in case of linear source, round source and flat source
        </item>

        <item>Design of Interior Lighting</item>
        <item>Definitions of maintenance factor, Uniformity ratio, Direct ratio, Coefficients of
            utilisation and factors affecting it, Illumination required for various work planes,
            Space to mounting height ratio, Types of fixtures and relative terms used for interior
            illumination such as DLOR and ULOR, Selection of lamp and luminance, Selection of
            utilisation factor, reflection factor and maintenance factor\nDetermination of Lamp
            Lumen output taking into account voltage and temperature variations, Calculation of
            wattage of each lamp and no of lamps needed, Layout of lamp luminaire, Calculation of
            space to mounting height ratio, Indian standard recommendation and standard practices
            for illumination levels in various areas, Special feature for entrance, staircase,
            Corridor lighting and industrial building
        </item>

        <item>Street Lighting</item>
        <item>Types of street and their level of illumination required, Terms related to street and
            street lighting, Types of fixtures used and their suitable application, Various
            arrangements in street lighting, Requirements of good street lighting, Selection of lamp
            and luminaire, Calculation of their wattage, Number and arrangement, Calculation of
            space to mounting height ratio, Calculation of illumination level available on road
        </item>

        <item>Flood Lighting</item>
        <item>Terms related to flood lighting, Types of fixtures and their suitable applications,
            Selection of lamp and projector, Calculation of their wattage and number and their
            arrangement, Calculation of space to mounting height ratio, Recommended method for
            aiming of lamp
        </item>

        <item>Special Features of Aesthetic Lighting</item>
        <item>Monument and statue lighting, Sports lighting, Hospital lighting, Auditorium
            lighting
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee367">

        <item>NRES</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction, Classification of Energy Resources; Conventional Energy Resources -
            Availability and their limitations; Non-Conventional Energy Resources – Classification,
            Advantages, Limitations; Comparison of Conventional and Non-Conventional Energy
            Resources; World Energy Scenario; Indian Energy Scenario. ENERGY STORAGE: Sizing and
            Necessity of Energy Storage
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>SOLAR THERMAL SYSTEMS: Introduction, Solar Constant, Basic Sun-Earth Angles,
            Measurement of Solar Radiation Data – Pyranometer and Pyrheliometer .Principle of
            Conversion of Solar Radiation into Heat, – Solar thermal collectors – General
            description and characteristics – Flat plate collectors – Heat transfer processes –
            Solar concentrators (parabolic trough, parabolic dish, Central Tower Collector)
            –performance evaluation
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>SOLAR ELECTRIC SYSTEMS: Solar Thermal Electric Power Generation –; Solar Photovoltaic
            – Solar Cell fundamentals, characteristics, classification, construction of module,
            panel and array. Solar PV Systems – stand-alone and grid connected; Applications –
            Street lighting, Domestic lighting and Solar Water pumping systems
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>ENERGY FROM OCEAN: Tidal Energy – Principle of Tidal Power, Components of Tidal Power
            Plant (TPP), Classification of Tidal Power Plants, Advantages and Limitations of TPP.
            Ocean Thermal Energy Conversion (OTEC): Principle of OTEC system, Methods of OTEC power
            generation – Open Cycle (Claude cycle), Closed Cycle (Anderson cycle) and Hybrid cycle
            (block diagram description of OTEC); Site-selection criteria, Biofouling, Advantages
            &amp; Limitations of OTEC
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>WIND ENERGY: Introduction, Wind and its Properties, History of Wind Energy, Wind
            Energy Scenario – World and India. Basic principles of Wind Energy Conversion Systems
            (WECS), Classification of WECS, Parts of WECS, Derivation for Power in the wind,
            Electrical Power Output and Capacity Factor of WECS, Advantages and Disadvantages of
            WECS
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>BIOMASS ENERGY: Introduction, Photosynthesis process, Biomass fuels, Biomass
            conversion technologies, Urban waste to Energy Conversion, Biomass Gasification, Biomass
            to Ethanol Production, Biogas production from waste biomass, factors affecting biogas
            generation, types of biogas plants – KVIC and Janata model; Biomass program in India.
            Small hydro power: Classification as micro, mini and small hydro projects - Basic
            concepts and types of turbines - Design and selection considerations. EMERGING
            TECHNOLOGIES: Fuel Cell, Small Hydro Resources, Hydrogen Energy, alcohol energy, nuclear
            fusion and power from satellite stations.
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee361">

        <item>OOP</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Review of Object Oriented Concepts - Objects and classes in Java – defining classes –
            methods – access specifiers
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Static methods– constructors, Arrays – Strings -Packages – JavaDoc comments</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Inheritance – class hierarchy – polymorphism – dynamic binding – final keyword –
            abstract classes – the Object class – Reflection – interfaces – object cloning – inner
            classes
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Streams and Files -Use of Streams, Object Streams,Applet Basics-The Applet HTML Tags
            and Attributes, Multimedia, The Applet Context, JAR Files
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>File Management. Multithreaded programming– Thread properties – Creating a thread
            -Interrupting threads –Thread priority- thread synchronization – Synchronized method
            -Inter thread communication
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Database Programming -The Design of JDBC, The Structured Query Language, JDBC
            Installation, Basic JDBC Programming Concepts, Query Execution
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee368">

        <item>SC</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction To Soft Computing And Neural Networks : Evolution of Computing - Soft
            Computing Constituents From Conventional AI to Computational Intelligence - Adaptive
            Networks Feed forward Networks Supervised Learnin
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Neural Networks Radia Basis Function Networks - Reinforcement Learning Unsupervised
            Learning Neural Networks Adaptive Resonance architectures.\nFuzzy Sets And Fuzzy Logic:
            Fuzzy Sets Operations on Fuzzy Sets Fuzzy Relations - Fuzzy Rules and Fuzzy Reasoning
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Fuzzy Inference Systems Fuzzy Logic Fuzzy Expert Systems Fuzzy Decision
            Making\nNeuro-Fuzzy Modeling : Adaptive Neuro-Fuzzy Inference Systems Coactive
            Neuro-Fuzzy Modeling Classification and Regression Trees
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Data Clustering Algorithms Rulebase Structure Identification NeuroFuzzy Control</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Machine Learning : Machine Learning Techniques Machine Learning Using Neural Nets
            Genetic Algorithms (GA)
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Applications of GA in Machine Learning - Machine Learning Approach to Knowledge
            Acquisition. Support Vector Machines for Learning Linear Learning Machines Support
            Vector Classification Support Vector Regression - Applications
        </item>
    </array>
    <array name="ee364">

        <item>SMPC</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Switched Mode DC-to-DC Converter - buck converters – boost Converter – buck-boost
            converter - Continuous Conduction mode – design of filter inductance &amp;capacitance -
            boundary between continuous and discontinuous conduction – critical values of
            inductance/load resistance - discontinuous conduction mode with constant output voltage
            - Output voltage ripple
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Cuk converter – Full-ridge dc-dc Converter – PWM with bipolar voltage and unipolar
            voltage switching –comparison of dc-dc converters - Linear Power Supply – disadvantages
            of linear power supply – switched mode power supply – dc-dc converters with electrical
            isolation –unidirectional core excitation &amp; bidirectional core excitation
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Fly back converter – continuous &amp; discontinuous conduction mode - double ended fly
            back converter – forward converters – basic forward converter – practical forward
            converter – continuous conduction mode only - double ended forward converter – push pull
            converter – half bridge converter – full bridge converter – continuous conduction mode –
            current source dc-dc converter
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Switched Mode DC to AC converter – 1-phase square wave full-bridge inverter – square
            wave switching scheme - sine PWM switching scheme – PWM with bipolar &amp; unipolar
            voltage switching - harmonic analysis of output voltage – output control by voltage
            cancellation - 3-phase voltage source inverter – 3-phase sine PWM inverter – RMS line to
            line voltage &amp; RMS fundamental line-to-line voltage – square wave operation -
            Switching utilisation ratio of 1-phase &amp; 3-phase full-bridge inverters
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Concept of space vector – space vector modulation – reference vector &amp; switching
            times – space vector sequence – comparison of sine PWM &amp; space vector PWM -
            programmed (selective) harmonic elimination switching – current controlled voltage
            source inverter - hysteresis current control
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Resonant Converters - Basic resonant circuit concepts – series resonant circuit –
            parallel resonant circuit – load resonant converter - ZCS resonant converter - L type
            &amp; M type - ZVS resonant converter – comparison of ZCS &amp; ZVS Resonant Converters
        </item>
    </array>


</resources>