<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <array name="ae202">
        <item>CP</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Programming basics: Flowcharts and Algorithms. Compiler– Interpreter-Linker-Loader.
            Structured programming Introduction to C: Character set, Identifiers, Keywords,
            Constants –Data Types- Variables – Operators and Expressions – Operator precedence and
            associativity – Expression Evaluation (Simple Examples) – Simple computational problems
            involving the above constructs
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Control Statements: Selection, Iteration (for, while, do-while), Branching (switch,
            break, continue, goto), Nesting of control statements- simple programs using control
            statements
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Arrays and Strings: 1D and 2D arrays –Searching (Linear and binary) - Sorting (Bubble,
            Selection) – Matrix manipulation programs – Strings and basic operations on strings –
            String functions – Basic Programs on string manipulation. Functions: Definition –
            Calling – Declaration – Parameter Passing (by value and by reference) – Recursion –
            Library functions –Basic Programs based on functions.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>User defined data types: Structure – Union - Enumerated data type - Programs involving
            structure and union. Pointers: Declaration, Initialization – Pointers and arrays –
            Pointers and structures – Pointers and functions – Command line arguments – Dynamic
            memory allocation – Operations on pointers – Basic Programs involving the above concepts
            Files: file operations
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Object oriented programming Introduction to Python : Comparison of following Python
            constructs with C- keywords, variables, operators, expression and statements, control
            statements- programming examples
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Comparison of constructs of python with C - Functions, calling functions, user defined
            functions, strings and lists-programming examples Basics of Tuples, Dictionary and
            Exception handling in python.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ae204">
        <item>SAT</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Transducers: Definition of transducers, classification based on transduction
            principle, measurand, material and technology, Analog and digital transducers, Active
            and passive transducers, Primary and Secondary transducers. Characteristics of
            transducers
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Resistance Transducer : Basic principle – Potentiometer – Loading effects, Resolution,
            Linearity, Resistance strain gauge –Types.Inductance Transducer :- Basic principle –
            Linear variable differential transformer – RVDT-types. Capacitance Transducer : Basic
            principle- transducers using change in area of plates – distance between plates-
            variation of dielectric constants-frequency response –Types
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Force and Torque Transducers: Proving ring, hydraulic and pneumatic load cell,
            dynamometer and gyroscopes. Sound Transducers: Sound level meter, sound characteristics,
            Microphone. Torque transducer design-the torque measurement system-the rotation rate
            measurement system
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Pressure Transducers: basic principle- different types of manometers-u tube
            manometer-well type manometers. Level transducer-continuous level measurement-discrete
            level measurement-mass –capacitive level gauges, Dead weight calibrator
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Hall effect transducers, Digital transducers, Proximity devices, , Piezo-electric
            sensors, eddy current transducers, tachogenerators and stroboscope, Magnetostrictive
            transducers, Fibre optic sensor, Semiconductor sensor. Basics of Seismic instrument and
            accelerometers
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Flow Transducers: Bernoulli’s principle and continuity, orifice plate, nozzle plate,
            venture tube, Rota meter, anemometers, electromagnetic flow meter, impeller meter and
            turbid flow meter
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ae301">
        <item>CS</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>System Analysis: Systems, subsystems, and stochastic and deterministic systems -
            Principles of automatic control -Open loop and closed loop systems -Principles of
            superposition and homogeneity-Transfer Function Approach: Mathematical models of
            physical systems and transfer function approach Impulse response and transfer function
            -Determination of transfer functions for simple electrical, mechanical,
            electromechanical, hydraulic and pneumatic systems - Analogous systems -Multiple-input
            multiple-output systems: Block diagram algebra - block diagram reduction -Signal flow
            graphs -Mason\'s gain formula.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Time Domain Analysis: Standard test signals -Response of systems to standard test
            signals –Step response of second order systems -Time domain specifications (of second
            order system) -Steady state response -Steady state error -Static and dynamic error
            coefficients -Zero input and zero state response
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Stability of linear systems -absolute stability -relative stability -Hurwitz and Routh
            stability criterion -Root locus method construction of root locus -root contours -root
            sensitivity to gain k -effect of poles and zeros and their locations on the root locus.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Frequency Domain Analysis: Frequency response representation -Frequency domain
            specifications -Correlation between time and frequency response -Polar plots Logarithmic
            plots -Bode plots – All pass, minimum-phase and non-minimum-phase systems
            -Transportation lag - Stability in frequency domain -Nyquist stability criterion
            Stability from polar and bode plot -Gain margin and phase margin -relative stability
            -M-N circles -Nichols chart
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>State Variable Analysis: Concepts of state, state variables, state vector and state
            space -State model of continuous time systems Transformation of state variable
            -Derivation of transfer function from state model -invariance property
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>State diagram -State variable from transfer function -bush or companion form
            -controllable canonical form - observable canonical form -Jordan canonical form
            -Diagonalization-State transition matrix -computation of state transition matrix by
            Laplace transform, Cayley-Hamilton theorem -Controllability and observability of a
            system. (proof not required
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ae302">
        <item>PCL</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Process characteristics: Incentives for process control, Process Variables types and
            selection criteria,, Process degree of freedom, The period of Oscillation and Damping,
            Characteristics of physical System: Resistance, Capacitive and Combination of both.
            Elements of Process Dynamics, Types of processes- Dead time, Single /multi capacity,
            selfRegulating /non self-regulating, Interacting /non interacting, Linear/non-linear,
            and Selection of control action for them. Study of Liquid Processes, Gas Processes, Flow
            Processes, Thermal Processes in respect to above concepts
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Analysis of Control Loop: Steady state gain, Process gain, Valve gain, Process time
            constant, Variable time Constant, Transmitter gain, Linearizing an equal percentage
            valve, Variable pressure drop. Analysis of Flow Control, Pressure Control, Liquid level
            Control, Temperature control, SLPC-features, faceplate, functions, MLPC- features,
            faceplate, functions, SLPC and MLPC comparison. Scaling: types of scaling, examples of
            scaling
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Feedback Control: Basic principles, Elements of the feedback Loop, Block Diagram,
            Control Performance Measures for Common Input Changes, Selection of Variables for
            Control Approach to Process Control. Factors in Controller Tuning, Determining Tuning
            Constants for Good Control Performance, Correlations for tuning Constants, Fine Tuning
            of the controller tuning Constants
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Multi Loop &amp; Nonlinear Systems: Cascade control, Feed forward control,
            feedback-feed forward control, Ratio control, Selective Control , Split range control-
            Basic principles, Design Criteria , Performance, Controller Algorithm and Tuning,
            Implementation issues, Examples and any special features of the individual loop and
            industrial applications. Nonlinear Elements in Loop: Limiters, Dead Zones, Backlash,
            Dead Band Velocity Limiting, Negative Resistance
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Multivariable Control: Concept of Multivariable Control: Interactions and its effects,
            Modelling and transfer functions, Influence of Interaction o the possibility of feedback
            control, important effects on Multivariable system behaviour Relative Gain Array, effect
            of Interaction on stability and tuning of Multi Loop Control system. Multi Loop control
            Performance through: Loop Paring, tuning, Enhancement through Decoupling, Single Loop
            Enhancements
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Intelligent Controllers: Step analysis method for finding first, second and multiple
            time constants and dead time. Model Based controllers: Internal Model control, Smith
            predictor, optimal controller, Model Predictive controller, Dynamic matrix controller
            (DMC). Self Tuning Controller. Fuzzy logic systems and Fuzzy controllers, Introduction,
            Basic Concepts of Fuzzy Logic, Fuzzy Sets, Fuzzy Relation, Fuzzy Graphs, and Fuzzy
            Arithmetic, Fuzzy If-Then Rules, Fuzzy Logic Applications, Neuro-Fuzzy Artificial Neural
            networks and ANN controller
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ae303">
        <item>EMMI</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>General Principles of Measurements: Absolute and Working Standards- Calibration of
            Meters- Qualities of MeasurementsAccuracy, precision, sensitivity, resolution, loading
            effect. - Characteristics - Errors in Measurement and its Analysis
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Essentials of indicating instruments- deflecting, damping, controlling torques- Moving
            Coil , Moving Iron, Dynamo Meter, Induction, Thermal, Electrostatic and Rectifier Type
            meter; Shunts and Multipliers-Various Types of Galvanometers- Accuracy class.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>DC Bridges: Introduction, sources &amp; detectors for DC bridge,general equation for
            bridge at balance. Wheatstone and Kelvin’s double bridge, Carry Foster Slide Wire Bridge
            – Bridge Current Limitations
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>AC bridges: Introduction, sources &amp; detectors for a.c bridge, general equation for
            bridge at balance. Maxwell’s Inductance &amp; Maxwell’s Inductance-Capacitance Bridge,
            Anderson bridge, Measurements of capacitance using Schering Bridge. Potentiometers:
            General principle, Modern forms of dc potentiometers, standardization, Vernier dial
            principle, AC potentiometers – coordinate and polar types, application of dc and ac
            potentiometers
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Cathode ray oscilloscope (review), Special purpose oscilloscopes- delayed time base,
            analog storage, sampling oscilloscopes. Digital storage oscilloscopes-DSO applications.
            Method of measuring voltage, current, phase, frequency and period using CRO, DSO.
            Graphic Recording Instruments: strip chart recorder, X-Y recorder, Plotter, liquid
            crystal display (LCD).
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Waveform analysing instruments: Distortion meter, Spectrum analyser, Digital spectrum
            analyser, Q meter, Watthour meter, Power-factor meter, Instrument transformers,
            Thermocouple instruments, Peak response voltmeter, True RMS meter
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ae304">
        <item>II</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Temperature measurement: Resistance temperature detector (RTD), principle and types,
            construction requirements for industry, measuring circuits. Thermistors, principle and
            sensor types, manufacturing techniques, measuring circuits, linearization methods and
            applications. Pneumatic and suction pyrometers, integrated circuit sensors, diode type
            sensors, ultrasonic thermometers, Johnson noise thermometer, fluidic sensors,
            spectroscopic temperature measurements, thermograph, temperature switches and
            thermostats.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Pressure measurement basics, mechanical type instruments, electromechanical type, low
            pressure measurement, related accessories, pressure measuring standards, selection and
            application. Transmitter definition, classification, pneumatic transmitter-force balance
            type, torque balance type, two wire and four wire transmitters, I/P and P/I converters.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Measurement of viscosity: definitions, units, Newtonian and Newtonian behaviour,
            measurement of viscosity using laboratory viscometers, industrial viscometers.
            Viscometer selection and application. Measurement of density, definitions, units, liquid
            density measurement, gas densitometers, its application and selection
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Flow measurement: Introduction, definitions and units, classification of flow meters,
            pitot tubes, positive displacement liquid meters and provers, positive displacement gas
            flow meters, variable area flow meters.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Anemometers: Hot wire/hot film anemometer, laser Doppler anemometer (LDA),
            electromagnetic flow meter, turbine and other rotary element flow meters, ultrasonic
            flow meters, doppler flow meters, cross correlation flow meters, vortex flow meters.
            Measurement of mass flow rate: radiation, angular momentum, impeller, turbine, constant
            torque hysteresis clutch, twin turbine Coriolis, gyroscopic and heat transfer type mass
            flow meters. Target flow meters: V-cone flow meters purge flow regulators, flow
            switches, flow meter calibration concepts, flow meter selection and application.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Level measurement: introduction, float level devices, displacer level devices,
            rotating paddle switches, diaphragm and deferential pressure detectors, resistance,
            capacitance and RF probes, radiation, conductivity, field effect, thermal, ultrasonic,
            microwave level switches, radar and vibrating type level sensors. Level sensor selection
            and application.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ae305">
        <item>MP AND MC</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Intel 8086, format:, Assembler directives and operators, Assembly process, Linking and
            relocation, stacks, procedures, interrupt routines, macros.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>8086 hardware design - Bus structure, bus buffering and latching, system bus timing
            with diagram, Minimum and maximum mode configurations of 8086, Multi-processor
            configuration, 8087 co-processor architecture and configuration, Memory (RAM and ROM)
            interfacing, memory address decoding
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>8087 co-processor architecture and configuration, Memory (RAM and ROM) interfacing,
            memory address decoding
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to 80386 – Memory management unit – Descriptors, selectors, description
            tables and TSS – Real and protected mode – Memory paging – Pentium processor -Special
            features of the Pentium processor – Branch prediction logic– Superscalar architecture,
            microprocessors - state of the art
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>8051 Microcontroller: Overview of 8051 family, architecture of 8051, Program counter,
            ROM space in 8051, data types and directives, flags and PSW register, register bank and
            stack, Addressing modes. Instruction set Arithmetic instructions JUMP, LOOP,CALL
            instructions, time delay generations
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Assembly Language programming in 8051 (some simple programs): programs using
            arithmetic and logic instructions, single bit instructions and programs, Timer/counter
            programming, 8051 serial communication programming, programming timer interrupts.
            Interfacing with Stepper motor, keyboard, DAC, external memory
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ae306">
        <item>DSP</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Signal Processing Fundamentals: Discrete-time and digital signals, A/D, D/A conversion
            and Nyquist rate, Frequency aliasing due to sampling, Need for anti-aliasing filters.
            Discrete Time Fourier transform and frequency spectra, Spectral computation,
            Computational complexity of the DFT and the FFT, Algorithmic development and
            computational advantages of the FFT, Inverse FFT, Implementation of the FFT, Correlation
            of discrete-time signals.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Discrete-time systems, Difference equations and the Ztransform, Analysis of
            discrete-time LTIL systems, Stability and Jury’s test.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>FIR Filters: Ideal digital filters, Realizability and filter specifications,
            Classification of linear phase FIR filters, Design using direct truncation, window
            methods and frequency sampling, Least-squares optimal FIR filters, Minimax optimal FIR
            filters, Design of digital differentiators and Hilbert transformers, comparison of
            design methods.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>IIR Filters: Design of analogue prototype filters, Analog frequency transformations,
            Impulse invariance method and digital frequency transformations, Bilinear
            transformation, Analog prototype to digital transformations, Difficulties in direct IIR
            filter design, Comparisons with FIR filters.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Filter Realization: Structures for FIR filters, Structures for IIR filters,
            State-space analysis and filter structures, Fixed point and floating-point
            representation of numbers, Errors resulting from rounding and truncating, Quantization
            effects of filter coefficients, Round-off effects of digital filters
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>DSP Processors: Computer architectures for signal processing – Harvard architecture
            and pipelining, General purpose digital signal processors, Selection of DSPs,
            Implementation of DSP algorithms on a general purpose DSP, Special purpose hardware –
            hardware digital filters and hardware FFT processors, Evaluation boards for realtime
            DSP.
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ae307">
        <item>SS</item>
        <item></item>

        <item>Introduction to signals and systems - Classification of signals - Basic operations on
            signals – Elementary signals - Concept of system - Properties of systems - Stability,
            invertability, time invariance - Linearity - Causality - Memory - Time domain
            description - Convolution - Impulse response
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Representation of LTI systems - Differential equation and difference equation
            representations of LTI systems ,Continuous Time LTI systems and Convolution Integral,
            Discrete Time LTI systems and linear convolution
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Frequency response of LTI systems - Correlation theory of deterministic signals -
            Condition for distortionless transmission through an LTI system - Transmission of a
            rectangular pulse through an ideal low pass filter - Hilbert transform – Sampling and
            reconstruction
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Frequency Domain Representation of Continuous Time Signals- Continuous Time Fourier
            Series: Convergence. Continuous Time Fourier Transform: Properties. Frequency Domain
            Representation of Discrete Time Signals- Discrete Time Fourier Transform: Properties,
            Sampling Theorem, aliasing, reconstruction filter, sampling of band pass signals.
            Fourier Series Representation of Discrete Time Periodic Signals
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Laplace Transform – ROC – Inverse transform – properties – Analysis of Continuous LTI
            systems using Laplace Transform – unilateral Laplace Transform. Relation between Fourier
            and Laplace Transforms. Laplace transform analysis of systems - Relation between the
            transfer function and differential equation - Causality and stability - Inverse system -
            Determining the frequency response from poles and zeros
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Z Transform - Definition - Properties of the region of convergence - Properties of the
            Z transform - Analysis of LTI systems - Relating the transfer function and difference
            equation - Stability and causality - Inverse systems - Determining the frequency
            response from poles and zeros
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ae308">
        <item>AM</item>
        <item></item>

        <item>Introduction: Need of advance microprocessors, Difference between RISC and CISC, RISC
            Design philosophy, ARM Design Philosophy, History of ARM microprocessor, ARM processor
            family, Development of ARM architecture.

        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>The ARM Architecture and Programmers Model : The Acorn RISC Machine, ARM Core data
            flow model, Architectural inheritance, The ARM7TDMI programmer’s model: General purpose
            registers, CPSR, SPSR, ARM memory map, data format, load and store Architecture, Core
            extensions, Architecture revisions, ARM development tool.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>ARM Instruction set: Data processing instructions, Arithmetic and logical
            instructions, Rotate and barrel shifter, Branch instructions, Load and store
            instructions, Software interrupt instructions, Program status register
            instructions,Conditional execution, Multiple register load and store instructions, Stack
            instructions, Thumb instruction set, advantage of thumb instructions, Assembler rules
            and directives, Assembly language programs for shifting of data, factorial calculation,
            swapping register contents, moving values between integer and floating point registers
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>C Programming for ARM: Overview of C compiler and optimization, Basic C data types, C
            Looping structures, Register allocations, function calls, pointer aliasing, structure
            arrangement, bit fields, unaligned data and Endianness, Division, floating point, Inline
            functions and inline assembly, Portability issues. C programs for General purpose I/O,
            general purpose timer, PWM Modulator, UART, I2C Interface, SPI Interface, ADC, DAC.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Memory management units: Moving from memory protection unit (MPU) to memory management
            unit (MMU), Working of virtual memory, Multitasking, Memory organization in virtual
            memory system, Page tables, Translation look aside buffer, Caches and write Buffer, Fast
            context switch extension.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Advanced Microprocessor Bus Architecture (AMBA) Bus System, User peripherals,
            Exception handling in ARM, ARM optimization Techniques.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ae312">
        <item>PE</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Power semiconductor devices: Power diodes-types, power transistors, thyristor family,
            SCRs, Triac, GTOs, power MOSFETs, IGBTs, MCTs-static and dynamic characteristics,
            protection circuits, series and parallel connections, turn-on characteristics, turn off
            characteristics
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Controlled rectifiers- single phase and three phase converters-power factor
            improvements-design of converter circuits-AC volt-age controllers-single phase and three
            phase-cyclo converters-single phase and three phase, design of AC voltage controller
            circuits.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>DC choppers – principle of step down and step up operations – step down chopper with
            RL load, Classes of chopper, MOSFET/IGBT choppers
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>DC to AC converters: Thyristor inverters, McMurrayMcMurray Bedford inverter, current
            source inverter, voltage control waveform control, inverters using devices other than
            thyristors, vector control of induction motors.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>DC and AC power supplies: Switched mode, resonant, bidirectional and multistage
            conversions, buck, boost, buck boost regulators. UPS-block diagram, types. Drive
            requirements and design of simple drive circuits for power BJT, MOSFET and IGBT
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Advanced control of power electronic circuits using microprocessors, microcontrollers,
            isolation amplifier circuits, synchronization circuits.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ae361">
        <item>VID</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Review of digital instrumentation: - Representation of analog signals in the digital
            domain – Review of quantization in amplitude and time axes, sample and hold, sampling
            theorem, ADC and DAC
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Virtual Instrumentation: Historical perspective - advantages - block diagram and
            architecture of a virtual instrument Conventional Instruments versus Traditional
            Instruments - data-flow techniques, graphical programming in data flow, comparison with
            conventional programming.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>VI programming techniques: VIs and sub-VIs, loops and charts, arrays, clusters and
            graphs, case and sequence structures, formula nodes, local and global variables, State
            machine, string and file I/O, Instrument Drivers, Publishing measurement data in the
            web.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Data acquisition basics: Introduction to data acquisition on PC, Sampling
            fundamentals, Input/Output techniques and buses. ADC, DAC, Digital I/O, counters and
            timers, DMA, Software and hardware installation, Calibration, Resolution, Data
            acquisition interface requirements.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>VI Chassis requirements. Common Instrument Interfaces: Current loop, RS 232C/ RS485,
            GPIB. Bus Interfaces: USB, PCMCIA, VXI, SCSI, PCI, PXI, Firewire. PXI system
            controllers, Ethernet control of PXI. Networking basics for office &amp; Industrial
            applications, VISA and IVI
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>VI toolsets, Distributed I/O modules. Application of Virtual Instrumentation:
            Instrument Control, Development of process database management system, Simulation of
            systems using VI, Development of Control system, Industrial Communication, Image
            acquisition and processing, Motion control.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ae362">
        <item>IP</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Industrial and Organizational Psychology: Introduction to industrial
            psychology, Definition, scope, major influences, goals, key forces, and fundamental
            concepts, History of industrial psychology, Major Fields of I/O Psychology, scientific
            management.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Individual in Workplace : Motivation- Definition, Types, Theory-Maslow’s and Herzberg,
            Job satisfaction- Definition, Factors affecting Job Satisfaction, Consequences,
            Leadership - Definition, Leadership Styles, Approaches to Leadership, Organizational
            Culture -Definition, Levels, Characteristics, Types, Functions
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Development of Human Resources: Job Analysis- Definition, Purpose, Types, Process,
            Methods, Recent Developments Recruitment and Selection- Nature and objectives, Sources-
            Internal and External, Process, Definition and steps in selection process Performance
            Management- Definition, Scope, Process, Tools Training and Development- Meaning and
            nature, Objectives, Methods- on the job and off the job
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Consumer Psychology: Definition, Scope, Marketing concept. Market
            Segmentation- consumer rooted, consumption specific, and brand experience as
            segmentation bases. Targeting- criteria for effective targeting; Positioning and
            repositioning
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Consumer Decision Making : Levels of Decision making, Views of consumer decision
            making, Model of consumer decision making: Input – marketing efforts, socio cultural
            environment. Process – psychological field, need recognition, pre-purchase search,
            Evaluation of alternatives Output – Purchase behavior and post purchase evaluation.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Performance management: Training &amp; Development: Work environment &amp; engineering
            psychology – fatigue, boredom, accidents &amp; safety, Job analysis, Recruitment &amp;
            Selection, Reliability &amp; Validity of recruitment tests.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ae363">
        <item>VCD</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>VLSI process integration: - fundamental considerations in IC processing - NMOS IC
            technology - CMOS IC technology - BiCMOS IC technology - GaAs technology. Ion
            implantation in IC fabrication
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>The MOS device: (n - channel &amp; p- channel) - capacitance of MOS structure -
            accumulation, depletion and inversion, threshold voltage, current equations -
            characteristics, channel pinch-off. Second order MOS device effects: short-channel
            effect, narrow width effect, sub-threshold current, device saturation characteristics
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Switch logic- pass transistors and transmission gates, Gate logic-The basic inverter
            using NMOS-circuit – current equations - pull up to pull down ratio- transfer
            characteristics- Alternate forms of pull up. Basic NAND, NOR circuits. The CMOS
            inverter, characteristics – NAND, NOR and compound circuits using CMOS. Other forms of
            CMOS logic: pseudo CMOS, CMOS domino logic, n-p logic
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Layout design of static MOS circuits – Layout rules - general principles &amp; steps
            of lay-out design - use of stick diagrams - design rules - Layout examples of NAND and
            NOR-Fabrication
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Combinational circuits - clocked sequential circuit - drivers for bus lines. Scaling
            of MOS circuits: scaling models and scaling factors for device parameters
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Timing issues in VLSI system design: timing classification- synchronous timing basics
            – skew and jitter- latch based clocking- self timed circuit design - self timed logic,
            completion signal generation, self-timed signalling– synchronizers and arbiters
        </item>
    </array>

    <array name="ae364">
        <item>MEMS/NEMS</item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Foundation in Microsystems : Review of microelectronics manufacture and introduction
            to MEMS- Overview of microsystems technology, Laws of scaling- The multidisciplinary
            nature of MEMS- Survey of materials central to micro engineering- Applications of MEMS
            in various industries
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Micro Manufacturing Techniques : Photolithography- Film deposition, Etching
            Processes-Bulk micro machining, silicon surface micro machining
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Micro Actuators : Energy conversion and force generationElectromagnetic Actuators,
            Reluctance motors, piezoelectric actuators, bi-metal-actuator Friction and wear
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Micro Sensors : Transducer principles-Signal detection and signal
            processing-Mechanical and physical sensorsAcceleration sensor, pressure sensor, Sensor
            arrays.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Micro/Nano Fluids : Fundamentals of micro fluidics- Micro pump –
            introduction – Types - Mechanical Micro pump – Non mechanical micro pumps, Actuating
            Principles, Design rules for micro pump – modeling and simulation, Verification and
            testing – Applications
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Microsystem Design and Packaging : Design considerations-Mechanical Design, Process
            design, Realization of MEMS components using Intellisuite. Micro system
            packaging-Packing Technologies-Assembly of Microsystems- Reliability in MEMS.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ae365">
        <item>IFA</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Necessity of instrumentation &amp; control for agriculture, engineering properties of
            soil: fundamental definitions &amp; relationships, index properties of soil,
            permeability &amp; seepage analysis, shear strength, Mohr’s circle of stress, active
            &amp; passive earth pressures, stability &amp; slopes, Sensors: introduction to sonic
            anemometers, hygrometers, fine wire thermocouples, open &amp; close path gas analysers,
            brief introduction to various bio-sensors.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Flow diagram of sugar plant &amp; instrumentation set up for it, flow diagram of
            fermenter &amp; control(batch process),flow diagram of dairy industry &amp;
            instrumentation set up for it, juice extraction control process &amp; instrumentation
            set up for it
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Irrigation systems: necessity, irrigation methods: overhead, centre pivot, lateral
            move, micro irrigation systems &amp; it’s performance, comparison of different
            irrigation systems, soil moisture measurement methods: resistance based method, voltage
            based method, thermal based method, details of gypsum block soil moisture sensor,
            irrigation scheduling, irrigation efficiencies, design considerations in irrigation
            channels.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Application of SCADA for DAM parameters &amp; control, irrigation control management
            up- stream &amp; down - stream control systems, green houses &amp; instrumentation:
            ventilation, cooling &amp; heating, wind speed, temperature &amp; humidity, rain gauge
            carbon dioxide enrichment measurement &amp; control
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Automation in earth moving equipments &amp; farm equipments, application of SCADA
            &amp; PLC in packing industry and cold storage systems, implementation of Hydraulic,
            pneumatic &amp; electronics control circuits in harvester’s cotton pickers, tractor etc.
            classification of pumps: pump characteristics, pump selection &amp; installation
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Leaf area length evapotranspiration, temperature, wetness &amp; respiration
            measurement &amp; data logging, electromagnetic radiations photosynthesis, infrared
            &amp; UV bio sensor methods in agriculture, agro metrological instrumentation weather
            stations, surface flux measurement, soil water content measurement using time-domain
            reflectrometery (TDR), ground water occurrence confined &amp; unconfined aquifers,
            evaluation of aquifer properties, ground water recharge
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ae366">
        <item>ESD</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Introduction to Embedded Systems: Definition of Embedded System, Embedded Systems Vs
            General Computing Systems, History of Embedded Systems, Classification, Major
            Application Areas, Purpose of Embedded Systems, Characteristics and Quality Attributes
            of Embedded Systems
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Typical Embedded System: Core of the Embedded System: General Purpose and Domain
            Specific Processors, ASICs, PLDs, Commercial Off-The-Shelf Components (COTS), Memory:
            ROM, RAM, Memory according to the type of Interface, Memory Shadowing, Memory selection
            for Embedded Systems, Sensors and Actuators, Communication Interface: On board and
            External Communication Interfaces.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Embedded Firmware: Reset Circuit, Brown-out Protection Circuit, Oscillator Unit, Real
            Time Clock, Watchdog Timer, Embedded Firmware Design Approaches and Development
            Languages
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>RTOS Based Embedded System Design: Operating System Basics, Types of Operating
            Systems, Tasks, Process and Threads, Multiprocessing and Multitasking, Task Scheduling
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Task Communication: Shared Memory, Message Passing, Remote Procedure Call and Sockets,
            Task Synchronization: Task Communication /Synchronization Issues, Task Synchronization
            Techniques, Device Drivers, How to Choose an RTOS
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Programming concepts of Embedded programming in C Program Elements, Macros and
            functions - Use of Pointers - NULL Pointers - Use of Function Calls – Multiple function
            calls in a Cyclic Order in the Main Function Pointers – Function Queues and Interrupt
            Service Routines Queues Pointers – Concepts of embedded programming in C++ – Cross
            compiler – Optimization of memory codes. Real time operating systems Definitions of
            process, tasks and threads.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="ae368">
        <item>PE</item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Engineering Plastics : Sources and Manufacture of raw materials, Methods of
            Manufacture of Polymer, General Properties and applications of Acrylonitrile Butadiene
            Styrene -Polyamides (PA-6,PA-66,PA-6,10,PA-11&amp;12) – Polycarbonates – Poly acetal
            &amp; Copolymers - Thermoplastic Polyesters (PET&amp;PBT) Poly phenylene oxide – Poly
            sulfones Fluoropolymers (PVF,PVDF,PTFE,PCTFE) - Thermoplastic Polyurethane
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Concept of testing &amp; identification of plastics : Basic concepts of testing -
            Specification and Standards - National and International Standards - Test specimen
            preparation - Pre-conditioning and test atmosphere. Identification of plastics by simple
            tests - Visual examination - Density - Melting point - Solubility test - Flame test -
            Chemical tests
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Test methods and standards for bio-degradable plastics: Plastics – criteria used in
            evaluation of biodegradable plastics – description of current Test methods – Scanning
            test for ready biodegradability – Test for inherent biodegradability – Test for
            simulation studies – Other methods for assessing polymer biodegradability
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Recycling technologies for bio degradable plastics: Conventional recycling –
            Degradable complicate recycling – reprocessing polyethylene starch/film scrap –
            Economics in in-plant recycling
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Inspection and quality control of moulds : Introduction to Tool Room measuring
            instruments – Vernier– Micrometer – Height Gauge–Slip Gauge–Dial Gauge–Measuring tapers
            and angles–CMM
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Environmental consideration: Plastic waste – Classification, Segregation, Sorting and
            Waste Management viz. source reduction, reuse/repair, recycling related to packaging
            films and constrainers. Pollutants an outline – Chloro Fluoro Carbon (CFC), Dioxin Life
            cycle assessment: A case study
        </item>
    </array>
</resources>