<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <array name="me301">
        <item>MM</item>
        <item>1. Ballaney P. L., Theory of Machines and Mechanisms, Khanna Publishers,2005\n
            2. S. S. Rattan, Theory of Machines, Tata Mc Graw Hill,2009
        </item>
        <item>4</item>
        <item>NIL</item>
        <item>Introduction to kinematics and mechanisms</item>
        <item> Various mechanisms, kinematic diagrams, degree of freedom- Grashof’scriterion,
            inversions, coupler curves straight line mechanisms exact, approximate – Ackerman
            Steering Mechanism - Hooke’s joint - Geneva mechanism -mechanical advantage,
            transmission angle
        </item>
        <item>Displacement, velocity and acceleration analysis</item>
        <item> Relative motion - relative velocity - instant centre -Kennedy’s theorem Relative
            acceleration - Coriolis acceleration - graphical and analytical methods – complex number
            methods – computer oriented methods. Cams - classification of cam and followers –
            displacement diagrams, velocity and acceleration analysis of SHM, uniform velocity,
            uniform acceleration, cycloidal motion
        </item>
        <item>Module 3</item>
        <item>Graphical cam profile synthesis, pressure angle Analysis of tangent cam with roller
            follower and circular cam with flat follower Introduction to polynomial cams.
        </item>
        <item>Gears</item>
        <item>Gears – terminology of spur gears – law of Gearing - involute
            spur gears involutometry - contact ratio - interference - backlash -
            gear standardization – interchangability
            Non-standard gears, centre distance modification, long and short
            addendum system. - internal gears - theory and details of bevel,
            helical and worm gearing

        </item>
        <item>Gear trains</item>
        <item>Simple and compound gear trains - planetary gear trains – differential -solution of
            planetary gear train problems –applications Kinematic synthesis ( planar mechanisms) -
            tasks of kinematic synthesis – type, number and dimensional synthesis – precision
            points. Graphical synthesis for motion - path and prescribed timing -function generator
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>2 position and 3 position synthesis – overlay Method Analytical synthesis techniques,
            Freudenstein&apos;s equation –complex number methods - one case study in synthesis of
            mechanism.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me303">
        <item>MTDM</item>
        <item>
            1. Chapman W. A. J., Workshop Technology, Viva books (P) Ltd,1988\n
            2. HMT, Production Technology, Tata McGraw-Hill,2001\n
            3. Zude Zhou, Shane (Shengquan) Xie and Dejun Chen, Fundamentals of Digital
            Manufacturing Science, Springer-Verlag London Limited,2012\n
        </item>
        <item>3</item>
        <item>NIL</item>
        <item>Introduction to metal cutting</item>
        <item>Tool nomenclature – Attributes of each tool nomenclature – Attributes of feed and tool
            nomenclature on surface roughness obtainable Orthogonal and oblique cutting - Mechanism
            of metal removal –Primary and secondary deformation shear zones Mechanism of chip
            formation – Types of chips, need and types of chip breakers – Merchant’s theory.
            Analysis of cutting forces in orthogonal cutting– Work done, power required (simple
            problems) Friction forces in metal cutting – development of cutting tool materials.
            Thermal aspects of machining -Tool wear and wear mechanisms. Factors affecting tool
            life– Economics of machining (simple problems) Cutting fluids
        </item>
        <item>General purpose machine tools </item>
        <item>Principle and operation of lathe –Types of lathes and size specification. Work holding
            parts of lathes and their functions – Main operations.
            Taper turning and thread cutting attachments Feeding mechanisms, Apron mechanisms
            Drilling Machines – Types – Work holding devices Tool holding devices – Drill machine
            operations Drilling machine tools – Twist drill nomenclature- cutting forces in
            drilling.
        </item>
        <item>Reciprocating machines</item>
        <item>Shaping machines – Types – Size –Principal parts – Mechanism Work holding devices –
            operations performed – Tools
            Cutting speed, feed and depth of cut – Machining time. Slotting machines – Types – Size
            – principal parts – Mechanism –Work holding devices
            Operations performed – Tools – Cutting speed, feed and depth of cut
            Planing machines – Types – Size – Principal parts – Mechanism –
            Work holding devices
            Operations performed – Tools – Cutting speed, feed and depth of cut – Machining time-
            Surface roughness obtainable.

        </item>
        <item>Milling machines</item>
        <item>Types – Principal parts – Milling mechanism Work holding devices – Milling machine
            attachments Types of milling cutters – Elements of plain milling cutters
            Nomenclature - Cutting forces in milling – Milling cutter materials Up milling, down
            milling and face milling operations Calculation of machining time Indexing – Simple
            indexing – Differential indexing
        </item>
        <item>Grinding machines</item>
        <item>Classification – Operations – Surface,cylindrical and centreless grinding
            Grinding mechanisms – Grinding wheels: Specification – types of abrasives, grain size
            Types of bond, grade, structure – Marking system of grinding wheels – Selection of
            grinding wheels
            Glazing and loading of wheels – Dressing and Truing of grinding wheels, surface
            roughness obtainable
            Superfinishing operations: Lapping operation– Types of hand lapping – Lapping machines –
            Types of honing –Methods of honing Types of honing stones – Honing conditions – Cutting
            fluids –Types of broaches – Force required for broaching – Surface roughness obtainable
            in lapping, honing and broaching operations. Semi-automatic machine tools – Turret and
            capstan lathes. Automatic machine tools – Single and multi-spindle machines
        </item>
        <item>Introduction to Digital Manufacturing</item>
        <item>Concepts and research and development status of digital manufacturing
            Definition of digital manufacturing – Features and development of digital manufacturing.
            Theory system of digital manufacturing science: Operation Mode and Architecture of
            Digital Manufacturing System
            Operation reference mode of digital manufacturing system –Architecture of digital
            manufacturing system Modeling theory and method of digital manufacturing science
            Critical modeling theories and technologies of digital manufacturing science
            Theory system of digital manufacturing science – Basic architecture model of digital
            manufacturing system.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me305">
        <item>CP</item>
        <item>
            1. Balagurusamy, Computer Programming 1e McGraw Hill Education , 2013\n
            2. Balagurusamy, Numerical Methods 1e McGraw Hill Education, 1999\n
            3. Jose S., Computer Programming and Numerical Methods, Pentagon, 2015.\n
            4. Ravichandran D., Programming with C++, Tata McGraw Hill, 2007.\n
        </item>
        <item>3</item>
        <item>NIL</item>
        <item>Introduction to Computer programming concept</item>
        <item>Internal representation of data - Algorithm and flow chart, Basics of procedure
            oriented and object oriented programming. Introduction to C++: Structure of C++ program;
            Keywords; Identifiers; Data types – integer, real, character, string, boolean,
            enumeration, Constant and Variables; Operators – assignment, arithmetic, relational,
            logical, increment, decrement and conditional operators;Statements – simple &amp;
            compound, declaration statements. Input and output streams.
        </item>
        <item>Control statements</item>
        <item>if, if-else, switch, for, while, do-while, break and continue statements, Arrays – one
            dimensional &amp; two dimensional; Functions: inline functions, function over loading,
            Functions
            with default arguments, recursion
        </item>
        <item>Basics of Pointers.</item>
        <item>Function call by value, call by reference. Preparation of programs for evaluation of
            Factorial of a number, infinite series, Sorting, Searching and Matrix multiplication
        </item>
        <item>Introduction to Class and Object</item>
        <item>Definition, data members, member function. private &amp; public member functions,
            member access, friend declaration, class objects, predefined classes, initialization.
            Inheritance- base class and derived class. Simple programs using the above features. (No
            programming questions for University examination and internals)
        </item>
        <item>Errors and approximations</item>
        <item>Sources of errors. Solution of linear system of equations: Gauss elimination,
            Gauss-Jordan and Gauss–Seidel methods. Interpolation: Lagrange and Aitken techniques.
        </item>
        <item>Curve fitting</item>
        <item>Method of least squares, non-linear relationships, Linear correlation, measures of
            correlation. Solution of Partial differential equations: classification, Laplace
            equation, Finite difference method. Numerical problems and preparation of computer
            programs for the above methods
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me361">
        <item>AFM</item>
        <item>
            1. Bansal R. K., A Text Book of Fluid Mechanics and Machines, Laxmi Publications,
            2010.\n
            2. Douglas J. F., Fluid Mechanics, Pearson Education, 2005.\n
            3. Kumar D. S., Fluid Mechanics and Fluid Power Engineering, S. K. Kataria &amp; Sons,
            1987.\n
            4. Muralidhar K., G. Biswas, Advanced Engineering Fluid Mechanics, Alpha Science
            International limited, 2005.\n
            5. Rama D. D., Fluid Mechanics and Machines, New Age International, 2009\n
        </item>
        <item>3</item>
        <item>ME203 Mechanics of fluids</item>
        <item>Basic Concepts and Fundamentals</item>
        <item>Fluid statics, Cartesian Tensors, Fluid Kinematics, and Description of fluid motion
            –Types of motion of fluid elements, Vorticity and circulation– Concept of rotational and
            irrotational flows. Equation of motion of forced and free vortex flow.
            Stream function and Potential function. Stream function and its relation with velocity
            field. Relation between stream function and stream lines - Relation between stream
            function
            and velocity potential for a 2-D irrotational and incompressible flow.
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Relation between stream lines and lines of constant potential. Sketching of stream
            lines. Lagrangian and Eulerian approaches, acceleration, temporal acceleration,
            convective acceleration. Reynolds transport theorem, derivation of continuity and
            momentum equations using Reynolds transport theorem. Problems on the application of
            momentum equation
        </item>
        <item>Potential flow</item>
        <item>Uniform flow, source flow, sink flow, free vortex flow and super imposed flow-source
            and sink pair,doublet, plane source in a uniform flow(flow past a half body), source and
            sink pair in a uniform flow(flow past a Rankine oval body), doublet in a uniform
            flow(flow past a circular cylinder). Pressure distribution on the surface of the
            cylinder. Flow past a cylinder with Circulation, Kutta-Juokowsky’s law. Complex flow
            potential, complex flow potentials for source, sink, vortex and doublet. Potential flow
            between two parallel plates, potential flow in a sector. Introduction to conformal
            transformation, conformal mapping.
        </item>
        <item>MODULE 4</item>
        <item>Incompressible viscous flow. Concepts of laminar and turbulent flows . Stokes
            viscosity law. Navier Stoke’s equation and significance (Derivation not
            necessary).Simplification of Havier stock equation for steady incompressible flows with
            negligible body forces. Parallel flow through straight channel and couette flow. Hagen -
            Poiseuille flow. Derivation of Hagen Poissuille equations for velocity and discharge
            through a pipe, derivation of friction factor for laminar flow, Couette flow for
            negative, zero and positive pressure gradients, flow in a rotating annulus, Viscometer
            based on rotating annulus
        </item>
        <item></item>
        <item>Boundary layer theory, Boundary layer thickness, Displacement thickness, momentum
            thickness, Energy thickness and their calculation. Laminar Boundary Layers,Boundary
            layer equations; Boundary layer on a flat plate, Prandtl boundary layer equations,
            Blasius solution for flow over a flat plate, Von- Karman momentum integral equations,
            Pohlhausen approximation solution of boundary layer for non-zero pressure gradient flow,
            favorable and adverse pressure gradients, Entry flow into a duct, flow separation and
            vortex shedding.

        </item>
        <item>Turbulent Flow</item>
        <item>Introduction to turbulent flow, Governing equations of turbulent flow, Turbulent
            boundary layer equation, Flat plate turbulent boundary layer, Fully developed Turbulent
            pipe flow for moderate Reynold’s number, Prandtl mixing hypothesis, Turbulence modeling.
            Boundary layer control.
        </item>
    </array>


    <array name="me363">

        <item>COMPOSITE MATERIALS AND MECHANICS</item>

        <item>CMM</item>

        <item>1. K. K. Chawla, Composite Materials : Science and Engineering, Springer, 3e, 2013.\n
            2. Reddy J N (Ed.), Mechanics of Composite Materials; Selected Works of Nicholas J.
            Pagano,
            Springer, 1994\n
            3. Robert M. Jones, Mechanics of Composite Materials, CRC Press, 1998\n
        </item>

        <item>3</item>

        <item>NIL</item>

        <item>Composite</item>

        <item>Introduction, definition, characteristics, functions classification of composites
            based on structure and matrix smart composites, advantages and limitations history,
            industrial scene and applications Interfaces: wettability and bonding interface in
            composites
            types of bonding at interface.
        </item>

        <item>Fibers</item>

        <item>Introduction, types of fibers, natural fibers glass fiber fabrication, structure,
            properties and applications boron fiber fabrication, structure, properties and
            applications carbon fiber, Ex-Pan carbon fiber Ex cellulose carbon fiber, Ex-Pitch
            carbon carbon fiber structure, properties and applications aramid fiber fabrication,
            structure, properties and applications whiskers: characteristics, properties and
            applications
        </item>

        <item>Polymer matrix composites </item>

        <item>Thermoset, thermoplastic and elastomeric polymers properties, characteristics and
            applications as matrix materials processing of polymer matrix composites: hand methods,
            Lay up method, spray up method moulding methods, pressure bagging and bag moulding
            methods, pultrusion and filament winding process.
        </item>

        <item>Metal matrix composites (MMC)</item>

        <item>Classification of metals, intermetallics, alloys and their potential role as matrices
            in composites properties, characteristics and applications of metals as matrix materials
            production techniques: powder metallurgy, diffusion bonding, melt stirring squeeze
            casting, liquid infiltration under pressure, spray code position, insitu process.
        </item>

        <item>Ceramic matrix composites (CMC)</item>

        <item>Classification of ceramics and their potential role as matrices,properties,
            characteristics and applications of ceramics as matrix materials conventional techniques
            : cold pressing and sintering, hot pressing,reaction bonding,hot pressing and reaction
            bonding new techniques : liquid infiltration, pultrusion, lanxide process, insitu
            chemical technique, sol-gel technique
        </item>

        <item>Post processing operations</item>

        <item>Machining, cutting, polishing, welding, rivetting and painting Advanced post
            processing methods : ultrasonic welding, plasma coating, Water jet cutting and laser
            machining Micromechanics of composites: maximum stress and strain
            criterion(derivations)Tsai-Hill and Tsai-Wu failure criterion (derivations)mechanics of
            load transfer from matrix to fiber (description)
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="me365">

        <item>Advanced Metal Casting</item>

        <item>AMC</item>

        <item>1. A.K.Chakrabarti, Casting Technology and Cast Alloys, Prentice –Hall Of India Ltd,
            2005\n
            2. Beely, Foundry Technology, Newnes-Butterworths, 1979\n
            3. Gruzleski, The Treatment of Liquid Aluminum-Silicon Alloys, the American
            Foundrymen’s Society Inc, USA, 1992\n
            4. Heine, Loper and Rosenthal, Principle of Metal Casting, 2
            Edition, Tata Mc-Graw-Hill Publishing Company Limited, New Delhi, 1978\n
            5. John Cambell, Casting, Butterworth-Heineman Ltd, Jordon Hill, Oxford, 1991\n
            6. T.V.Rama Rao, Metal casting Principles and Practice, New Age International,2010\n
            7. Gruzleski, The Treatment of Liquid Aluminum-Silicon Alloys, the American\n
            Foundrymen’s Society Inc, USA, 1992.\n
        </item>

        <item>3</item>

        <item>NIL</item>

        <item>Design of molds</item>

        <item>Functional requirements of molding materials, type of sands Properties of molding
            sand, sand testing techniques Effect of molding on sand properties, Bonding material
            Mould surface coating Sand design and control Thermal aspect of molding sand, mould wall
            movement

        </item>

        <item>Pouring and feeding Gating
        </item>

        <item>Type of gating- gating design Factor involved in gating design-illustrative problems
            in determination of filling time and discharge rate Aspiration effect- effects of
            friction and velocity distribution
            Risers – primary function of a riser Theoretical consideration Riser design and
            placement Determination of dimensions of rise- blind risers Internal risers-use of
            chills Use of insulators and exothermic compound

        </item>

        <item>Solidification</item>

        <item>Freezing of pure metal Skin effects- nucleation and growth Shrinkage- freezing of
            alloys Effect of mould materials and alloy composition on casting Fluidity- factor
            affecting fluidity- fluidity measurement and application of fluidity Gases in metals-
            degassing Grain refinement Illustrative problems related to determination of
            solidification time
        </item>

        <item>Heat transfer during solidification</item>

        <item>Methods of manipulating heat transfer Experimental methods for the study of heat
            transfer during solidification Crystal growth methods Heat flow in solidification Heat
            transfer with in the solid/liquid metal system Heat transfer at the metal-mould
            interface Heat flow in one dimensional solidification geometries Freezing at mould wall
            Rapid freezing in contact with a cold substrate with initial melt super cooling
        </item>

        <item>Ferrous and non ferrous castings Steel Casting
        </item>

        <item>The family of cast iron Melting of steels and cast irons–Grey iron Foundry practice –
            ductile iron – Malleable Iron casting design
            Aluminum and its alloys: Different Aluminum alloy systems
            Advantage and limitation of Aluminum alloy castings Molding for aluminum castings -
            melting of Aluminum- degassing- grain refinement Modification- effect of various melt
            treatment on the
            mechanical properties of Aluminum castings.
            Magnesium and its alloys: different alloy systems- advantage and limitation of Magnesium
            alloy castings Molding for magnesium casting- melting of Magnesium-
            flux and flux less melting Type and functions of fluxes used- degassing and grain
            refinement- pouring technique.
            Copper alloys: advantage of Copper alloys- melting- drossing-oxygen and hydrogen in
            Copper melting- control of gases- de oxidation

        </item>

        <item>Casting defects and testing</item>

        <item>Functional design- metallurgical design simplification of foundry practice- economic
            considerations design of junction- specification of castings inspection of castings-
            analysis of casting defects nondestructive testing of casting- dye penetrant testing
            magnetic flaw detection, radiography, ultrasonic testing,etc.quality control and quality
            assurance
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="me367">

        <item>Non-Destructive Testing</item>

        <item>NDT</item>

        <item>Baldev Raj, Practical Non – Destructive Testing, Narosa Publishing House ,1997</item>

        <item>3</item>

        <item>NIL</item>

        <item>Introduction to NDT</item>

        <item>Comparison between destructive and NDT,Importance of NDT, Scope of NDT, difficulties
            of NDT, future progress in NDT, economics aspects of NDT.
            Visual Inspection - tools, applications and limitations -Fundamentals of visual testing:
            vision, lighting, material attributes,environmental factors.visual perception, direct
            and indirect methods mirrors, magnifiers,boroscopes, fibroscopes, closed circuit
            television, light sources special lighting, a systems, computer enhanced system
        </item>

        <item>Liquid Penetrant Inspection</item>

        <item> Principles, properties required for a good penetrants and developers - Types of
            penetrants and developers and advantages and limitations of various methods of LPI – LPI
            technique/ test procedure interpretation and evaluation of penetrant test indications,
            false indication and safety precaution required in LPI, applications, advantages and
            limitations

        </item>

        <item>Magnetic Particle Inspection (MPI)</item>

        <item>Principles of MPI, basic physics of magnetism, permeability, flux density, cohesive
            force, magnetizing force, rentivity, residual magnetism Methods of magnetization,
            magnetization techniques such as headshot technique, cold shot technique, central
            conductor testing,magnetization using products using yokes direct and indirect method of
            magnetization, continuous testing of MPI, residual technique of MPI, system sensitivity,
            checking devices in MPI Interpretation of MPI, indications, advantage and limitation of
            MPI.
        </item>

        <item>Ultrasonic Testing</item>

        <item>Principle, types of waves, frequency,velocity, wavelength, reflection, divergence,
            attenuation, mode conversion in ultrasonic UT testing methods contact testing and
            immersion testing, normal beam and straight beam testing, angle beam testing, dual
            crystal probe, ultrasonic testing techniques resonance testing, through transmission
            technique, pulse echotesting technique, instruments used UT, accessories such as
            transducers, types, frequencies, and sizes commonly used. Reference blocks with
            artificially created defects, calibration of equipment, Applications, advantages,
            limitations, A, B and C scan- Time of Flight Diffraction (TOFD).
        </item>

        <item>Radiography Testing</item>

        <item>Principle, electromagnetic radiation sources: X-ray source, production of X-rays, high
            energy X-ray source, gamma ray source - Properties of X-rays and gamma rays Inspection
            techniques like SWSI, DWSI, DWDI, panoramic exposure, real time radiography, films used
            in industrial radiography, types of film, speed of films, qualities of film screens used
            in radiography, quality of a good radiograph, film processing, interpretation,
            evaluation of test results, safety aspects required in radiography applications,
            advantages and limitations of RT
        </item>

        <item>Eddy Current Testing (ECT)</item>

        <item>Principle, physics aspects of ECT like conductivity, permeability, resistivity,
            inductance, inductive reactance, impedance Field factor and lift of effect, edge effect,
            end effect, impedance plane diagram in brief, depth of penetration of ECT, relation
            between frequency and depth of penetration in ECT equipments and accessories, various
            application of ECT such as conductivity measurement, hardness measurement, defect
            detection coating thickness measurement, advantages and limitations of eddy current
            testing
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="me369">
        <item>Tribology</item>

        <item>1. Ernest Rabinowicz, Friction and Wear of Materials, John Wiley &amp; sons,1995
            2. I.M. Hutchings, Tribology: Friction and Wear of Engineering Materials, Butterworth-
            Heinemann,1992
            3. Prasanta Sahoo, Engineering Tribology, PHI Learning Private Ltd, New Delhi, 2011
        </item>

        <item>3</item>

        <item>NIL</item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Introduction to Tribology- Tribology in Design, Tribology in Industry, Economic
            Aspects of Tribology Tribological Parameters Like Friction, Wear and Lubrication The
            Topography of Engineering Surface, Contact Between Surfaces.Types of Bearings,
            Comparison of Sliding and Rolling Contact Bearings.
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Introduction, Empirical Laws of Friction, Kinds of Friction Causes of Friction,
            Theories of Friction Measurement of Friction Friction of Metals, Ceramic Materials,
            Polymers.Rolling Friction- Laws of Rolling Friction, Relation Between Temperature and
            Friction Stick-Slip, Prevention of Stick-Slip, Consequences of Friction
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Types of Wear, Various Factors Affecting Wear Theories of Wear, Wear Mechanisms
            Measurement of Wear.Wear Regime Maps, Alternative Form of Wear Equations Lubricated and
            Unlubricated Wear of Metals, Materials Used in Different Wear Situations.
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Fundamentals of Viscosity And Viscous Flow Principle and Application of;
            Hydrodynamic Lubrication, Elastrodynamic Lubrication, Boundary and Solid
            Lubrication.Types of Lubricants, Properties of Lubricants Effect of Speed and Load on
            Lubrication, Frictional Polymers.Lubrication in Metal Working: Rolling, Forging, Drawing
            and Extrusion.
        </item>

        <item>Adhesion</item>

        <item>Introduction, Adhesion Effect by Surface Tension, Purely Normal Contact and
            Compression Plus Shear Adhesion in Magnetic Recording Systems Dependence of Adhesion on
            Material and Geometric Properties.
            Bearing Materials: Introduction, Rolling Bearing, Fluid Film Lubricated Bearing, Dry
            Bearing, Bearing Constructions.

        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Introduction To Surface Engineering, Concept and Scope of Surface Engineering.Surface
            Modification – Transformation Hardening, Surface Melting, Thermo chemical Processes
            Surface Coating – Plating and Anoding Processes, Fusion Processes, Vapor Phase
            Processes.Selection of Coating For Wear And Corrosion Resistance,Potential Properties
            and Parameters of Coating
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="me371">


        <item>NE</item>

        <item>1. S. Glasstone and A. Sesonske, Nuclear Reactor Engineering, D. Van Nostrand
            Company,\n
            INC. 1967.
            2. S Glasstone, Source book on atomic energy, Krieger Pub Co., 1979\n
        </item>

        <item>3</item>

        <item>NIL</item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Review of Elementary nuclear physics: Atomic structure – nuclear energy and nuclear
            forces – Nuclear fission. Nuclear reactions and radiations – Principles of radioactive
            decay interactions of an ray with matter – Neutron cross sections and reactions –The
            fission process – Chain reactions
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Basic principles of controlled fusion .Nuclear reactor principles –Reactor
            classification – Critical size. Basic diffusion theory -Slowing down of neutrons –
            Neutrons – Neutron flux and power –Four factor formula – Criticality condition – Basic
            features of reactor control 
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Boiling water reactor . Description of reactor system – Main components –Control and
            safety features .Materials of reactor construction – Fuel , moderator , coolant
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Structural materials – Cladding –Radiation damage,Nuclear fuels : Metallurgy of
            Uranium – General principles of solvent extraction – Reprocessing of irradiated fuel –
            eparation process fuel enrichment .
        </item>

        <item></item>

        <item>Reactor heat removal / equations of heat transfer as applied to reactor cooling–
            Reactor heat transfer systems – Heat removed in fast reactors. Radiation safety :
            Reactor shielding – Radiation dozes – Standards of radiation protection
        </item>

        <item></item>
        <item>Safety and disposal: Nuclear plant safety-safety systems-changes and consequences of
            accident-criteria for safety-nuclear waste- types of waste and its disposal-radiation
            hazards and their prevention-weapons proliferation
        </item>

    </array>


    <array name="me373">


        <item>HRM</item>

        <item>1. Gary Dessler, Human Resource Management., Pearson Education, 2017\n
            2. Seema Sanghi , Stephen P. Robbins, , Timoti A Judge : Organizational Behaviour,
            Pearson
            Education, 2009\n
        </item>

        <item>3</item>

        <item>NIL</item>

        <item>Human Behaviour</item>

        <item>Biological characteristics, age, gender, tenure.Ability, intellectual and physical
            abilities. Learning, theories of learning.Values, importance of values, types.
            Attitudes, types, attitudes and
            consistency, workforce diversity. Personality and emotions, personality determinants and
            traits, emotion dimensions. Perception, factors influencing perception, making judgement
            about others, link betweenperception and individual decision making
        </item>

        <item>Human Behaviour and Relations in Groups</item>

        <item>Defining and classifying different groups. Stages of group development, Five stage
            model. Group structure, roles, norms, status and size. Group decision making, group
            versus the individual. Types of teams, self-managed work teams, problem solving teams.
            Creating effective teams, composition, work design, process and team players.
        </item>

        <item>Management of Human Relations in Organisations</item>

        <item>Ethics and fair treatment at work, ethics and the law, ethics fair treatment and
            justice. Ethical behaviour at work, individual factors, organizational factors, the
            boss’s influence, ethics policies and codes, the organization’s culture, role of HR in
            fostering ethics and fair treatment. Disciplining an employee, formal disciplinary
            appeals process, discipline without punishment, employee privacy.
        </item>

        <item>Management of Human Laws and Collective Bargaining</item>

        <item>Employment law, gross misconduct, personal supervisory liability, layoffs and the
            plant closing law. Collective bargaining, good faith, negotiating team, bargaining
            items, bargaining stages, bargaining hints, impasses, mediation, and strikes, the
            contract agreement. Grievances, sources of grievances, the grievance procedure,
            guidelines for handling grievances.
        </item>

        <item>Management of Training and Employer-Employee Relations</item>

        <item>Training and development, objectives, strategies, methods and techniques. Design and
            organisation of training and evaluation of training. Employee relations,
            management-employee relations, managing discipline, grievance and stress, counselling,
            are handling problem employees. Industrial relations implications of personnel policies,
            nature of employment relationship
        </item>

        <item>Management of Human Conflicts, Customer Relations, Unions and Global Relations
        </item>

        <item>Industrial and organisational conflict, managing for good industrial relations and
            managing the moment of conflict. Customer relationship management, what if customer is
            the problem. Place of unions in organizations. The future scenario, the changing
            personnel management scenario. Managing global human relations. HRD the development role
            of personnel to the force. Employee safety and health
        </item>

    </array>

</resources>